[Music]
[Applause]
my
[Music]
done
so
[Music]
hello everybody and welcome you to react
native youth edition my name is mike and
i'm your host of react native eu so
welcome everybody to our stream we are
streaming out of words of poland and as
you can see this conference is happening
remotely this time as well just like one
year before now regardless of this fact
we want to make sure that you take
maximum out of it because networking and
sharing knowledge between each other is
what we think is the most important
aspect of react native you so despite
being remotely we put a lot of effort to
making sure that this will be easy for
you um to do so before we start with the
talks i do have a couple of informations
to tell you uh connected to the
networking part there is a discord
channel on our callstack server you can
find the link
down below you can join it and ask your
questions about the talks we will answer
them on our special react native show
podcast that will be published soon
after the conference you can also talk
with other participants you can share
your knowledge and experience within
each other based on the talks so just
log in there stay there and treat it as
your networking aspect just like we were
all here in poland in the same place in
broadsword
now also make sure to follow call stack
i on twitter and reacneview on twitter
and tweet react native eu
everything about the conference let your
friends know that we are live so that
they can join us and they will not miss
the first part of the conference which
will be very exciting like the entire
two days that are in front of us
you can also visit our react native eu
website where you can see the agenda all
the talks and in case you are busy you
can pick the ones that you want to
attend but worry not we will all we will
publish them to our youtube channel a
couple of days
or maybe weeks after the conference so
it's still better to be here with us so
you can have the first hand experience
and knowledge
straight from the speakers
we are organizing this conference here
as i said in our code stack office so as
you can probably assume callstack is the
organizer
now callstack is a team of super great
react native and react developers we are
doing very very interesting projects all
about cross-platform software so in case
you are here somewhere from around
poland or maybe from poland make sure to
apply or just let us know that you are
interested in changing your job we have
a lot of great interesting opportunities
for you and challenges that may
uh feel you like there is still a lot of
exciting projects in front of you
just one important information before we
start this conference is also co-hosted
by my friend from costa gucash so in
case you see somebody else not me
introducing you to another call today or
tomorrow
don't be afraid
everything's going okay we are doing
this together because there is just so
many great talks here today that i i
felt like it's going to be a good idea
to share some of that experience with
somebody else that calls stack that also
likes doing podcasting and conferences
so let's start with what you are all in
for here so the react native talks now
the first blog is a cross-platform and
architecture blog so in this part we
will be talking about the things that
are important to react native at a core
level so underlying building blocks and
some things that you may not hear
every day about but understanding them
and having full exposition to them will
make you feel like you can build even
more advanced apps so our first speaker
is mark from expo and he will be talking
about how jsi powers the most advanced
camera library out there for react
native now
of course he will be talking about the
camera library but one thing that you
may that you don't that you can't miss
out of this talk is that uh gsi is
something that is yet to be public and
open for everybody yet still
folks at xbar using it already for the
camera library so we are not only here
for a great talk about camera features
but also how jsi
is enabling you to do even more advanced
things so you can think about it as a
very very future proof talk something
that maybe next year or two years from
now will be what everybody will be
talking about so let's learn about how
they are using jsi and how their camera
library is working
hello everyone my name is mark and
welcome to my talk about vision camera
and jsi i will be splitting this talk
into two parts so in the first part
we're going to take a look at vision
camera as a library and how you can use
it in your app and we're going to create
a simpler object detector app using
frame processes
and the second part i will go over how
gsi works what json really is and how
you can create a simple fast and
synchronous library using jsi so let's
get right to it
so i've created a new react native
project and installed reanimated and
vision camera i've added some basic code
to request for camera permission so if
the user has not granted permission
we're going to display that
and if there is no device available
we're going to show a loading indicator
otherwise we can display the camera
let's take a look at how this looks for
now
and as you can see the camera is running
fine all right we have our camera
running how do we implement an image
label now
so let's first try to understand how
this works in native apps in a native
ios app you have to create your camera
session and then create a new instance
of the av capture video data output
class
then you can implement the capture
output delegate method and this method
gets called for every frame your camera
sees so for example if your camera is
running at 60fps this function gets
called 60 times a second with a new
frame
in there you can try to implement any
sort of processing you want you can use
this for facial recognition object
detection image labeling qr code
scanning and even upload the frames to
webrtc to create a real-time video chat
on android this is basically the same
story you create a new image analyzer
and this image analyzer gets called with
the new image every time the camera sees
a new image so for example in here you
might want to run your image labeling
object detection facial recognition or
webrtc uploading
okay we now understand how it works in a
native ios or native android app but
we're react native developers we're all
afraid of native code so how can we do
this in javascript
luckily mission camera provides an api
for this it's called frame processors so
just like the image analyzer or the
capture output delegate from your native
ios and android apps this function gets
called for every frame the camera sees
you can use the frame object to access
frame data
for example you can inspect the image
width or height properties for high
performance algorithms you can also
create native functions so you write a
few lines of native code and then
directly call them inside a javascript
frame processor for example the detect
is hotdog function is a native function
written in objective c or swift and java
or kotlin
let's take a look at how we can create a
simple frame processing
we're going to create a new variable
called frame processor and we're going
to use the use frame processor hope to
create a new frame processor inside the
use frame post is a function we have to
use the workload directive so let's add
it and let's just simply log something
to the console every time a new frame
arrives
all right let's add the frame processor
to the camera
let's hit save and test the change in
our console below we can now see that a
new frame arrives every time the frame
processor gets called which gets called
every second by default
we can also adjust this behavior by
passing frame processor fps and pass
some higher value which is 10 which gets
called 10 times a second
all right let's start creating our first
frame processor plugin a frame processor
plugin is a native function you can
write an objective c or swift or java or
kotlin
and you can directly and synchronously
call it from a frame processor for
example if we create a native function
that's called labor image we can call it
like this
label
so to create the native function let's
go ahead and open the project in xcode
all right let's start implementing the
plugin we're going to create an
interface and an implementation for the
plugin and then we're just going to
create a static inline function which is
called every time you call the plugin so
for example in this case i'm calling it
labor image and the function receives a
frame as well as any arguments passed
through the function
we're going to export it to make it
available in division camera runtime
using the vision export frame processor
macro let's go ahead and start
implementing the labor image algorithm
we're going to use ml kit for this and
the ml kit has an api where we can label
images we need to add the library to our
pod file and then run pod install
and then we're going to create an mlk
vision image instance
and assign an orientation after we've
created this you have to create an mlk
image label instance which is
responsible for labeling images
then you can use the process image
function to process an image let's try
it we're going to create an mlk image
label instance which is going to be a
static instance we're going to reuse
and then we're going to create a new mnk
vision image instance we're going to
initialize it with the frame buffer as
you can see here we use the frame and
we're going to set the orientation to
the frame orientation
then we're going to scan for labors in
this case we're using the results and
image function which is synchronous
using the labels we can now initialize a
new array and fill in the labels
so in this case we're creating an ns
mutable array
i'm going to call it results and then
we're going to iterate over each label
in this array and assign it to this
array
then we just return it all right that's
it that's all of the native code you
need for frame processor plugin
let's go ahead and create the javascript
site now i'm going to create a new file
called label image
in this file i'm going to export a new
function called label image
i have to use the workload directive so
it can be called from revision camera
runtime
then as we learned earlier the function
now exists in a vision camera runtime
prefix with two underscores
so i'm just going to call it like this
lastly we need to add it to the bubble
runtime
so open your bubble conflict and then
find the line where the reanimated
plugin is added we just need to add a
new configuration to it
and pass it in as a global variable
that's all you need to do now restart
your metro bundler
and you can simply call it function
we're going to import it
now let's try just logging all image
layers
so let's start the app and take a look
as you can see the frame processor
plugin gets called and we're logging all
of the labels to the console
all right now that we know how to use
frame processors let's take a look at
how jsi works we're going to create a
simple jsi library and afterwards we're
going to look into more advanced
examples such as the jsi host object and
how vision camera uses jsi to provide
all of this functionality let me start
by explaining what jsi really is i'm
sure all of you already know that react
native uses a bridge for communication
between javascript and native
since the javascript runtime runs in a
very isolated context there's not a lot
of things you can do in it
sure you can create functions create
numbers add numbers create strings
create objects and stuff like that but
what if you wanted to access the device
name or the phone's ip address
those things are available for
platform-specific apis so api is written
in objective-c or swift and java
as with most programming languages out
there you cannot automatically and
direct your car into another programming
language there always has to be some
sort of communication layer in between
for example in java you can call into
native c or c plus plus code using jni
the java native interface to call c plus
plus aks in swift you have to manually
create a bridge using c or objective c
which acts as a communication layer in
between
in c sharp you have to reference the
function's name and the dll it lives in
so that's why the react native bridge
was invented it provided a tunnel to
send messages between native and
javascript if you wanted to find out the
ip address you have to send a message
like get ip address to the native word
the native word receives that message
finds out the actual ip address and then
sends back another message with ip
address in it javascript receives that
message and now javascript has a value
which contains the ip address which is a
string
this is of course not an ideal solution
since the bridge uses a batching system
and the message is not immediately sent
but rather patched with other messages
at some later points in time all of the
messages are then sent to native
also there's a lot of serialization
going on here which is done in the json
format so you cannot send a number to
the native function it has to be
converted to a string adjacent first as
you can imagine that's really slow okay
so
what's the solution well since our
javascript run times javascript core
hermes v8 are written in c or c plus
plus
some very smart people invented a c plus
api called jsi jsi is an abstraction
layer over virtually any javascript
runtime it works the same for javascript
core for hermes 4v8 and any other
runtimes that might implement jsi so if
you know object-oriented programming you
can think of it like an interface which
is exactly what it is it is functions
defined which the randoms increment for
example you can create a javascript
number straight out of sql squares okay
but let's take a look at some actual
code
so in javascript we can create numbers
by using the assignment operator in this
case the variable number stores the
value 42.
let's see how we can create this in c
plus plus in c plus plus we use the jsi
value constructor to create a new value
called number we can also use this
equals plus which holds the value 42
this variable can directly be passed to
javascript either by passing it as a
parameter or by citing it as a property
on an object
let's try creating a string
in javascript we can again use the
assignment operator and two quotes
in c plus plus we also have to define
the encoding format so in this case it's
utf-8 and we have to pass the runtime
again the value name exists in the cpus
plus password so we can directly run
some operations or functions on it now
let's take a look at functions
let's create a function which just adds
two numbers together we're going to call
this function add
in javascript we can again use the
assignment operator and create an
anonymous function this function has
first and second together and returns
the result
in c plus plus
we have to create a jsi function which
creates a new function from the host
function a host function is a function
which actually lives in the host
environment so in a native world
this function contains c plus code but
can be directly called from javascript
we have to pass the runtime we have to
pass the prop name which will be add in
our case we have to specify the number
of parameters in this case it's two the
first or the second number and then we
can create a c plus plus lambda and then
on this first argument is the round term
the second argument is this way so you
can bind a function to another base
value
the third argument is an array a c style
array of all arguments passed to the
function
for example on the first position there
would be the first number on the second
position there will be a second number
and the count parameter specifies how
many arguments were actually passed to
the function in our case this will be 2.
then the lambda returns a json value you
always have to return a jsi value and if
you don't want to return anything you
have to return the gsi value of undefend
so in this case we're casting the first
argument to a number then casting a
second argument to a number and add it
all together then we return a new jsi
value of the result numbers in jsi are
always doubles
let's try calling this function in
javascript we will simply use add and
pass two parameters this function add
can either be the one we created in
javascript or the one we created in c
plus plus the host function we can call
both of them synchronously let's try
calling the same function from c plus
plus
again we have to have a reference to the
add function and then we can simply use
the call property to call the function
we have to pass the runtime and then all
the variation parameters we want to pass
so let's try adding this function to the
over next place in javascript we can
simply use global.add and then use the
assignment operator to assign this
property
in c plus we can use runtime.glober to
get the global property and then we can
use set property to set a new property
i won't go into detail about cpus plus
memory management but you have to move
the add function because there's no copy
operator for jsi values
so in this case if we set the add
function to the global namespace in the
javascript runtime we can directly call
it in javascript which we call the
native host function from here so if we
compare this to a bridge module now you
notice that this function no longer has
to be awaited this function is
completely synchronous so the result
returned in the host function can
directly be used in javascript
this value
holds the result we return here to do
this with a bridge function we have to
use a weight which cannot be used in a
top level javascript code so as you
might have already noticed this is the
benefit of providing a direct fast and
synchronous access to the javascript
runtime if we go back to our ipaddress
example we can now create a function c
plus that simply returns the ipads we
can then install this function in a
javascript runtime's global property and
then simply call this function we don't
have to use a weight anymore and the
function is directly called just like
any other javascript function also
there's no more serialization going on
because as we learned earlier all of the
javascript values can be directly
accessed in c plus so a javascript
number can be directly used in c plus as
a jsi value of type number for our ip
address this would be a jsi value of
type stream so let's take a look at the
ipa in this example we create a host
function in c plus which simply gets the
ap address from some platform specific
api for example from an objective c api
and that simply returns a jsi string
which contains the ipa risk we move this
function to the global namespace in
javascript and then in javascript we can
simply call it
so global now contains the get ipa
address function which is a host
function that exists in sql plus and you
can directly call it without using a
weight
this is how you would install a nav
function into the javascript router
so let's quickly recap jsi is a
replacement for the bridge while
currently both the bridge and json
exists in a recognitive project the
bridge will soon be completely removed
and every native module will use gsi
under the hood
jsa is faster than the bridge and jsi is
more powerful than the bridge by
providing a direct access to the
javascript content with the rich the
communication between javascript and
native was asynchronous remember the
batch message system so this means you
have to use a weight for every single
function you call even if that's an add
function which simply adds two numbers
together with jsi everything is
synchronous per default so you can use
it a top-level javascript code but don't
worry you can easily create promises to
make something a way to work if it's a
long running or an asynchronous test
since jsi accesses the javascript
runtime it is no longer possible to use
a remote debugger such as google chrome
instead you have to use flipper remember
jsi is just a replacement for the bridge
so only the underlying technology
changes in most cases you don't need to
use jsi directly or even sequels plus nr
the turbo modules api will be almost the
same as the native modules api so this
means for every native module that
exists today it will be very easy to
migrate to turbo modules without
rewriting the entire thing currently
there are three runtimes that implement
jsm javascript core which is the default
runtime for now hermes which might be
the default runtime sometimes in the
future and v8 also json does not
implement any sort of thread safety
logging
while jsi is ready it's a bit quirky to
get access to the javascript runtime at
the right point in time there are a few
hacks involved i will show you now
we'll take a look at my react native
mmkv library which provides a fast and
easy storage solution for react native
using jsi
it's about 30 times faster than async
storage and it is a really good example
for jsi since you benefit from better
performance as well as synchronous
access in top level javascript code
let's take a look at the project
structure first so compared to native
bridge modules there's currently no way
to auto link or automatically install a
jsi module
instead we have to go into our main
application.java find the react native
host instance we're creating and then
overwrite the get jsi module package
function in this function i'm going to
return a new mmkv module package
instance which is a class that
implements the jsi module package
interface let's take a look at it
as you can see the class implements the
jsi module package interface and
overrides the get jsi modules function
in this function you can return a list
of jsi module spec instances but we just
return an empty list why do we do this
well there's something special about
this function this function is actually
called on the javascript thread so since
this function is called in a javascript
thread before the javascript bundle
executes we can quickly install the mmkb
module into the global namespace
if we wanted to do that on another
thread for example in the native module
thread we would likely get an error at
runtime and the app simply crashes so
let's take a look at how the install
function works we're going to open the
mmkb module class which is still a java
class and as you can see here's the
install function which takes a
javascript context holder as a parameter
which is the jscontext
this is a java hybrid class and it
actually contains the javascript runtime
as a c plus instance but we cannot
access this in java right now so let's
take a look at how we can pass it to c
plus plus
we call the native install function
which is a jni function it's a native
function that exists in c plus but you
can directly call it from java this is
the first time we cross languages so in
this case we go from java to c plus plus
to implement the c plus function we have
to create a cmake and gradient setup i'm
not going to go over this right now but
you can take a look at this at github so
let's take a look at the native
installer function this function exists
in a c classifier
and as you can see here it is prefixed
with the full java namespace
so the first parameter is the jmi
environment then i'm going to get the
class which is the mmkv module then i'm
going to get the first parameter which
is a long in my case this is the pointer
to the javascript runtime and then i'm
getting a java string to the path where
mmkv stores all the documents
if we take a look at the java function
this is exactly what we defined here
so now in the cpus plus file i can now
reinterpret the javascript runtime
pointer to be an instance of the jsi
runtime so and if the cast succeeded we
can now install the actual functions
if the cards didn't succeed we're likely
not in an environment that supports jsi
for example if you use a different
runtime than the three runtimes are
listed earlier or if you're using a
chrome debugger so let's take a look at
the installer function the install
function receives a jsi runtime
reference
and i can use this reference to install
variables into the global namespace in
this case i'm installing the mmkv set
function in the global namespace so this
is a jsi host function as we saw earlier
which simply sets the value to the mmkv
storage instance as you can see you can
check the arguments for the types using
is4 this number is string and we can
also throw jsi errors at the end of the
function we always have to return a jsi
value and if we don't want to return any
value at all so no number no string no
object we can simply return undefined
and then here's the actual
implementation for mmkv where we simply
set the value to the default mmkd
instance in this case recording set and
getting the value if you want to convert
the jsi value to a number you can use as
number and you get a returning doubler
value same thing for booleans and for
strings there's a jsi string redwood so
as string will return a jsi
of course you can also convert the
string to an actual c plus string so an
std string using the dot utf-8 function
so let's take another look at frame
processes earlier we saw that we can
directly access the frame's width and
height properties and we can even
directly pass it to a native frame
processor plugin which by the way is a
host function
so how does this work what exactly is
the frame object how does it contain a
full 10 megabyte image from your camera
is it really slow to copy frames from
native to javascript for every frame the
camera sees which can happen up to 240
times a second well there's actually no
copy of serialization happening here the
frame parameter is actually a jsi host
object
this means the object has been created
in c plus but javascript can also
interact with it similar to how host
functions work so if i access
frame.height this actually resolves to
the c plus code and calls get property
on it so let's take a look at the shape
of the frame object i've created simple
typescript types for this which don't
contain any code or anything but we can
understand the shape better so for
example for the frame we have an is
valid width height bytes per row planes
count
properties and then we have two
functions two string and close
all of these properties actually do not
exist in javascript they all exist in c
plus let's take a look at how we defined
the host object so as you can see this
is the frame host object header
this is a c plus class which inherits
jsi host object
we can override those two methods to
provide information for the jsi host
object so you cannot directly use the
frame object in javascript because it's
an objective c object and javascript
doesn't know how to interact with it
instead we create a frame host object
which acts as an interaction layer
between the javascript frame instance
and the objective c frame object we
stored here so for example if we call
frame.height the get function gets
called with the name being height
and then we can simply access the frame
with objective c code to find out the
actual height of the frame and return it
as a jsi value a number
let's take a look at the implementation
so the get property names function
simply returns a list of all valid
properties this is useful if you want to
use object.keys on the frame which then
returns all of these keys so for example
tostring is valid with height bias perov
planes not enclosed get returned
then you can implement the get function
which acts as a getter so if you call
frame.height which is not a function
it's simply a property getter this
function gets called with the name being
height in our case we can then get the
height using an objective c api from cm
sampler buffer
then we can simply return the height as
a dauber using the jsi value constructor
so for every time you try to access
frame.height this is not a value stored
in javascript instead this c plus plus
code gets called if you try to access
some value that is not supported we just
return jsi value undefined the same
thing applies to the close and two
string functions for example for the
close function we have to create the
host function
and then return the host function so if
you access frame dot close
this function gets returned so then if
you try to actually call it so two
brackets
this function which is a host function
gets called as you can see all of this
exists in c plus and javascript only
provides an interaction layer by using
the host object instance you can find
all of this code online on github at the
vision camera repository
so let's start creating our own custom
hall subject
i'm going to create a class in c plus
i'm going to call it example host object
and we're going to inherit from jsi host
object
then we have to overwrite the functions
get and get property names
so in this case we have to add get
property names and overwrite the
signature is always the same from jsi
host object
and now we start by implementing get
property names you have to return a
vector of all property names that you
can access in the host object this is
useful if you want to access object.keys
on the given object
so in our case we're just going to add
some value
in this case we have to create a prop
name id and give it a string of some
value
now let's start implementing the get
function
so now let's try to find out what the
user actually wants to access you can
use
name.utf8 to actually get an std string
value for the past prop name id
with the std string stored in the name
variable we can now work
let's find out if the user actually
tried to access some value
we simply compare name to some value and
if it's true we can return some value in
this case i'm going to return the lucky
number 13 but you can also return an
object a string a boolean whatever
so let's look into some other value
types first we can try returning a
boolean
so if the property sum bool is accessed
we simply return true
next let's try returning a string
if the value some string is accessed we
create a new string from a utf-8 scd
string in our case hello let's try
something more complex we try to build
an object with two values some value and
some bold so we create a new object
using the jsi object constructor then we
can simply use set property to set some
values some value is set to jsi value of
and some bore will have the property
true
then we can simply return the object
let's try building an array if the value
sum arrays exist we build an array with
two elements inside since we already
know the size of the array we can simply
pass it to the jsi array constructor
now let's try inserting the values and
simply returning them
now in this case this should be one
instead of zero but you get the idea
now let's try creating another host
object
let's try creating a new instance of the
example host object so in this case
we're creating a new shared pointer of
the example host object using the
default constructor and then we can use
jsi object create from host object to
create a new host object
next let's try creating a host function
host functions look very complex at
first but in reality they're really easy
so the first step is to create a c plus
landlord you have a capture list of all
values that get captured in the lambda
and then you have four parameters the
runtime we're currently using
the this value of the function if the
functions bound to any specific this
value a sees that array of all arguments
and a property defining how many
arguments are actually passed so how big
this cra is then you return a jsi value
which is undefined if you don't want to
return anything or any other gsi value
if you want to return something in our
case let's just add the first and the
second argument together so it's a
simple add function
we're getting the first argument as a
number and adding the second argument as
a number two then the result is a number
we can create a new json value from the
doubler and return it now we still only
have a c plus plus lambda and not a jsi
function yet so to create a jsi function
you have to use the create from host
function
you have to pass the runtime and then
you have to pass a prop name id which is
in this case just fine
then you can specify the number of
parameters that will get used for this
function in this case it's two we're
expecting two parameters the first and
the second number and then you're simply
passing the c plus plus lambda
in most cases you want to move this so
std move
and then we simply return the function
then you can also access the global
namespace so anything that's defined in
the global namespace can be accessed by
using runtime.global for example you
might want to create a host function
that can be called from javascript and
it performs some asynchronous tasks on a
new thread such as uploading something
to a server
to make it a waitable in the javascript
world you can create a new promise
by accessing runtime.global getproperty
as function and then simply get the
promise property which is a function
remember all constructors in javascript
are simple functions
so then we call the promis constructor
as a constructor and then you have to
pass in a jsi function which is a host
function which then can resolve or
reject the promise
this promise object can then be returned
to javascript and your code can execute
inside the lambda you passed in here
then as soon as your upload is complete
on the other thread you can simply call
the resolver and the code that is
awaiting in javascript can then continue
executing
there's also another json value type
that's not directly included in the json
implementation and that's the array
buffer and expo gl implements this as a
typed array as you can see here so if
you have a large data buffer in the
native code converting into a jsi array
by looping over it and pushing element
by element
um will probably make you hit an out of
memory error or you're or you're going
to notice serious performance problems
instead you can use the typed array
implementation to quickly make the offer
available to the javascript world you
create a new typed array by using one of
the available types array types which
are the sizes of the types so 8-bit
integer 16-bit integer 32-bit integer
and so on
and then return it to js this is faster
because under the hood only a simple man
copy operation happens as opposed to
looping over the entire thing and
pushing a new jsi value into the array
each time
and this is also more memory efficient
because as we heard earlier jsi values
are always shortest hours with the only
exception being a typed array so an
array buffer so if you're dealing with
anything smarter than a 64-bit double
for example a 32-bit integer a
six-simple integer or an 8-bit integer
the five-dollar implementation actually
only allocates that amount of memory so
for example for one double you could
actually allocate eight eight bit
integers so this means if you have a one
megabyte array of eight-bit integers
this would actually be 8 megabytes in
size if you use a normal jsi array
with the typed array kind of type 8
array it would stay at 1 megabyte
so now that we finally understand how
jsi works it's about time it's already
hard outside we can take a look at how
vision camera uses jsi to provide the
frame processing feature
first of all why can't we not use the
bridge for this there are multiple
reasons for this first since the bridge
sends messages in json format we cannot
pass the entire camera frame to
javascript that would be a 10 megabyte
json for each frame and it will simply
not be fast enough to run this 30 60 or
even 240 times a second
second we would have to pass the json
back to the native world for every time
we want to call a frame processor plugin
this would be twice the same with the
bridge since we go from native to
javascript and then javascript back to
native but with jsi this has almost no
overhead at all third all of this json
conversion would be blocking the
javascript thread so any state updates
navigations or re-renders will be run
with jsi we can use really make this
worklet api to spawn a secondary
javascript runtime and run all of this
code in parallel and uninterrupt it to
the react.js runtime so this is how the
frame processor gets created inside the
frame processor we create a new instance
of the j image proxy host object which
is the frame from the j image proxy
then we simply call the function which
is frame processor by passing in the
host object
i'm not going to go into much detail as
to how to work that aka from reanimated
works
this is a topic for a whole other talk
but if you really want to know how it
works i highly recommend you to read the
source code of the animated basically
that uses jsi to copy all values
captured in a function in a worklet and
i call it workflow function with the
capture variables
this means all of the captured variables
used inside the worklet are actually
only copies of the original objects so
if you want to make changes to an object
you
is frozen
also for the frame processing plug-in
api the user can use objective-c or
swift to write the frame processor
plug-in to make this possible i convert
all of the jsi values to objective-c or
swift values
for example a jsi value of type number
can be converted to an ns number
same thing for jsi objects which get
converted to an nsdictionary or jsi
array which gets converted to an nsra
this of course also applies to the
android side so any jsi value can be
converted to a jni value so a java
negative interface value in this case
booleans numbers
strings
and objects can be used
and for the arrays you use the native
array implementations from java
so that's about it for my talk today if
you want to learn more about jsi or
worklets i highly recommend you to check
out the reanimated or vision camera code
base make sure to follow me on twitter
for updates and if you have any
questions just dm me on there
bye everyone
thank you mark really exciting talk and
like i said this is something that i
think will be very popular next year
when jsi becomes something that
everybody is using so i kind of take
this talk as i look into the future
into how we all are going to be building
apps and how we can benefit from the new
architecture so thank you now our next
speaker is joshua from facebook and this
is a very very special talk because this
talk is about fabric but it's unlike all
the other talks we are not going to be
talking about how fabric works and what
fabric is this stuck is actually showing
how fabric can be utilized in production
so you all been listening that fabric
jsi and new components were still in pro
in development and
one day they were about to become public
and production ready but you know we've
been waiting quite a while for it and
i'm so happy to finally see a talk that
is actually talking about this
particular thing how facebook is using
fabric in production what is their
experience with it results performance
benefits so this is another look into
the future on how react native apps will
be looking and working like
next year
so
i'm really excited to learn more about
fabric how facebook is using it and how
they migrate it because their code base
is huge and fabric is probably not the
easiest thing to migrate to so let's
learn about their experience and how
they are using fabric in their facebook
app
my name is josh gross and i'm an
engineer on the react native core team
at facebook
for the past three years the react
native team at facebook has been
re-architecting core pieces of react
native and we've been testing rollout of
them within our own apps including the
flagship facebook app
today i'll talk about just one part of
that the fabric renderer rewrite and out
react native was originally built for
ios
and then for android
today react native has renderers for vr
windows mac os tv os and many other
platforms as well react native is
written and essentially rewritten in
java for android objective-c for ios c
for windows
and so on
basically every one of these
platforms is a full unique uh
re-implementation of react native and
they attempt to behave the same way but
they they don't all behave exactly the
same way
in 2018 the react native team embarked
on a project to build a new architecture
that would be future compatible
we wanted concurrent rendering we wanted
better performance and reliability but
we didn't want to build this end times
for every platform
ideally we could build these features
once
using a cross-platform implementation
and then deploy it to every platform
in order to accomplish this goal we had
to
rewrite react native
but we needed to make sure that we could
bring along all of the apps in the world
our first step was making sure that the
rewrite would work in the biggest app in
the world the facebook app
i'm going to focus today on our journey
of rolling this out in the facebook app
if you want more technical details i
highly recommend watching these talks or
some of these talks given by current and
former members of the core team
the first one here is a high level
overview of all these projects by ram n
at react conf 2018
there is a deep dive of fabric given by
david vodka at react native eu 2018
and there is a talk about the new
architecture by emily janzer at react
native eu 2019
we will also be publishing more blog
posts soon so you can watch out for
those as well
this will not be a technical talk i'm
not going to be doing a technical deep
dive into any
details of fabric or its features but
instead i'll describe our experience of
using it at scale and migrating a very
large code base to use only fabric
this is going to be a story time so sit
back relax grab a warm beverage
or
you can also grab a companion if you'd
like
and i'll share with you our journey of
deploying fabric at scale at facebook
so this is marketplace in the facebook
app
specifically this is the marketplace
home surface
marketplace consists of many many
surfaces
other surfaces include product detail
and commerce profile all of these are
built with react native
in the facebook app react native is used
to build many other products as well so
dating and jobs
and many other products all together
there are over 1 000 surfaces in the
facebook app built with react native
that's a lot so i tweeted about this
recently and a lot of people were
confused or didn't believe me or thought
i misspoke some people thought i meant
that react native within facebook has
1000 components i can assure you it's a
whole lot more than a thousand
components
so when we talk about a surface within
react native at facebook what do we what
do we mean technically speaking um if
you have an ios or android background a
surface would be like a full screen ui
view controller on ios or a fragment on
android um sort of roughly
regardless the assumption here is that
if you navigate to a new surface in
react native at facebook we expect that
surface to sort of take over and redraw
the entire screen so some of these can
be relatively small say you go to a
privacy policy surface maybe it's just
some text but most of them the vast
majority are much more complex and some
of them are huge with hundreds of
features packed into a single surface
so i want to emphasize that number a
thousand plus surfaces however you want
to think of it is a huge
number another unique part of our setup
is that uh at facebook
um
all of our apps using racknative use
react native from the main branch of
github
so whenever we make a change to react
native or whenever we merge a pull
request from github that change goes
into our main developer build
immediately
and then it goes live to all facebook
users in the next weekly release
this only gives us about a week to
ensure that every change we make is
stable on every one of those 1000 plus
surfaces for all of our users
so
what does it mean to be stable
more than one billion people globally
visit marketplace each month
we have to make sure that marketplace
continues working well for people from
different countries with different
network conditions different device
types
since the launch of dating over one and
a half billion matches have been created
so even the smallest regression in react
native easily affects product usage
metrics and that gets amplified by the
scale of facebook a tiny performance
regression of a few milliseconds
will get caught and matters a lot
incredibly rare race conditions or
crashes that are one in a billion events
will happen many times it'll happen
thousands of times a day
we've had to ensure that every screen
every metric every interaction was
working properly
in the meantime the facebook app is a
moving target products and libraries
built on top of react native are
constantly changing they're being
reworked and refactored
so in order to accomplish our goals of
unifying react native and enabling new
features and better performance we
focused on stabilizing existing features
and maintaining neutral metrics
so as part of this rollout we
specifically decided not to focus on
improving metrics or expanding
capabilities yet
we also made sure that any braking
changes were absolutely necessary and
very easy to to migrate and to roll up
very proud to share that as of last
month react native in the facebook app
is now completely powered by the new
architecture
this doesn't mean however that it's
quite ready for everyone to use right
now mostly because documentation is
lacking honestly and some things like
popular open source native modules may
need to be updated i'll say more about
this towards the end of my presentation
let's talk about the development and
rollout process of fabric
we modified our navigation system to
support selectively turning on and off
the architecture for individual surfaces
and allowing us to control what
percentage of users would get fabric or
the old renderer for a particular screen
our work kind of followed the cyclical
pattern we would identify a surface we
would play around with it we would we
would investigate if we found any issues
and try to fix them or implement the new
fabric feature
that they were using that wasn't
supported yet
we'd fix any of these issues and then
we'd run a production test we'd analyze
data
fix any issues that we found again and
then repeat the cycle
pretty straightforward
after we kind of nailed the cycle and
this workflow all we had to do was
repeat it a thousand times it was easy
we just had this playbook and we had to
just keep doing it over and over and
over again
we thought that this was going to be a
six-month project that's not a joke
and
it took us about a full year before we
realized the full scope of the migration
from the start it took about two years
to enable the architecture on the first
surface and nine months after that to
enable fabric on
all the rest of the surfaces
so to be fair to us our estimations were
fairly close only five times off
seems pretty good in the world of
software estimations
so what challenges did we face
well first
we had challenges of scope
so the full scope of the project like i
said wasn't realized until about a year
into the migration
our scope expanded a lot after the
investigation kind of went underway
along the way we discovered a lot of
hidden features of react native as well
as hidden and undocumented optimizations
i i hinted towards this at the beginning
but we also found a lot of subtle
differences between the android and ios
code bases
the vast majority of which were not
documented and the vast majority of
which were not even intentional
they just sort of accidentally drifted
over time
we discovered and documented and patched
a lot of these and actually improved the
non-fabric code base as well but a lot
of them couldn't be fixed without the
fabric rewrite
some of these platform differences over
time had resulted in javascript product
engineers writing platform checks and
slightly different code for android and
ios
so platform switches were sprinkled all
across the facebook codebase
thankfully with the the migration effort
we were able to delete many of these
entirely because of the unified code
base so in this way our production code
has become much easier to read much
easier to reason about after the
migration and the experience between
android and ios users has has been
unified
one concrete example is that scroll view
for android has been almost entirely
rewritten internally compared to two
years ago and it's much more stable
performance
full-featured and in general just higher
quality and aligned with existing
features that ios had already already
had
and a lot of these changes we were able
to back port to the non-fabric renderer
as well
another example is layout animations
which was never fully supported in react
native on android previously it was
always
flagged as sort of an experimental
feature
now it works well on both platforms with
fabric equally well
another challenge for us in the
migration was coming up with backwards
compatible alternatives to apis that we
were deprecating
so this is a pain that nobody else will
go through because we spent a lot of
time making it easier for ourselves and
for our own engineers internally to
migrate code
in most cases because of the time that
we spent up front the migration work
involved
required deleting code because the new
apis are simpler in most cases and some
of the changes involve just like using a
best practice
and
some of the apis are simpler so we could
just delete code
this applies to apis used for rendering
for native modules and for custom native
components
because we always ran screens
during this experiment in both fabric
and the non-fabric render at the same
time until the experimentation was
complete
all code needed to be compatible with
both
in the vast majority of cases a
surface's code didn't need to be
modified at all to work in both fabric
and on fabric
we also encounter challenges with scale
first there's a spectrum of
instrumentation across the facebook code
base
some surfaces have no instrumentation at
all besides sort of the basics that are
provided for all surfaces so our only
signal might be
crashes or bug reports we would test
these screens ourselves we would rely on
qa teams to do some manual testing but
you know this sort of lack of
instrumentation could pose some
challenges
other surfaces have everything
instrumented and would catch regressions
of just a few milliseconds in
performance with some specific
interaction
these hyper-instrumented screens are of
course also challenging
but did offer us an opportunity to
you know kind of really make sure that
fabric is very performant in in all
corners of it
another challenge we faced is that
screens were hyper optimized
specifically for the non-fabric renderer
um and facebook had really found like a
local
a local maximum you know local optimum
for for the the performance of these
screens within the rack native renderer
screens would rely on undocumented
undefined and sometimes just unsupported
behavior
in order to squeeze out any performance
when
non-fabric code does some things
incorrectly but was sometimes faster
because of it
a good example is measure apis the
timing is not guaranteed previously to
fabric it's not guaranteed
so there are many possible race
conditions that can and do occur and
sometimes the measure api returns
incorrect results because of it but the
api is very fast since it was optimized
for speed and not correctness
we were eventually able to optimize the
new fabric apis enough to get to to
parity with
many of these apis are all these apis
and fabric is very performant now but we
did have this initial disadvantage um
because
the non-fabric renderer
had sort of an initial unfair advantage
here right due to its trade-offs
another challenge we faced is that
facebook is a moving target
surfaces are being iterated on very
quickly so there are again i'll
reiterate the number 1000 plus surfaces
but this number is growing daily as well
and in addition many of these screens
are being worked on very very actively
so new features are being released old
features are being deprecated new
metrics are being introduced old metrics
are being removed metrics are being
updated and the baseline is sort of
constantly shifting
especially in the early days in 2018 and
2019 we would try to experiment with
screens that
didn't use as many
features so that we could experiment
with fabric without having implemented
all features necessary for the for the
full implementation so we'd implement
say 50 of fabric and then find a screen
that only used sort of those 50
features
the problem with this approach is that
those screens could be updated at any
time to introduce some usage of an
unsupported feature so um this was
this was a bit of a challenge especially
in the early days because of how fast
facebook moves
given all of that for context let's move
back to the timeline so hopefully it'll
make a little bit more sense now
through mid-2020 most of our time was
spent discovering the scope of fabric
and re-implementing existing apis for
fabric
we provided migration paths for a very
small number of apis that we are
deprecating
like set native props and find node
handle and we provided replacements
backwards compatible replacements for
them
we also migrated screens from using
these deprecated apis to using the new
apis
by the end of
um
like december 2020
we were 99
feature complete
most of the 1000 plus surfaces had
fabric enabled but only for a very small
number of users so around 1
by the end of 2020 99 of surfaces
were only using fabric for all users
so that left only one percent of screens
but as you can imagine that is because
these one percent of screens were very
important
those were the
very high volume hyper optimized hyper
instrumented screens like marketplace
home for for instance
these screens were extremely optimized
specifically for the non-fabric renderer
so we had to spend a lot of time
understanding the the screens and these
products and improving their performance
specifically for fabric
luckily so when i say that that we
improved performance for fabric
basically this just meant adhering to
best practices no longer using all these
undocumented uh
you know sort of unsupported corners of
react native that people had been using
just using best practices using some of
the new apis using just the documented
features
six months later those one percent of
screens were migrated fully to fabric as
well
now i'd like to tell
a couple of interesting stories from my
personal experiences with this rollout
so this is a real photo
from very early on in the fabric
architecture discussions and we spent a
lot of time like this in the early days
huddled around a white board with
someone
trying to explain to us or figure out
how fabric worked uh sort of one person
at the whiteboard explaining it and the
rest of us just kind of staring confused
until
it clicked um and a lot of time in the
in the early days it was us trying to
pull ideas out of sebastian's head as
you can see in this photo until the idea
sort of clicked for the rest of us
i want to share these stories because i
think they can reveal the scale of
facebook and how things can work
internally
and i also want to emphasize um
i expect the vast majority of people
migrating to fabric to never have any
issues like this
in part because we already went through
all of this pain at facebook
so this is part of the reason that we
haven't encouraged facebook adoption as
much before
we wanted to iron out as many of the
edges as possible
another point here uh to make is that
some of these problems are specific to
facebook
so believe it or not sometimes code
within the facebook app isn't perfect i
know that's hard to believe but
sometimes you know there's bugs that get
introduced
sometimes there's some optimal patterns
that really shouldn't be used and this
did make um getting feature parity and
and debugging harder
um so the the first one of these stories
i like to tell um
is that every november like clockwork
um there ends up being some
big crash or bug that blocks my work in
production and every time it takes over
a month to solve
usually well well over a month actually
and this has been true every november
that i've been at facebook
so i'm really hoping it doesn't happen
this november but
you know we'll see i'll have to have to
wait and see
so
to give an insight into what my day to
day looked like during the migration
um i generally would wait until a new
version of the facebook app was released
so
every week a new version is released to
production i would wait 24 to 48 hours
for you know some significant chunk of
users to
um to update
um
and then you know have some time to use
the app as well and then i would analyze
early crash data so basically i wanted
to know did fabric crash
more or less and if it crashed more i
would do a deep dive into finding out
what the issue was and i would you know
try to fix it as soon as possible
um and if the crash was big enough i
would i would just like disable fabric
temporarily as well obviously as we were
rapidly
implementing new features especially in
the early days in 2019 and 2020 we would
get maybe usually like a maximum of one
to two new crashes a week
many weeks we got nothing but if we got
new crashes it was like one or two
most of these were very small volume
uh very marginal like one in a billion
or one in a trillion type events and
most of them were very
trivial like a null pointer exception
where the the root cause is very obvious
and the mitigation was like a null check
you know like one line of code and the
fix is easy
um
but
the reason i'm telling the story is that
sometimes the crashes were not as easy
to
fix or replace so in one particular case
i got an android crash that was pretty
high volume so higher than i was
comfortable with um
and
uh
you know much higher higher than the
most crashes i
had gotten i looked into the sac trace
and there was no facebook code
involved
and there was no react native code
something in the internals of the
android ui layer was crashing that's
basically all i knew and so initially i
was going to just
ignore it or punt it to another team
um
but there was a clue that i had was
which is that it was only crashing on
react native surfaces
and
in addition to that it was only crashing
within uh the sort of the fabric
experiments it was only crashing for
react native fabric users on react
native screens
and only on a few screens as well so
there's you know very little for me to
go on in terms of debugging but it was
very clear that it was actually a fabric
and react native problem
um
but yeah react native is huge our
products are complicated so
uh i didn't have that much information
so at this point i
did what i would normally do i tried to
reproduce the issue
um and of course i couldn't after you
know many many hours of trying to
reproduce it on different devices and
different emulators i just i couldn't
reproduce it my co-workers couldn't
reproduce it
so the next step is to add logs
so hopefully i could get some logging
information with a production crash
telling me roughly what react native was
doing
right before the crash at least what
section of code was executing
before the crash
so i added logs over the course of a few
weeks and predictably got no new
information
um
and because of the cadence of the
releases of our apps it takes a while to
you know
write the code to do logging to to land
it and then for that code to go into
production and so this is a pretty
expensive process um so it actually took
me a month and a half to get no new
information
at this point um i wasn't just waiting i
wasn't just sitting around i had already
looked into the data deeper and noticed
an unusual pattern which is that it only
reproduced on a few specific devices
that itself isn't that unusual but
it didn't reproduce on any samsung
devices or google pixel devices which is
very unusual and in fact it only
reproduced on a few devices that are
generally not used at all within
[Music]
north america or within europe at all
and
some of these devices it's not even
possible to buy within the us uh so this
is also a problem
um but at this point you might be
thinking well why did i just waste all
this time why didn't i just buy one of
these devices that like i could get my
hands on
and the answer is pretty simple
i had never had to do that before in all
the times i'd done development before
that and all the time after it i had
never run into an issue this thorny that
required that i have like one specific
device
um and often um
you know i have run into a lot of device
specific issues
but usually there would just be a stack
trace that indicated that like oh
there's a null pointer exception that
only happens on this one device it
happens in this code
dig in and it becomes clear after some
investigation
not not so easy in this case
so i finally
got one of these devices and
in order to protect the innocence i will
not name the oem
but thankfully i was able to immediately
reproduce the crash within
30 minutes of unboxing this phone
hopefully you're curious at this point
so the problem was that if you have an
empty
parent view on android
and you attempt to remove a child from
it so a view with no children and you
want to remove a child with no parents
from it
uh google like pixel samsung stock
android will just fail silently and move
on and don't do anything because the end
result has already been achieved you're
trying to remove
a view from a parent with no children so
you can kind of
kind of squint at it and say like well
you've already achieved your goal so we
can just move on
but
some oems have modified android i guess
to crash at this point
um and not only that but
a few custom internal facebook
view managers on android
did this in some like use this behavior
in some marginal cases
this is notable and kind of funny to me
because it's the first time i've run
into a case where the oem had changed
really core behavior in this way
and changed basically an undocumented
feature
of android without
also any documentation
um so sort of just undocumented on both
sides it's really unclear you know what
to expect from this api without digging
into the code
it's also worth noting that this is kind
of a classic design problem for apis
if the user does something nonsensical
should you fail silently should you
crash should you give them a warning so
there are pros and cons with any of
these approaches i don't think it's
incorrect or correct for you know stock
android to just move on silently i don't
think it's correct or incorrect to to
crash at this point they're just
different decisions with different
trade-offs
and
you know unfortunately i ran into indoor
case where
both decisions are made in different
cases
um foreclosure here fabric became
resilient to the sequence of operations
and fabric now does just fail sort of
silently in this case
although it logs something to the
console if it happens so technically
there is some clue here
in case you have an issue and it's and
it's related to this
um another november bug i had
was related to performance and event
ordering i believe that this was the the
previous previous november so about a
year earlier
so
earlier days in fabric i was testing a
marketplace screen
and i noticed that in fabric it would
take like five seconds to load the
screen
and most of the time the screen was just
blank and i could tell
from like metro logs that it wasn't like
loading javascript it wasn't really
doing anything it wasn't logging
anything it was just sitting there as
far as i can tell
so i did what we normally do for
performance investigations
i collected log markers which we have
instrumented in react native in our
product code
and so i got sort of a linear sequence
of events for the startup during fabric
and then during non-fabric and i would
compare these timelines
and over time i would drill down to find
you know which specific regions were
slower in fabric
um and you start you add additional
markers you can do like a binary search
of where in this
startup and which segments of code are
slower
um
and and i basically just use this
use this method and then sort of rinse
it and repeat it to dig down
um but i kind of exhausted that
eventually um and i ended up uh
using another tool which is one of my my
favorite and most sophisticated uh
logging tools
which is
logging text to the console using
console.log
so i had a hunch here i would add
logging statements all over the code
base i would collect text logs and
fabric and then a non-fabric i would
literally copy and paste them into text
edit put them side by side on my monitor
and just comb through line by line
you're probably horrified by this after
a couple times of doing this i did end
up using like more sophisticated diff
tools to highlight the differences
between them
but i was still ultimately just using
console.log
and what i ended up finding
was pretty interesting and it was that
the ordering of some events was
different in fabric so
these are like android life cycle events
mixed with react native life cycle
events and methods the specifics don't
matter here too much and i i want to
emphasize that for the vast majority of
even our services in facebook like over
did not have any issues related to this
and most of those surfaces don't do
anything with those lifecycle methods so
they're usually just not needed
but for a few surfaces that were highly
customized highly optimized for the for
the previous renderer
they were doing certain things to
optimize startup
so they were using they were doing sort
of some some special stuff in
like android fragments on fragment
create on start on stop on activity
results sort of that's what i mean by
life cycle methods um mixed with react
native java life cycle methods like
layout and and measurement and you know
again start up things like that
so again the specifics don't matter just
want to give you kind of a general idea
of what kind of apis were were involved
um and so yes some of these events were
happening in a different order in fabric
than they were happening in non-fabric
so i thought well it's it's a long shot
but but i kind of followed my gut and
dug further
and it turned out that the startup of
the screen was constructed as a state
machine sort of an asynchronous state
machine
where it expected event a to happen and
then event b asynchronously and then
event c
and if the sequence was was changed at
all the state machine just broke
so if the sequence instead of being abc
was acb
startup just didn't work and the screen
would just sit there in a in sort of a
perpetual loading state eventually there
was there is like a long-running timeout
that would force the screen to re-render
um so that users were never like truly
stuck um but the screen could appear
more slowly in those cases
so i want to be clear here i'm being
intentionally vague because the
specifics of like the apis don't matter
this is one of those local maxima of
performance that i mentioned earlier
we were doing something uh sort of not
great
to squeeze milliseconds of performance
out of react native in the best case
um and i actually expect this
optimization will go away entirely this
this is like again an internal facebook
optimization i think this this will go
away internally
entirely in the future it's not really
as relevant with fabric and i've never
heard of anyone else doing this outside
of facebook so before i continue i just
want to be clear
i don't expect anyone to run into this
uh scenario period
but why is the ordering
why why is like this a problem if the
ordering events has changed slightly and
since it was causing us an issue why
didn't we just change fabric so that we
could guarantee the previous ordering
of operations even though it was never
like documented or guaranteed
why didn't we just do that
well
since it was never documented or
guaranteed um the ironic thing is that
the sequence of events changed because
we were able to optimize certain things
in the internals of fabric
so maybe that's still not convincing
you're saying it's it wasn't documented
it wasn't guaranteed but we still
changed something that was working right
so sort of
so this is where things like facebook
scale become important
it turned out that even uh with the old
system the ordering events was never
consistent so not only was it not
guaranteed not documented but it also
wasn't ever really consistent
so it would have this particular
sequencing of events like 97 98 of the
time
and in fabric we had that expected
sequencing of events only 90 of the time
so we always had this problem for some
number of users but we never realized it
because
it happened sort of too infrequently for
our metrics to really like alarm on it
and internally uh nobody reproduced it
and so
you know didn't catch it really in
production it wasn't a big enough
problem in in production to raise any
alarm bells and then internally nobody
was impacted by it so we just
uh ignored it never caught it um
the the real problem is that you know
basically if you're building a state
machine based on asynchronous events
you need to either
know that the ordering events is always
going to be the same 100 100 of the time
and then you have to add warnings or
crash if you ever encounter a different
ordering or you can be resilient to
different orderings of events
um this is a hard problem you know async
programming is difficult
uh state machines are difficult to get
right but especially at scale it's
crucial to get this correctly
if you assume a particular ordering and
it's wrong for one percent or five
percent of users that's that's a huge
number of people at scale so long story
short we were able to fix this issue by
making our product code more resilient
to different orderings of events
and in so doing we actually also
improved the user experience for both
fabric and non-fabric and improved
performance for both as well
so again i want to reiterate
for the vast majority of difficult
issues we face with say poor
interactions between product code and
fabric fixing the issue for fabric also
improved the user experience for
non-fabric because generally the issue
was caused by usage of like
undocumented apis undocumented behavior
or just like not using best practices
um
and
um yeah so so we we and we ended up uh
as part of this process also um spending
a lot of time
thinking about and analyzing the
ordering of events
in react native and fabric
and sort of ways of solving this class
of problems in general
and what i what i will say is that it
really illustrated how important it is
both for apis to document any
assumptions and constraints they have
but also that it's very important as a
as a developer as a user of apis for me
to keep an eye on what is not documented
so if documentation was perfect it would
just call out explicitly that something
is subject to change
um but obviously that doesn't always
happen
and now when i notice a gap in
documentation when i'm looking for
something and i kind of can't find it
sometimes now i wonder if that's almost
intentional sometimes maintainers don't
want to provide guarantees
because if you do then people rely on
them and then that causes parts of the
systems to become less flexible
again
i don't expect frankly anyone outside of
facebook to be impacted by this most
people will never use or think about
these events that were involved
um
as a side note one thing that we thought
about uh doing internally to force
product code to be more resilient is to
have like a chaos monkey event mode
where for you know developers only
in some cases we would just randomly
delay events or reorder some events um
so we haven't done this yet
if you hear facebook engineers
complaining about it in the future maybe
it's maybe that's my fault um but i
actually suspect that doing this sort of
thing would catch a lot of bugs and like
future bugs in waiting
finally um it's taken us a you know very
long time to fully migrate the facebook
app onto the new react native
architecture
we're very proud of this moment and you
know
uh very proud of all the work that went
into it but we know that we are we are
we're not done yet and our next step is
to bring it to all of you
we're starting to plan this work now
we're clearly you know very bad at
estimating so i'm not going to make any
claims for dates
um
so while we don't know how long this
full process will take we we do know the
next steps
we're currently working on tutorials and
guides to help people take advantage of
the new architecture
we're partnering uh closely with
companies like expo
call stack and software mansion
as well as maintainers of the most
popular packages in open source to make
sure that they're compatible with the
new
architecture it's very very important
for us that this upgrade goes as
smoothly as possible for everyone and we
really can't wait to get to get it into
all of your hands
i am but one part of a pretty large team
uh and this effort involved a lot of
people
including a lot of engineers within
facebook that are that are not on the
react native team
too many people to count
um but within the team i'd like to give
a big thanks and recognition to the
people that i've been working with daily
for the past few years
so especially david vodka samuel susla
and valentin shurigen big thanks this is
a huge effort thank you for uh making my
life easier and helping me out along the
way
um i'd also like to thank our leadership
who supported such a huge ambitious
rewrite especially when it took years
longer than
expected um so big shout outs here to
tom aquino tim young yuzi zang kevin
gozzali and eli white
thank you so much for watching and i'll
see you on github
thank you joshua for this talk it's been
really great to learn about your
experience and i guess i'm really happy
to see that
you at facebook are actually sharing
that knowledge i feel like this is not
something that everybody would do
because to a certain extent
this is sort of a um
you know your business domain so maybe
not something that you want everybody to
know about but i'm so happy that you are
sharing this knowledge with the
community so we can all learn from you
so
i just wanted to thank you for being
around with cold stack and react native
eu uh ever since i guess we started your
support has been great here and i'm so
happy that we can have this uh readme
video as a field for you to kind of
share those breakthrough
updates so uh thank you and i'm looking
forward to the next year edition already
now let's move to the next speaker uh
which is calif from microsoft and caleb
is going to talk about react native for
windows and mac os now you probably
heard about red native for windows quite
a while ago but
maybe you haven't heard about it but
it's been rewritten to a new version and
then folks at microsoft added the macos
part now
windows and mac os
didn't have a easy start because react
native has been always about android and
ios so making sure that react native
architecture is ready for another
platform has been always a challenge and
we have seen that in react native cli
for example that i'm contributing to but
also in other parts
so they've been doing a very very hard
job into not only supporting windows and
mac os but also into back porting the
features that they are doing uh into
react native itself so today caleb is
going to share their experience creating
that framework and how they actually
enable their teams to build great
applications so i'm kind of excited to
see what they are about to share with us
but i'm kind of expecting that there's
going to be some interesting use cases
of how react native is working
in desktop applications in both macos
and windows environments so let's learn
about that and calif good luck
hi everyone
i'm calif and i'm really excited to be
here to talk to you about react native
for desktop platforms
so a little bit about myself i am an
engineering manager at microsoft and i
work in the office division
before becoming an engineering manager i
was an engineer and i worked primarily
on accessibility
and when it comes to react native i have
been in this space for the last couple
of years now
i really like how with react native you
can learn the technology once
and then be able to run your apps
anywhere you need to
and you can imagine that for
applications like office such technology
is really important because our code
base has millions of lines of code and
so we really benefit from being able to
share our code across multiple platforms
as well as reapply the same the same
technology across
we've seen a lot of engagement around
react native at microsoft as well like
the there are multiple apps and features
that have been built either you know
brownfield or greenfield applications um
using react native and we have a nice
little ecosystem that keeps growing
every day
so it is a very very exciting place to
be and uh i'm glad to be here to talk to
you a little bit about how
we are evolving the desktop platforms
and so what we will talk about today
first we'll go through the investments
in react native for windows and mac os
that have happened recently
and then we'll talk a little bit about
some applications that have been built
using those platforms
so let's go ahead and jump in and talk
about react native for windows and for
mac os
and as you probably know uh this has
been a journey for microsoft for a few
years now
with a lot of investments for so that we
can bring the power of react native uh
to the to the desktop platforms
and it's been a really nice partnership
like we've worked very closely with
facebook uh to to evolve those platforms
lots of design meetings discussions uh
alignment and directions and where we're
going and uh we've made a lot of
improvements over the last few years and
and the fact that we're seeing multiple
applications shipping on top of that
platform is really encouraging for the
future
so uh
let's talk about a little bit about the
investments that we've actually made
and uh when we think about those we
typically bucket them into three
different areas
the first one is the core runtime itself
so think of this as the core of react
native that runs on user devices and
allows you to build your experience on
top so we'll talk about that then we'll
talk about some ui frameworks that we've
built on top that allows you to augment
the default experience that's provided
with react native
and finally we'll talk a little bit
about some tooling
that is making our lives easier and
hopefully will make yours as well
so let's jump in and talk about the
runtime first
starting with the react native for mac
os
and so the major highlight that we have
for mac os is that we recently released
the version 0.63 of the platform
there are several improvements in it
including support for svg for tooltip
and key loop
we are currently working on version 64
and expect this to be ready in the next
few months
and
there's also been a lot of really nice
additions to community modules for mac
os
so if you're interested head over to
react native.directory and then filter
on mac os and you will see all of the
modules that are now currently supported
[Music]
and then when it comes to react native
for windows we've released version 64
0.64 and we're currently working on
version 0.65
so uh one of the things that uh i would
like to highlight here is that uh for
this version 0.64 we were able to
release react native for windows at the
same time as the ios and android
platforms version 0.64 as well were
released
and this was something that was very
important to us because
what we want is we want to make the
upgrade process as seamless as possible
and allow people to upgrade both the
desktop and the mobile platforms at the
same time
so we spent a lot of time getting
windows up up to date and current with
uh react native and then we're able to
release that 0.64 simultaneously
now we are working on getting mac there
as well such that once we're done like
you will be able to see all four
platforms being released at the same
time
and then the next thing is
we now have support for react native
windows in upgrade helper
if you're not familiar with this uh what
a great helper is is it's a place where
you can go plug in your current version
of react native and plug in the version
that you would like to upgrade to and
upgrade helper will show you what
changed and how you can go ahead and
update it's a really cool tool uh makes
upgrading a lot easier
uh we've also improved the developer
experience so uh
you are probably familiar using
you're probably familiar with codebush
already so
that technology was available on ios and
android
and what it does is it allows you to
update your bundles over the air without
having to redeploy your application
it's very powerful and it's now
available natively in react native for
windows as well
code push itself is part of
our visual studio app center offering
and if you head over to
microsoft.github.io
codepush you'll get more information on
how to get started and leverage it
uh and the next thing i want to talk
about is the documentation so
uh this is one place where uh we've
spent a bit of time uh to to make to
improve what we have already and we
definitely want to spend a bit more time
there uh like getting the whole spectrum
of our documentation
out there for you to use
but right now the biggest improvement is
on the native api side and so if you
head over to our documentation site you
will see a lot more native apis being
documented including you know like how
to use it if you need to
um
also we want to make it easier to to use
react native across again across
multiple platforms and in order to do
that we've increased the parity that we
have in windows with ios and android so
there are new props supported like
accessibility info and platform version
and we have more coming up as well
so the next thing i want to talk about
is uh is your build time and uh we have
in experimental support right now a
binary distribution so what this is is
uh instead of consuming react native for
windows uh as source code you can
consume binaries that have already been
built and just start building your
application on top
this is something that we've been
experimenting with and we've seen really
really good improvements to both build
time and disk usage by doing that so in
our tests the build time was about 80
faster and the disc usage was about was
about half of what it used to be
so this is still experimental we're
working to make it full production
quality uh but you can give it a shot
and see if it works for you
and then let's talk about hermes so i'm
sure everyone must have heard about
hermes right now and uh
how it improved both the startup time
and the memory usage on the mobile
platform
so uh we've had hermes for some time in
react native windows as well and
recently we've done a lot of work to
make it easier to use
so first there
in order to use hermes all you need to
do is turn on one build flag and we will
take care of the rest so we will package
the runtime we will
do the bytecode generation and package
this with the with the application
and then and then configure react native
for windows to use hermes instead of the
default engine on windows
and what we've seen is that the
performance gains are similar to the
ones that uh that uh have been seen on
mobile platforms as well
uh it's easier now to debug your
application using when you're using
hermes we support direct debugging and
uh we've also recently added support for
profiling so you can see how your
performance characteristics are
measuring up
so
hermes right now is supported for our c
plus plus applications and
we will have support for the c sharp
ones as well in the future
[Music]
and then let's talk about community
modules so these are of course super
important in the ecosystem and uh
we've increased the number that is
supported by windows as well
there are a few here that are listed to
give you an idea for example the react
native sketch canvas is one that i will
talk about a little bit later in one of
the demos
but i think at this point we support
around 40 community modules and if you
want to see that full list that's
supported just head over to react
native.directory and filter on windows
and you'll see that
so in summary when we talk about react
native for windows
it is much easier for you to upgrade to
the more recent versions we are so as i
mentioned we have version .64 up and
running we are currently working on
version 0.65 it should be available very
soon
and we've improved the developer
experience we've improved the support
for hermes
and also we built react native windows
on top of the wind ui library and so
when we make changes to the ui layer you
get that for free and that's what
happens in the case of windows 11
where we rejuvenated the ui layers so
you will just get that for free by using
react native for windows which is pretty
great
so let's switch gears and talk a little
bit about the ui frameworks
and
the first one i'm going to talk about is
fluent ui react native
right now this is mostly for early
adopters we have a few controls that you
can find and see if it works for you and
we're in the process of adding new
controls um and and being able to
support additional scenarios as well
but what this is so
fluent ui react native is a is a set of
controls that are supported across
multiple platforms
and that have the fluent design system
built in
and the fluent design system is is
essentially a set of styles that is
designed to look great across all
platforms so this comes built into the
controls when you use them
now if for any reason you want to
override the built-in design system to
match what you would like to to render
you can do that as well
so head over to github.com microsoft
slash ui react native and you can learn
more about it
and and i'll show you a quick demo of
how this works so you have a mac os an
ios and an android application and what
we're showing here is the difference
between light mode and dark mode as well
as the ability to inject your own
branding so
if you see for example
word is typically blue and excel is
green and so you can you can customize
it such that
on on excel it looks green and on word
it looks blue and then and so have that
branding for those applications
and here's a couple of examples of
controls that we have today so uh these
are the ones that are on mac os
in light mode
these ones are controls on mac os using
dark mode
these are the ones that are on ios
and these ones are on android
so again
this is an in this is an area that we're
investing fairly heavily in as well uh
so you'll see more controls coming up
but feel free to give it a try and let
us know what you think
so the next ui library that we'll talk
about is react native xaml
and what this is is it's a library that
exposes the xaml ui controls to react
native for windows
if you're not familiar with xaml what it
is is it's the native ui framework that
that's built into windows
and uh what react native xaml does is it
provides a projection of those controls
into javascript
so that allows you to write uh you know
any of your view managers like purely in
javascript without having to touch the
native code at all
so let me show you a demo of what this
looks like
and here what we're doing is we're using
the the color picker of the xaml of the
xaml library
so uh
with just a few lines of code about like
five lines or so uh you can you can use
the control inside of your application
and then uh respond to the callbacks
that it provides so in this case uh what
we're doing is uh we are
rendering the control and then just
displaying the rgb values
that are coming back into a text block
pretty powerful control and very easy to
use with with just a few lines of code
uh so react native xaml is intended for
uh windows developers who are familiar
with the xaml
language already and who are not
planning to
to use their applications across
multiple platforms
and then the third ui library that we'll
talk about is
babylon react native
so what this is is
first let's talk about babylon.js and
babylon.js is a very popular javascript
library that is built on open web
standards so it is completely free and
open source and there's several
really nice models that have been built
using it if you head over to the js
website you will see
hundreds of examples of of this uh
already
and babylon js on native is also
supported on native platforms so the
first thing is what we that we have is
babylon native and it brings that power
of babylon js over to those native
platforms
and babylon react native is the
integration of that babylon native
platform into react native
so what it does is it provides you a
react native component
that you can use as a rendering surface
for your babylon
model and you can use that to render the
model and etc this is currently
supported on ios on android and windows
so over to a quick demo uh this is this
is for example uh one that's actually
running on android here
that shows you
uh live reload working so you have a
couple of models and on the left side
what we're doing is we're just switching
between them and so
here's the first here's the first one
and we went to the second one now we can
go back to the first one etc
and so that's completely supported in
react native for windows and one of the
experiences that you can build there is
uh is an augmented reality one
and so here's the same model that was
built earlier running on top of the
hololens device
so we can render it in inside of the
space
of uh that the person is seeing
in augmented reality
which is pretty cool and again that's
running on top of react native for
windows
so here so those were a few
ui frameworks that we provide uh it's
there's a lot of work going on there uh
let us know what you think try them uh
happy to hear feedback uh on how this uh
how your experience is using them
and so now let's talk a little bit about
tooling
and uh
and i will mention a couple of things so
one is uh we have uh we recently built a
test app we call it the react native
desktop uh that simulates you know like
a real neat real react native
application on multiple platforms so ios
android mac os and windows
and uh uh it's really nice because it
abstract a lot it abstracts a lot of the
complexity of all those platforms for
you allowing you to just go ahead and
just write your applications on top
fairly easily
and the other thing that's cool about it
is that there is a we have a workflow
that's uh supported that allows you to
quickly switch between react native
versions
and that's important because you can
then just try a newer version and see
how your experience will run um
in a very
quick and efficient manner
so uh the link for this one is
github.com microsoft slash react native
test app
the other one i will mention is a reaper
called rnx kit
that is also supported by microsoft
so what this is is it's a set of tools
that we built to help you
maintain and build your react native
applications and libraries it's a lot of
things that we learned as we were
building our own applications that uh
where we felt we needed
small tools to help us and all of those
are in this rna skid repo
so i put a table on the right here where
you can see some examples of those tools
but i would say if you're interested in
learning more about this we have a
separate talk at the react native eu
conference where we will discuss that so
that talk is by lorenzo chandra and
tommy nuyen and it's called improve all
the repos highly recommend that you
check this out we will go into a lot
more details around one of the tools
that is in the rnx kit as well as the
react native test tab
cool
uh so next i'm going to talk a little
bit about the applications that have
been built using react native uh and and
maybe starting with one that you might
have heard already so facebook is
building the new messenger application
on top of react native for windows and
mac os
um and this is a great testament of the
power of the platform it allows you to
build that to build one app to build
your app once and have it running on
both on both operating systems
so you've heard about that one and i
will now talk about a couple of other
ones that you may not have heard about
so
the first one is the pneumatics backpack
application and what it is is it's a
digital classroom experience with tools
that are integrated for students and
teachers to use
the app was originally developed but for
ios and android and then pneumatics saw
that there was a high demand for windows
as well and so what they did was they
migrated the application for to windows
using react native for windows now you
can imagine like those applications
right now are really important
especially with people working uh
studying remotely and needing really
good uh applications for them to be able
to do this efficiently and so here's a
screenshot of the dashboard for
pneumatics you can see it's very
detailed it gives you an idea of the
classes that you have the assignments
that you need to do etc
the next one is what pneumatics calls
its smart paper experience
and this one is actually using the react
native sketch canvas so it supports
touch it supports inking
and
what it does is it allows you to
for example here do a long division and
uh enter your step you enter your
content step by step
and that's really nice because the
teacher can then replay uh the steps
that the student did and identify areas
where they might have made mistakes and
help them there
so so in some cases these applications
are optimized for touch as in the case
of when you're running on android
and and when you're running on windows
with touch support you can use that as
well
the next one is the one called smart
label and so this one allows you to take
a static image and be able to add labels
to them dynamically
so really cool experience as well for
kids so that they can label things
as part of their workflow
cool
and then let's look at one at the second
application so this one is
coming from mashreq bank and uh mashreq
is the oldest regional application the
oldest regional bank in the united arab
emirates and it has uh offices in
several continents so
here's what mashreq
had they had they had an android
application already uh that was being
used by their frontline workers to
interact with the customers
uh and what they what they needed was
this a similar application for windows
because uh part of their part of their
employees were also using well using
windows devices
so they used react native for windows in
order to stand up that application
now what's great about it here as well
is that on android the application is
optimized for touch
uh and on react on windows it's
optimized for mouse and keyboard uh
thanks to the built-in support that we
have there already
uh
the the the team was able to do this uh
while sharing the majority of the code
between the android and the windows
application which is a really nice win
as well
so this is a screenshot of what they
built this is the
logging part of their experience and
then
when a user uses logged in you can see
what a
sample customer information page would
look like
so this is also very rich and again
built on top of
react native for windows with a lot of
code shared between the android and the
windows implementation
and then let's talk a little bit about
how microsoft is using react native on
desktop platforms so we've got several
apps again i mentioned that we've been
shipping already
some of brownfield applications some
some are greenfield ones but at this
point we're shipping to hundreds of
millions of customers around the world
so uh we'll talk about office first
and uh office builds brownfield epic
applications in the client apps so think
about word excel powerpoint and outlook
there's at least an app there's at least
any experience in it today running react
native
and these are shipping in ios on android
on mac os and on windows
as a couple of examples uh this is a
revamp of our commenting experience so
previously when you commented in word it
used to be inline on the canvas we've
now moved it to a pane and provide you a
very rich experience where you can
comment
and interact with other users or who are
looking at the document and this is a
screenshot of what that experience
actually looks like
the next one is our privacy dialogue
this is again like completely built
using react native
this is the dialogue that you get when
you sign into office for the first time
and then to be able to set your privacy
settings
and then this one is is what we call the
unity canvas it's it's a place where we
can advertise some really cool features
around the application that we would
encourage people to use
uh so this is this these are examples uh
for office and then we can talk about uh
react native uh for windows on xbox
and uh you might have seen those
screenshots already because we've shared
them before but but again i just wanted
to show the richness that we have here
so there are multiple experiences today
on xbox that are shipping on react
native and if you have a fairly recent
version of the operating system and an
xbox at home chances are you're running
react native on it
so here's an example uh the when you get
to the xbox events
this page is built using react native
once you go uh once you go inside and
start looking more about the events you
get into a new a new react native for
windows view
that is that you can interact with
here's a couple of additional
screenshots uh with showing apps that
you can purchase
um and and a set of search results
so uh
we had really great feedback from our
xbox colleagues as well on their usage
of react native
they they highlighted a lot of really
good performance improvements that they
saw and uh if you if you're using this
experience on uh
on the xbox you'll notice that it's it's
very very smooth
so it was it was a it was a great
experience for us
and so how do you get started uh writing
your own react native applications so
the first thing you want to do is head
over to aka dot ms slash react native
and we have a bunch of getting started
guides guides there
you can start you know writing an app
from scratch or you can port an existing
app that you have for android or for ios
over
uh to windows and and mac os and
we'd be very happy to hear you know how
your experiences and one of the things
that you've been able to do so you can
always connect with us on github if you
have any questions as well that we can
help you with
uh
so so just as a short demo i i went over
to that website and in the interest of
time i already set up an environment so
here i am on my mac os laptop
and i am running a virtual machine for
windows and what you can see is
the uh the application for
our test application when you go through
the first experience you will get this
test application uh on the left one is
the one for windows and the right one is
the one for mac os
and so uh
so i have the development experience set
up and
i already
downloaded the prerequisite the
prerequisites i have my bundler running
and so what i will do next
is go ahead and just
um
show you show you how what this looks
like so on the mac uh you can use you
will use xcode and we have live reload
working for example so here you know i'm
increasing my font size uh from 24 to 48
to 48 once i save you can see uh the
live reload working pretty quickly in
the test application
uh and that's all fully supported
and uh the same thing on react native
for
for windows as well so here i'm using
using visual studio you can use visual
studio code as well let me just make
this a little bit bigger and i'll just
try the same thing so
change the font size and then go ahead
and save the new bundle will get pushed
there and here you can see on the left
that the phone just became bigger
so you can you can try this as well it's
it's very easy to get started and write
an application on both of those
platforms
so give it a shot
let us know how it how it is
and uh we'll be very happy to hear what
your experience was like
so with that i'd like that's the end of
my presentation so i'd like to thank you
for listening uh thank you also for call
stack from course focal stack to set
this this conference up it's really
great to have everyone together to talk
about those experiences and i know it
takes a lot of time to get those
conferences up and running so thank you
again
if you want to get in touch with me my
contact info is here on this page
and then i have on the left a link to
all of the repos that we talked about in
this presentation
so again if you want to get started aka
dot ms slash react native give it a try
let us know how it how things go
and again thank you for listening and
enjoy the rest of the conference
bye
thank you khalif really exciting talk
and honestly i'm so happy that there is
mac os and windows at the same time
because i can kind of make windows apps
developing mac on macos at the same time
so i don't have to deal with those vms
now i guess you know this has been a
very very intense first block so i guess
you are all probably excited for what's
next to come but before we do that i do
have a 15 minutes break for all of you
to kind of maybe get more coffee have a
break and most importantly open up
discord go to the react native eu
channel and just talk with each other
maybe you have some interesting insights
about the talks that you have just heard
or maybe you want to ask questions to
folks at microsoft or facebook or expo
about the things that they have shared
with us so just take the most out of
this time and we will see each other in
15 minutes from now
this conference is brought to you by
codestack react and react native
development experts
[Music]
[Applause]
my
[Music]
[Applause]
look at this garden
[Music]
hello
hello i'm mike serious co-founder at
callstock and today i'm looking for the
best react native developers to join my
team besides working on high-end
software used by millions we also
contribute to many opus projects such as
react native paper react native testing
library or repack and so you will have
an opportunity to develop your skills
and knowledge within these projects as
well as move your own ideas into life by
taking part in our r d program we are a
great team full of people crazy about
react native technology and we can't
wait to share our knowledge and
description with you trust me it's great
to be part of such a team so don't wait
anymore join us check out the job
description and in the link below and
apply and i'm hoping to see you soon in
our callstack office or maybe remotely
depending on your location bye bye
[Music]
hello everyone this is luca speaking i
have a pleasure to co-host this fifth
react native eu conference live from
wordsworth poland from our call stack
office i hope you're having a great time
today
we just had our icebreaking session and
we talked about cross-platform and
architecture of react native
applications
at our first session we had a great
speakers
mark from expert joshua from facebook
and caleb from microsoft thank you guys
for doing this
i want to remind you all
that all of the talks will be available
on our youtube channel call stack
engineers please check check that out um
join us also on discord when we can do
some networking and you can ask
questions that will be answered either
by our speakers right now or will be
addressed in our next react native show
podcast
you can also and you are encouraged to
tweet about this conference using react
native eu
so that you can let your friends and
family know that you are here with us
today um yeah and that was all from this
break
uh let's have a cup of coffee and we'll
see
you in a few minutes for our next round
of talks
[Music]
wake up in frostwolf get up and get at
him
react native eu is on and it's happening
check in to check up on all of the
latest news and strategy man it's kind
of the greatest
and welcome to react native you 2019
[Applause]
keynotes that unlock a new world of
insight lightning talks this cutting
edge it really seems so right
networking with everyone in the react
native community from the thinkers to
the linkers we're all here in unity
q and a's that dive deep into cold dna
and it's all covered here in only two
days
especially when it comes to trouble
after the last session we're gonna party
okay
food drinks with good vibes and dope
karaoke
[Music]
high fives all around it was good to be
here
[Music]
can't wait to the next one we'll see you
next year
[Music]
so
uh
[Music]
this conference is brought to you by
coldstack react and react native
development experts
[Music]
welcome back after break and uh we are
after a quite intense series of talks
about react native core features and
what's here to come so now let's focus
on something that you can probably all
relate to which is application
development and features or libraries
that we are using every day now next two
speakers are from call stack so these
talks are what i'm particularly excited
about um so the first speaker is
alexandra and she's going to talk about
uh game development with react native
now there's been quite a few talks in
the past about game development the
react native on the react native eu but
this one is different because it's
talking about using unity 3d now i've
been also doing unity development quite
a while ago but my prototyping with
react native failed so that's why i'm
particularly excited to learn more about
what she has to tell us today and how
she has succeeded on her journey
while developing games with react native
and unity so let's learn about that and
see how she make that happen
hello everyone i hope you are all having
a great time in react native eu 2021
i'm alex i'm here to talk to you about
game development the exact title of my
talk is what if i want to be a game dev
i would like to start with a quote by
ernest cline from the book ready player
one maybe some of you have heard about
it or the book or
the movie
being human totally sucks most of the
time video games are the only thing that
makes life bearable
okay that quote is kind of a bummer but
video games are really a great way to
spend your free time right and we do
play
a lot of games
that's why i would like to talk to you
about developing games because you know
somebody has to create the games that we
play
my talk will be divided into four parts
first i'll do an introduction
about a little bit about myself and
about
the reasons for
making this talk
i will then go on to presenting your
options
what
can you do if you want to develop games
and then i will concentrate on a game
engine called unity and
lastly i will talk about integrating
unity
in a with a react native app
i'd like to start off with a little
introduction as i said in the beginning
my name is alex this is actually my
second talk at react native eu
i spoke last year about animations in
react native apps
and i showed you a little preview during
the talk of a small app called
that i worked on and i'm very proud to
say that that app is currently available
on the google play store and on
the app store
i would like to briefly add that
publishing uh the app by myself was a
challenge but it's doable so if you're
out there doing some solo mission and
you're worried if you'll be able to make
it
you will it's okay you can you can do it
um
i like to push boundaries
of
uh what i do of currently of app
development
so working on games is kind of pushing
it what
pushing what we currently do
in react native apps usually
and last but not least i recently joined
call stack and i'm very excited about
that
let's move on to the topic of this talk
i entitled this slide why so serious
because we developers sometimes take
ourselves a little bit too seriously
so let's talk about games a little bit
let's wake up our inner child
i would like to convince you that
developing games is
a great thing to do
because it creates new challenges
in very new areas
it can become your creative outlet
you know
some people
make bread some other people like make
pottery you can make games
you can learn new stuff new programming
languages but also new concepts in
programming
especially if you are self-taught like
me
then
facing like new approaches to
programming is very enriching
and
maybe there's some game that you
would like to play yourself but that
doesn't exist yet
so you can go ahead and create it
so now that you're super convinced that
game development is fun
and is a good way to spend your time
let's weigh your options
you can take
pretty much one of three votes
you can go with just plain old react
native and it can be done in react
native there are a lot of flappy bird
examples of games developed in
just
plain old react native i guess flappy
bird is the game
equivalent of the to-do apps for
react.js tutorials
another road you can take is using a
library called react native game engine
it's just exactly what the name says
it's a game engine it has some built-in
functionalities like loops or character
movement and
it will help you start
faster
or you can try to integrate a game
engine
that can be super useful if the game i
have in mind is maybe a bit more
complicated than flappy bird
let's
take a deeper dive into those three
options
there are many games written in react
native alone
um
i myself saw a presentation of flappy
royale
on the stage of react native eu 2019
written in react native alone
and
there's a minesweeper game a basketball
game you can you can find all kinds of
great examples
on github
and i would like also like to um
recommend watching william candyland's
youtube channel
where
the channel is called can it be done
react native and the answer is usually
yes
so what he did is he created a
[Music]
three baby 3d engine and
he shows
how to use it
and how he used it
with just react native and reanimated
if your game is a little bit more
complicated or complex you may want to
go with
open source library react native game
engine
this library will help you tackle some
standard
game functionalities such as character
movement
or loops or many many others
but what if your game is even more
complex
then you may want to go with the game
engine
there are many many game engines out
there in the world
two
two game engines that are really
renowned are unity and unreal
unity
has a vast tutorial
ecosystem
and it has actually existing
integrations with react native
unreal is
is a famous
game engine that has great 3d rendering
and there is an unreal js plugin where
you can use the unreal engine and write
all your code in js
so why am i talking about unity here
unity is simply my personal preference
to be honest both of those game engines
have editors
which have a little bit of a learning
curve it takes some time to understand
all the fields and there's a lot of
fields
[Applause]
[Music]
and it's
you have to you have to put some time in
so
i put my time in to unity and
what i got back
was really satisfying for me and that's
why also i wanted to
present it to you today
here you can see
a few second gif of a game i created
thanks to a tutorial on unity
it was a 14 hour tutorial that i took a
couple of hours a day for a week so
after a week i had i have this complete
game uh with ruby the main character who
is animated
moves around she can get damaged she can
eat her little strawberry to get her
health back you can see her health in
the corner
she can talk to other characters
and
this was all done
in just a few days with the help of a
very
nicely
done tutorial
all the assets were free and this was a
real fun way to learn unity and at the
same time i ended up with a game that i
can play that i can show to my friends
and family that i can
build out i can create a whole world now
and make this a really big
game
here are a list of some key points which
convinced me to use unity
as i said unity has a lot of tutorials
some of them are in editor
very
very comfortable to use
with highlights of buttons that you have
to click to
to achieve the goal of the tutorial as
well as tutorials on the website
the website also contains learning paths
where by completing tutorials you earn
points and
that's that's a pretty nicely gamified
solution for learning
there are a lot of free assets to start
off
there are a lot of paid assets as well
but if you don't want to invest any
money
you can start off with really a bunch of
very nice free assets
unity is great for 2d games as well as
for 3d games
and it is used for some very few for
some very big titles which i will
mention in a second and there are
actually a few react native integration
libraries out there that you can use
here are
a few notable titles they use the unity
engine
it's used in the game overcooked 2
4 guys or subnautica
and as far as mobile games are concerned
unity is used for super mario run
monument valley angry birds epic and
many many more
if you notice super mario run here i can
add that nintendo actually uses the
unity game engine for all of their
mobile games
and that includes animal crossing
crossing a pocket or dr mario world and
mario kart tour
and three quite a few titles out there
so now i have convinced you that game
development is great
then i hope i convinced you that unity
is great
now the last
piece of the puzzle is talking about the
marriage of react native and unity
i believe they create quite the power
couple
integrating react native with unity
can be
done
in two ways on a high level
you can have a react native app
and integrate
a unity mini game or some unity
functionalities in your app
or
you can have a unity app
in which you integrate a react native
app and functionalities
so let's start with the first approach
use we start with a react native app and
integrate a little bit of unity
goodness inside of it
on the high level it takes three steps
you start by creating your app your
react native app
then you can use unity as a library
which is a new feature introduced to
unity in 2020
or you can check out some open source
implementations
and then you just sit back and
admire your beautiful app game
here are some examples
of such integrations
here you can see a
a game like a shooter game
which is inside of a react native view
it's a pretty it's a pretty big complex
game
um but at any time you can go back to
your react native app
and there's also another here you can
see another example
of an app which has a react a unity game
a reaction app with a unity game but
it's presented on a tab
and
if you look closely you can actually
even see there are buttons
in the unity app where you can change
the background
or like rotation of the 3d object can
you imagine trying to
render this 3d object in javascript i
mean that would be
and that would be a lot of work right
and unity is
pretty much
a few clicks
here you can see another example of an
integration is
it's different in the sense that the
react the unity
game or view is in the background of
your react native app
[Music]
and on the right you can see something
that i find super exciting
it's an example integration
made by the united team
of using unity as a library inside a
native app
so
they have like a native app with a store
which
we all know you can do in react native
and then at the touch of a button you go
into an augmented reality powered by
unity
where your shopper can see
what their item would look like on their
actual desk
so as you can see
there are a lot of ways
to use unity you they have virtual
reality augmented reality mixed reality
3d models games
you know the sky's the limit
and
this is my cat who really wanted to
participate in this talk
[Applause]
i have to tell my cat to go away he was
not being very helpful
so
the sky is the limit for for
all the different things you can do
between react native and unity and let's
not forget that thanks to those
implementations
unity and react in your react native app
can communicate communicate both ways
which really opens up a lot of awesome
doors
so let's take a look at going the other
way around
and integrating react
reactant app into a unity game
the steps to accomplish this on a high
level
are
pretty much the same you start off by
creating a unique game this time
and then you export it into an android
studio project or
an
ios
project
and then you can integrate
the react native activity or react
native as a module inside of unity 3d
so the first thing is what is
recommended by
uh the fish react native documentation
you can always implement your
react native into a native app right
um but i read an article
which presented
an integration of react native as a
module into unity 3d and i have to tell
you it got me very excited about some
other possibilities
of creating great experience creating
great experiences for gamers
so here's a short gif of
which presents how how such an
integration could work
and
as you can see on the screen you can
just imagine your favorite game written
in unity and you click the the store
button and you can stay in the game
and still by yourself maybe like a cute
t-shirt with your uh favorite character
from that game
and
that creates an awesome opportunity to
create very immersive experiences for
our gamers
and all of our users
so that's it for me thank you very much
for listening i really hope i did
convince you to try out unity
if you decide to try out unreal i will
not be mad
it's it's a great game engine as well
and it also has a lot of tutorials
and
just go out there and create some great
bye
thank you alexandra for this talk and
now a fun fact is that alexander
actually applied to react native eu
while not being a call stack employee
now
you know we've been discussing herzog
for so long that i guess our
relationship turned out to uh this kind
of a form where we are now working
together so
it's kind of interesting how real native
eu can you know let you meet new people
and maybe somehow and sometimes make you
work together
now our next speaker is satya and satya
has been working with us actually from
quite a long
probably from the from the very
beginning and he's been very very
excited about open source in particular
about react navigation it's something
that has been on from the very beginning
developing ever since you know the react
navigation came out to the open space
and he's been i guess last year talking
about react navigation new features and
now he's going to talk about kind of the
same thing but worry not it's not going
to be boring because there is a whole
new version coming up and that's what
satya is going to tell us about today so
react navigation 6
let's fasten our seat belts and
see what satya has prepared for us today
i'm satisfied
and i'm the maintainer of react
navigation
today i'm excited to share the act
navigation sex with all of you
so navigation in react native
is one of the most important parts of
react native
it's one of the first things that users
experience in the app and that's why
it's important to provide a smooth and
native feeling to the user while keeping
things mature brand
today we have react navigation which is
one of the most popular navigation
libraries
but it wasn't always like that
in fact there have been many attempts at
solving this problem there have been a
lot of libraries with a lot of different
apis and varying approaches
i still remember when i first tried
building something like native one of
the first things i was looking for was
to replicate that native field
it was one of the first things that came
to my mind
so i wasn't like searching for
navigation libraries per se but that's
what i meant like that's the feeling i
wanted to capture
so interestingly the ignitive already
included a navigation library when it
first launched unlike that now
so initially there was navigator ios it
was
long before react native added android
support and it was ios only
so it was a fully native component
which was
only for ios and it replicated ios
navigation controller it had a very
small set of customization options you
could only change the header color and
the font family etc
but since it was native it was pretty
smooth
this component is no longer in react
native code but luckily this was just
the beginning
so
when the f native launched on android we
needed a new navigation library since uh
navigator ios did not work on android
so navigator was born
navigator was
fully javascript written and did not use
any native apis
and
this was
a little bit
more customizable than navigator ios
since it could change
a lot of stuff
but there was one major drawback with it
it did not use the animated api
so the problem is
when animated added support for native
driver you could not use a native driver
because
it used to call request animation frame
to drive its animations without using
the animated api
so the migration wasn't straightforward
so we needed something new
and we had navigation experimental it
was built by eric visanti from facebook
and it was part of reactionary code
it was a set of navigation related
components which are
now built with the animated api it was
very low level which allowed you just to
build own behavior on top of it like
our own navigation library on top of
this
it was very customizable but wasn't easy
to get started
i remember when i was using this api in
one of my apps i had a lot of custom
code
to like manage the navigation because
this library only manages the animation
not
not the logic
so
not long after
a new navigation library from wix was
born called react native navigation this
has fully native navigation library
worked on android and ios is still
maintained and currently at version 4
and one of the most popular navigation
libraries after react navigation
it introduced the concept of registering
screen
a separate groups
so each screen acts like its own
independent app
so this data is still accessible from
javascript you can use javascript to do
everything but
it still used some native apis and
some things were not possible
so next we got x navigation this was a
kind of continuation of navigation
experimental by expo
and
mainly built by brent batney and other
mischievous
similar to navigation experimental
it used animated api for animations and
implemented in pure javascript
this was also one of the first
navigation libraries
which supported multiple patterns such
as tabs drawer
etc and it was very customizable and had
a lot of features
but as all good things to do like
this also came to an end
uh it wasn't forever
so yeah the next big navigation library
was airbnb navigation
so this was built around brownfield apps
and it was to make um integration with
brownfield apps easier which airbnb did
a lot
so it was very similar to
native navigator uh react native
navigation by wix
and we have to register the screens uh
upfront like we can we do in weeks
so sadly now is no longer maintained
since since the airbnb is no longer
working with react native but
yeah it's
it's now up and down like a lot of
navigation libraries and recognitive
so
all of these libraries have their pros
and cons
i also didn't mention
many libraries because they are not very
popular and probably i i cannot like
mention all of the libraries that exist
in this presentation
but yeah
now it is time to come up with something
uh from the community something that
people who actively work with react
native maintain
so
the community facebook and expo came
together and
built a new navigation library called
react navigation
so it was very customizable adjust many
use cases
it was written in javascript only like
x navigation like navigator
but
the main limitation of this
library was a static navigation api
which prevented many use cases
it went through many major releases so
current version is the accommodation for
but the
core api
of defining the screens
statically
is still the same
so
even if all all of these things changed
the basic api stayed the same
so react navigation 4 is still used in a
huge number of apps
so
we are not going to duplicate it anytime
soon because
it will be like terrible to migrate all
of them to new reactivation
5 which which is completely
different api
so yeah we are still merging cool
requests for getting innovation for
and if while we are not adding any new
features it's still actively maintained
so yeah uh mentioning reactivation 5
after react navigation 4
the next thing we had was react
navigation 5.
even though it's still react navigation
i i thought like i should mention it
here
because it had a reimagination of the
code api so i think it's a
like
big milestone in the landscape of
navigation
so one of the biggest changes
was the dynamic api
instead of the old static api that
navigation for react navigation for used
uh recognition 5 had a new api which was
fully component based and it was dynamic
that you can
change only time
uh depending on state of drops
the code had to like go through a lead
to to be able to support this
and
it was like major undertaking service
the migration for the ethnicity
accommodation four to five isn't
straightforward because the whole api
for the navigation changed
while some apis remained
a lot of apis are like totally different
but i guess it was worth it
considering how how many pain points
it's solved like how many new use cases
it enabled
and people
tend to find it like a lot more
intuitive than the previous api
so now there is another major version
we introduced the academic project
navigation 5 here on react europe two
years ago
now it is time for the activation 6.
largely react navigation 6 maintains the
same code api as react navigation 5
and you can think of it as like further
polishing of the api on the code base of
what was in react navigation 5.
when working on like navigation 6 there
were a few things we wanted to focus on
the first thing was flexibility
many of the navigators accept some
customization as props
which means we cannot customize them
based on the
currently active screen
so for example here is a
video i have
where we have a bottom test
and
we have several tabs
we have contacts we have album
say i switch to the album tab
and you can see that
the whole styling of the tab change now
we have a translucent uh and dark
background tab bar
and the highlight color of the tab
change to white instead of blue
so
previously this was not possible at all
because all of the options we wanted to
specify were specified at navigators
level so
at navigator level you can have like
only one set of props so
we cannot change the background color
when you switch to album screen so
to make this possible we have to make
this all of these options customizable
per screen
so this is how we did it we had tabber
options property top on navigator before
and instead of using tabber options now
they are part of screen functions
so
now you can pass all of these things
inside screen options
but
you can also specify them in the options
prop of the screen so screen options is
the default for all of the screens in
navigator and options will be specific
to the screen
where you're using it so
with this we'll be able to have a set of
default for the whole navigator
and you can override those defaults per
screen
so we did the same thing for
bottom task material top tabs and drawer
so all of them instead of having tabber
options or drawer content options you
can specify all of these options in
screen options
it will also be simpler for users to
understand because
you don't get confused about what is
tabber options and what is screen
options
so
to make it more flexible we also
introduce a new library called react
navigation elements
so the activation elements is a set of
components and utilities that we use in
their navigation
uh but they're like exported for using
any any
any app or any library if you're
building custom navigator you can use
these or you can use this inside your
app
so we have currently header header back
button header title platform principle
and some other components and we'll be
adding more soon
and if you have ideas on what to add
then feel free this is not a like full
full-fledged component library these are
only components which are useful for
navigation
and integrations with navigators
so next thing is we wanted to simplify
some of the api and reduce the manual
work
the app navigation supports a lot of
customization and it's possible to
achieve many advanced things with it
and
you can do a lot of things but you have
to tweak things a bit
you have to play around with it a bit
because sometimes things may not be
obvious
but
what we wanted to do is like we wanted
to simplify some common tasks because
yeah if you want very advanced
niche tasks it makes sense that you will
have to like figure out things your own
but for common tasks if we just make it
one line it's much better for everybody
so
yeah one example of this was model
presentation style we introduced this in
the act navigation 5 and also in idea
navigation for
with
the activation stack version 2.
so to do
to use it you have to specify the
animation with the transition preset and
you have to
specify card overlaying able to true you
have to specify head or status bar
height so you have to specify all of
these things manually
now
with react navigation 6 all you have to
do is like specify the transition and
everything else will be set
automatically
so
you can still customize everything
if you want to but
the common case which is the native
model presentation styles from ios
you just need one line
so this is not all
another common example was when you set
a custom header on stack navigator
you have to also set header mode to
screen or
if you don't do that you have to handle
the animation manually
so
while
it's nice to have nice to be able to
handle the animation manually a lot of
people got confused that they had to do
that they
and they did not read the documentation
even if it was mentioned and we wanted
to reduce this confusion
and so
in react numeration 5 we could not do
this automatically because the problem
is we have this option for the header
but we also have header mode which is a
prop on navigator and these props cannot
be changed based on screen
so in the identification 6 which moved
header mode to screen options
and since we did that we are able to
automatically set it when you specify a
custom header
so
now it will default to screen when you
have a custom header you can only change
it to float
and if you if you need it
but the default will be screen when
you're using a custom header
another small thing is
when you had use header height it would
return zero if you had if you had a
hidden header hidden header
so in the activation 6 if you have it
inside a
nested stack and the pattern stack has
a header phone and the nested stack as a
hydrogen falls
now use header height will return the
height of the parent header which is
more useful
so
another thing is transparent model
for transparent models you also need a
couple of options now we have only one
optional presentation transferring model
and that's all you need for transparent
models of course you can also customize
it more
there are examples in the documentation
but the simplest case request online
similarly we added a new feature to
specify a background for bottom tabs for
example you can specify blurred view
or you can
specify a gradient or like an image or
whatever you want without having to use
the custom tab button or wrapping the
default tab
so yeah we we wanted to make this thing
simpler for users
and react navigation 6 includes a lot of
these quality of life improvements
so another api
we looked at is
uh
in a lot of us people wanted to
navigate from redux middleware on like
things which are not in components
and to do that they have to add a left
to the navigation container
but when you do that you have to manage
some things manually
for example you have to like make two
reps you have to check if the navigation
layer
was assigned and you also have to add a
delay to check if uh navigator
navigation was ready to be able to
disperse options
now we have like a create navigation
container that helper and also use
navigation containers hook
and it has all of these
set up automatically so
all you need is like just check is ready
on this dress
and then you call navigate on this
website which is much simpler than
before
so another thing we often noticed that
people nest their navigators a lot
sometimes due to necessity and sometimes
because of organization
we always recommend keeping listening to
the minimum when possible because of a
couple of reasons when you nest more it
becomes harder to do some things
for example
you have like typescript
there is a lot of a lot of
complicated code when there are nested
navigators
and when you are navigating you have to
like write
screen then pass patterns where you
specify the
name of the child stream so it also
becomes
more complicated as you nest more and
more
a flat navigation tree is much simpler
to use
if if you have the same
same amount of strings
so another reason is performance when
you nest more
on the performance decreases because
updating deep navigation trace is slow
and
also
listing a lot of views
is not not good for memory users in the
int native there are layout waves which
are automatically optimized out
but if you're nesting navigators
unnecessarily
um it's gonna increase the view count so
there is enough there is not a lot we
can do
so we wanted to minimize this uh
this
necessities by providing alternatives
so one of the alternatives yeah i mean
one of the use cases was
for nesting navigators is model and
regular screens
so earlier you had to have a model
screen at the root and then as a child
you have to have a regular stack
so you you put all of the modal screens
inside this model stack and all of the
regular screens inside of this regular
stack it was not possible to mix model
screens and regular screens
so
you had to have
two stack navigators
so we did some work to
make it possible so that you can use the
single stack navigator with two types of
screens
so now you can have one stack navigator
and
where wherever you want model you just
pass presentation modeling options
and that screen will be treated as a
model
so
in case of uh
here you don't need to invest anything
it's all possible in one navigator
but there is still the case of
organization maybe maybe you like to
keep all the models in one
one group
yeah so
what we did is we introduced a new
new api to group things
uh normally you can use the
react fragments for this but fragments
are couple of things issues i mean
they're not issues but they're more
readability thing because it's not
obvious
why you are using a fragment
like maybe
you read the quote and like there is a
fragment why is there
maybe if you add a comment it gets
clearer but
still
another problem is pregnant do not do
not pass options to their uh screen like
you cannot specify options like you turn
on your navigator
so if you have two navigators there for
all of the models you want like a blue
blue header or something like that so
you cannot do that when you're just
grouping their fragments
so we introduce a new api called group
and with group you can just like group
things inside
this group component
and you can also pass common options in
screen options to this group like you
can do on a navigator
and
you can even nest groups inside groups
so
yeah you can go crazy with like how much
organization you want
growth don't actually gain but anything
like fragments they are just used for
configuration
so it's not going to affect performance
like nested navigators too
so here you can see that we have two
groups we have one group for regular
regular screens and one group for model
strings
so another common reason for nesting was
headers previously
we
when we wanted to show a header in a tab
bottom tabs or drawer we had to nest a
stack navigator inside
because they did not render a header by
default
so what we do now is we render the
header by default in draw or bottom tabs
and
then you don't need to nest anything
because it's already there and for draw
we automatically add a button to open
the drawer for tabs
uh we don't add any button but
in both torrent apps the header will
represent the name of the current screen
by default so you don't have to handle
that manually so i think um as a whole
it simplifies things
you can of course hide this header if
you want
but it's there if you want it
so next thing is native navigation
historically like navigation and a lot
of precursors like x navigation
navigation experimental have been
javascript only
with animation sun just shows everything
written in javascript
it works for a lot of apps
this heavy heavy streams can suffer
so we also wanted to address this
concern
uh so we wanted to like promote use of
native navigation primitives
so with react navigation file we
introduced the native stack package
this native style package
from react native screens
and we also had uh
the viewpager backend for material top
tabs
and this backhand used viewpager2 and ui
pageview controller
so yeah we wanted to promote user ui
navigation controller for stack
on ios and fragment on android
and view pager to 100 for the material.
and ui pageview controller for ios
format top tabs
so
uh in react navigation file these are
these were optional and
i mean in reactivation 6 now we promote
use of native stack by default if you go
to react novation.org and you go through
the getting started guide
by default you will set up native stack
the diversity stack is still there and
still maintained
but
for new apps
we'll have the native stack by default
so you'll have better performance unless
you need more customization then you can
always go for the javascript best slack
navigation
so i wanted to thanks react native
screens from software mansion
made by christopher magera voidtech and
casper and
native strike is possible only because
of their native screen without their
work it would be possible
so yeah i want to thank them
and similarly i also want to thank
pilser
zero zero one zero
for the admitted pager wheel
it wouldn't be possible to
have a native backhand for metal top
tabs without their work
so
yeah thanks thanks everyone uh thanks
for making the activity better
so next thing we wanted to focus on are
the better types
react navigation five has much better
types than their connection for
but some things that as use navigation
were still untyped by default you could
like
navigate to
any random string and it will give you a
type error
so we wanted to change that and make
them more type safe
so now in the acquisition 6 you do not
need to annotate use navigation to get
auto completion on type checking
it is typed by default
but like it's not automatic
because we cannot know all of the
screens in your app automatically
you still need to change one thing uh
but like if you already have typing for
your navigation screens
it's just like
very few
changes to make this work
so it is possible by defining a type of
the
root root navigation
the navigator of the root
and it works by using a feature in fact
called declaration merging you can find
more about this feature how to use that
in our task related talks
so next thing we wanted to improve as
developer tools now we have a flipper
plugin for your communication
uh this is only working in reactivation
but this plugin includes similar
functionality to us currently in the was
currently available in the redux step
tools extension that we have
uh this data stream tools extension
works with both react navigation 5 and
react navigation 6
but
um the problem with uh reacted
later step tools extension is
that it is not our ui we are just using
the redux step tools so we cannot like
build anything we want so with this
flipper plugin since it's fully custom
built
we can add any any new features we want
we can
like here you can see there is a linking
tab
where it shows you the deep link
structure
another advantage of this triple plugin
is it doesn't need chrome debugger
so
when you are using chrome debugger some
things may not work properly
so this flipper plugin gives you a
better idea of
like how things are working
uh instead of this chrome debugger which
which may break things
unfortunately this playable plugin
doesn't work in expo but
it works in other react native apps
so yeah with every major releases there
is still question about upgrades because
everyone did this upgrades
while react navigation 6 isn't a huge
change over there navigation 5.
it's much smaller change than the
activation 4 to react navigation 5.
and there are still a lot of breaking
changes so there are a few things we can
do when updating to make things easier
so first of all
all of these changes are listed in our
upgrade guide we have some mandatory
breaking changes which you will have to
do if you are upgrading
we also have some duplication warnings
you don't have to do or change them
immediately
these things will continue working until
next major release but
they'll show you duplication ones which
you can ignore with your yellow box api
so another thing you can do to
simplify this migration is you can mix
versions from 5x and 6x
so generally it's not something you do
if you're starting a new application
but for upgrading
is perfectly reasonable and it will work
but there are some caveats
please refer to the upgrade guide for
the list of
cabinets if you're mixing these two
packages and as long as you keep these
two things and keep these things in the
mind
you should be able to mix those versions
so yeah go to our update guide and read
more about it we have a full list of
breaking changes full list of
duplication
and we also have the list of calgar's
when you're mixing 5x and 6x packages
so
just wanted to
mention few more things before i sign
off
we enabled github discussions on our
depot
so feel free to go there and talk with
other community members
developed and community
so yeah please participate in these
discussions answer people or like ask
questions
or like just share things you have done
with that navigation
so if you want to help um
you can help with code obviously but
there are a lot lot more things you can
do to help
so you can improve our documentation you
can answer questions uh on stack over
for github discussions you can try
issues uh check which issues are valid
which are not check the uh check the
reflow they have posted or if they
haven't you can ask for something or try
to make a difference yourself
or review full requests
we have a very small development team
for any any help
will help us a lot and it will be very
beneficial to everyone
another thing i wanted to ask is we
enable sponsorships for the
ignominication
and if react navigation is valuable to
you if it brings value to your company
consider sponsoring us we have twisted
any financial contributions and
sponsorships
so you can go here github.com
sponsors slash react navigation
and we have a lot of different tires
and you can sponsor whatever is
comfortable for you
okay so that that's all for now
and i thank you a lot
hope you have a nice day or nice evening
and hope you enjoy react navigation
thank you satya for this talk and i'm
really excited can't wait to actually
try these features on a application now
maybe this is a challenge for you but
let's see if we can uh challenge you to
do react navigation seven point x next
year if you submit a talk like that i'm
pretty sure you will be on our agenda as
well now let's move to another speaker
trolls and he is working at crown and
he's going to tell us about react native
going native and while this title may
seem like something very generic this
talk is about very interesting use case
when sometimes you have to do a bit of
native code while doing rec native in
their particular use case they were
building a podcasting application so
related to music and audio streaming and
they had to do quite a few things
natively to make sure that the
application works properly with the
system things properly
reacts to the native events and most
importantly works properly in the
background so there are cases when
sometimes you have to go native and i
guess there his talk is about these use
cases and when they are happening and
how to handle them so let's see how they
did that and how he made that happen in
his podcast app
hello everyone today i'm going to talk
about how you can leverage the native
sites in order to improve the
performance the readability and
maintainability of your react native app
some of you might know that airbnb tried
to integrate react native into an
existing app and coinbase recently
rewrote their app from a native app and
to a react native app today i'm going to
talk about another option where we
actually started off with the rack
native app and we moved some of it to
the native side
so a bit about me my name is troops i
work for a company called kirwan here in
norway where we make investments
available for everyone a shameless
little plug here if that's something
you're interested in we are looking for
react in ragna developers so please
reach out
other than that i've been using react
native since version 08 when
upgrading to a new react
version was actually opinion ass and ios
was only supported
i've also
built and maintained several rack native
apps for
for a period of years
and the project i'm going to talk about
today is a project called shift that was
started over three years ago
so before we dig deep into that i just
want to give you overview of uh what
this talk is going to be about
so i will start off giving your
introduction to shift dab so you can get
a better context of
of what app is about when i'm going to
show you the use cases of where we moved
code from react native to the native
site
and then i will talk a bit about the
motivation of why i wanted to have this
talk in the first place
then we will start off with the use
cases and then i will close off with
some closing thoughts so let's dig into
it
so the elevator pitch for shift
is that is a workout workout app that
lets you
shift within podcast and music
uh it all started over three years ago
when uh my friend and i wanted to carve
out more time for podcast in our daily
life so uh we figured that listen to
podcasts while we work out is is a good
start but really you can't really
listen to podcasts when you are working
out hard but the rest times in between
worked flawlessly so
what we did is that uh we built an app
that plays music and podcast and it's
all controlled by a timer so if you run
in 12 for four minutes it will play
four minutes of music when the
four minutes is up the app will
automatically shift to podcast and then
play podcast
for your rest time and then it will
shift back to
uh music when your rest time is up
so i guess that's enough talk i wanna
give you uh just
a short intro to the app as well just to
give you some issues it might be easier
to
to to understand what i'm talking about
so
let's go
this is the front page of the app you
have a portal section and a music
section
for music you can
either use spotify
or our own curated
mixtapes
for
podcast it's basically just a normal
podcast app where you have your
queue we have a set of discover
episodes and you can also import
podcasts from other podcast apps
but the most important thing for this
talk is the workout screen so let's
start a workout and jump right into that
so as you can see now i've started
working out and i'm in resting mode and
then i'm listening to podcast
so one thing uh
we have a couple of settings and some of
them are actually quite important for
this talk so remember them for later we
have setting where you can play
beep when it's
a given set of time left of your rest or
work period and we also have the same
for
for speech
so now i don't know if you saw it but
the timer just ran out and it
automatically uh shifted to music and
now we're listening to club live club
live by tiesto and another thing to
remember for later is that we also have
a notification that also shows the timer
left and uh
what is current plane
so now the timer will run out again and
it will automatically shift to
the podcast and you can see that the
notification is also updated
and
we also have a feature where you can
pause or what we call it freeze the
workout and you can unfreeze it and
these are
features that i will
break down
later in the talk in the
in the use case
so
i guess that's
enough
of that let's dig back into the
presentation
so uh the motivation
for me to
to do this talk was that
when we started
uh thinking about moving stuff from rec
native to the native side um
there wasn't a lot of good resources out
there there are resources on how to
create
native uis and to integrate them into
your native app there are resources now
to create
uh bridge but there we didn't find any
good resources on why you should do it
and that's essentially why i would like
to have this talk here today to try to
give you a tool in your toolbox that you
can use if you also experience the same
thing that's that we have experienced
there
and i want to give a shout out here to
my co-founder michael
gunderson uh this is what i'm going to
present there today is a team effort
that we have
done all together
so
uh
let's
dig into it
and before i start with the use case uh
it is important to know what the bridge
is in react native because that's
essentially the whole point
so in react native for you to
communicate with the native sites you go
back and forth
over a bridge
so an example of that is that if you
create a view and you for instance have
a style that will go
will be passed over to the native site
and rendered on the native side and if
you have inline styles for instance
react native need to sterilize that and
pass it over a bridge which requires
more of the bridge so if you have tried
to console log
a property on your style seat you will
see that it's a number and that's for
performance optimalization so majority
of the time everything runs smoothly
just like a real life bridge
but you can occasionally get traffic
jams and that's essentially what i'm
gonna show you here today
so
we have this concept of shifting
and
one thing that i actually didn't show
you but you can also press on this
button and that will automatically
shift to
uh to the other
music source and
if that happens
then
that
is catched by the javascript site
and
it goes over the bridge and pauses the
podcast because
how we uh play podcast we're using a
package called react native track player
on the native side so we need to go over
a bridge and pause the podcast
and that
in return resolves a promise when the
podcast is paused and then that gets
back to the javascript side then we can
start playing music
and the music does the theme so for
music we are using a package called
react native spotify to play spotify and
for mixtapes we are using a package or
we have
a package we built our own
and then the same process here it
returns a promise over a bridge when
the the play has started and we can
finally update the ui so you can see
here we are going a bit
uh back and forth over a bridge so this
is actually the best case scenario for
us
it's uh
it gets it gets worse so
a lot of clients said that they don't
want to they don't want to click
on this button in order to shift if they
don't have put a timer here
so
we implemented a way for them to do that
and that's with headphones so with
headphones you can press
play or pause you can
and it will
automatically switch and that that means
that we have set up
headphones
events on the native side and they catch
when the clients press on player pause
and that is emitted
over the bridge and then
it starts the same process
and the same
happens for
the beep that i showed you and also the
android notification in order for us
to
actually
[Music]
communicate
that you're gonna play a beep
then uh we pass
that
back over the bridge
in order to play the actual beep
and then now it starts to get
a bit of course over the uh over the
bridge but it's not much it's it works
perfectly but uh what i'm gonna show you
next is uh
is is our worst use case but before we
get there i wanna just give a bit of
background on what it actually actually
is so i don't know how many of you have
tried to
run a background timer
in react native when the app is also in
in in background so
it seems like at least it's 3 000 people
here who have had this problem or at
least looked for a solution and
what jose is
is mentioning here is that he tried to
use
package called react native background
timer
which we also tried to use but it had
some bugs at the moment and the the same
for us unfortunately
so
but as a good samaritan as jose's he
also
answers his own question
and that's
he actually computes the value he takes
computes the
the duration between two dates so he
takes the value
it takes the the
timestamp when
the app does something and when it
finished and then he calculates how long
the duration has been and that's
essentially what we do as well but we
have one more
uh problem for us
and that's
we have this timer loop because we
need to
uh actually check every second
uh what is going on we also need to
update the ui every second so every
second we are emitting an event over
bridge to the javascript side
and we update the javascript size and
update the ui it checks the counter if
the counter is zero it will
automatically switch
and we also
proceed some data every 15
seconds for instance we are persisting
uh the podcast position so that when you
close the app and open it again uh you
will
start where you
left off and now as you can see uh we
are sending an event over the bridge
every second now
uh
that starts uh
to blow the bridge
a little bit
so
how did we solve this
so i recently
stumbled upon this table on
the react native documentation and this
is quite important for in this talk as
well because as you can see here react
native has listed out a couple of
uh
components and what they are in the
native world and that means that react
native is actually compiling your views
into native code
and why that is important that is
because that's what we are going to do
as well we are going to create our own
native use in order to solve this
problem
so as you remember this was where we was
where we were we were meeting an event
every second over bridge and maybe based
on that we will go even more over a
bridge
so what we did is that we took the
duration
and the countdown timer and we moved
those to the native site and then we can
get rid of all the calls going
over the bridge so essentially what it
looks like then is that now we have a
main counter
which is basically the same as the as
the time loop from before
and then
that emits an event to account ui which
is responsible for just displaying this
and displaying this
and then we have something called the
shift master which is
responsible for the notification that i
showed you
playing a beep whenever
the counter is at the threshold
set by the user playing speech
and also when the counter goes to zero
it will automatically switch so you will
also have control over which audio is
playing and have a reference to
all the players
so this
is essentially
the architecture we went for and now we
are
not using the bridge
at all
but another uh
great thing that came out of this was
actually that
our codes got
much cleaner and the readability was
much better so i'm going to show you an
example of that
so
i've heard that you might not see this
and so i'll try to just go through it
briefly but the whole thing is the the
freeze or the pause mode that i showed
you earlier
the thing is that when
you press set and you start to freeze we
need to get the current timestamp and
also
do some calculations based on previous
timestamps and then when you
unfreeze
it will
use those timestamps and calculate what
the current uh countdown is and what the
duration is and
this was quite error-prone and you can
see we also have some sort of reporting
here that reports to century for us
and
this was really hard for us to debug
because we had events coming
on the bridge over bridge every second
and then
it was very hard to reproduce that
events came in a certain order so
after we did
this
rewrite this is essentially
what
that looks like now now we just have
a basic counter which
most people start off with when they
learn how to program the same as how to
do app i guess
and
it's just made our confidence
in the codes so much more and this is
just one of the examples of where our
scalability and readability increased
quite a lot
so
i just want to
emphasize
some of the key points i think it's
important for this talk uh before we
finish and
i hope that if there's one thing that
you will
take away from this talk is that
you will have another tool in react
native tool belts when you are gonna
when you are approaching problems so
this is the first time i've ever
experienced a problem like this
and
i
i don't think you will reach for this
often but i'm
i
it might be and that's also the as i
said in the motivation uh part is that
what i want to have this talk in the
first place to just show that this is
actually in is is
possible and
we also did
this
change
after three years of maintaining the app
so we had
we knew the ins and outs of the app we
knew where we had
problems
of bugs and where things were hard to
reason about the code and also
where things might fail feel a bit
sloppy
and
why do you think and the reason why that
is important
is that when you start
moving stuff from the native side like
from react native to the native side you
lose one of the biggest
uh
biggest things of frag native and that's
learn once and write everywhere because
now essentially we need to write every
feature
for
uh all the platforms that we support
and so
i don't think this is something you
should reach for whenever you have
a
problem like it you really need to think
think it through and make sure that this
is something that you would like to
maintain
for the period of the app as well
but another
important point for this is that our app
was not
did not perform poorly because going
over the bridge
as much as
as we did our app was
chosen as app of the day by apple we
were monthly promoted in the app store
as well and we're also invited to the
apple into a nerd program
so i'm actually i was very positive
surprised
how good react native is when you're
actually bloating the bridge as well and
how much
the bridge actually can manage
so i'm not saying that uh
so i'm saying that this is this might
not be something that you will do
that that often
and
another thing is that often when we when
i speak about the rewrite to other uh
people um a lot of
a lot of them are saying that
this is not for them they are
not comfortable
writing native code they are comfortable
in direct native world and i was the
same as well so i want to just share
a couple of tips on how you can dip your
toe into
into the
into the native side
so uh
what's how we started is that we took a
small problem and we moved it to the
native side and over time we saw how
that went and then we just start moving
more and more parts and now
each time i try to
each time i integrate a new react native
native package into my app i always go
and look at the score source code and
see how how they structure
their bridge how are they writing their
code and then i use that as an example
of
things i want to get more interested in
and i start to take the internet and
there's a lot of great resources out
there on how to create
native use correct for for deck native
and integrate them create bridge and
there's also great resources if you want
to pick up
android or ios
development and
at least for me going
going into the native site
has made me an even better react native
developer because now i have a better
understanding of how the native
platform works
so
that's it thank you for listening all
the way through and if you have any
questions for me please route reach out
on twitter
my handle is through science and yeah
that's it thank you
thank you jules very much for this talk
now
you know if there is a way we can make
react native show our podcast be played
while resting let me know we'll be
interested in making that happen
now moving on we got another speaker
suncat from geeky hands
he's going to talk about something very
important often overlooked which is
accessibility
um they have actually created a set of
hooks uh called regnative aria that lets
you build accessible apps with
less effort than usually so something
that you probably should all be aware of
and should be using to make sure that
your applications are actually okay for
people with visual impurities or any
kind of disabilities that accessibility
supports so let's learn about their
library and how mate did how they did
make that happen and how we can benefit
from it from within our applications
hey everyone i'm super excited to be
back at react native eu
and uh today i'm going to talk about
building accessibility hooks for react
native and web
i'm sanketh i'm a software engineer at
geeky hands and yeah i go by the twitter
handle sun kate sahu
you might have come across this tweet
which went viral
and yeah so that's me
and uh yeah so i'm tuning in from the
beautiful city of bangalore uh
i wish i was there
and i wish it was a an in-person
conference but yeah here we are
uh this nice illustration by abby buck
so thank you so much for that
uh so let's
get back to the topic and
try to decode that
building accessibility hooks for react
native and web first of all what is
accessibility
so
i went through the mdn docs and found
this which broadly defines what
accessibility means so it is the
practice of making your websites
uh usable by as many people as possible
i think the same applies to apps too so
it would be websites and apps making
them usable by more and more people
that's a very broad
broad definition so if we narrow it down
into like what are the characteristics
or what are the support
that you need to make your website and
apps accessible it would be something
like it should be
uh compatible with screen readers so
that
people with visual impairment or low
vision can can
use the screen readers and understand
what the app is all about or what the
website says
uh
and the same thing applies with contrast
ratio with people with low vision uh and
then we have responsive design like
the the app or the website needs to be
accessible on
uh mobiles like smallest mobile out
there and and to the like desktop and
maybe to the largest display out there
108 inches tv or something
and
keyboard accessible i think this
i i
really am fond of using keyboards a lot
and i use like
tabs and arrow keys a lot and
websites
that don't work uh with with keyboards
it's it's like really hard uh so let's
see what what are these things and how
we can enable these things in our
websites and apps
uh so yeah how to build accessible
websites uh and i'm going to talk
specifically in term in terms of react
so
straight to the documentation
documentation says that
uh web accessibility also referred as
a11y
uh it can be enabled we can work on this
and react fully supports building
accessible websites often by using
standard html techniques
so
what are these standard html techniques
so uh
w3c and wcag uh these are like
guidelines uh wcga cag is a guideline
that is provided uh
and and we can
like go through all the things that we
can do so it's usually with
attributes that you can add to to html
markup and that makes
uh the the particular page or app
accessible let's see an example for
example if there is an input box and
i would like that to
uh
to
make it aria compatible and make it
required for people who are using it
which just say screen readers
so i can pass in a prop called
arya hyphen required as true
and this is an html standard attribute
that is also supported in in react
if you pass that when we are using a
page with or this input box with a
screen reader it it says that this is a
required field
and we can also add a label something
like arya hyphen label and and drop in
some some label and it reads that loud
so
react and html standards for arya it's
it's more or less the same thing but
react provides
reactivity on top of it which makes more
sense so
let's see that in detail
so how do we create a component so a
component can be created by these five
steps that i always come back to writing
the markup doing the styling
and
adding interactions like handling events
and then handling the states
and last but not the least accessibility
let's take an example of creating a
checkbox component for the web
so
say
i want a checkbox so i'll wrap it in a
label
uh markup and then have input type
checkbox and some text around it
as step 2 i would add some styling
just with class names here no css and js
and
yeah so late next we can add interaction
for example on the right side you can
see like as as we click on the check box
it shows an alert message so
really standard stuff
input on change alert and then it does
the trick
next
let's make it
talk to the state and let the state
update
the the dom
how do we do it so create state and then
on change set that state and pass in the
same value in the checked value of
the input box check drop of the input
box
so as we do it we click on that and then
state is updated
and the screen
the component renders
last accessibility
so we have props like arya hyphen
checked arya hyphen labeled by that we
are going to use here in this input box
is uh
the same value that we passed to checked
prop in input we can use the same thing
and pass it to aria hyphen checked
so
with screen readers or with when we like
use
keyboard so
this says that the the current value
object box is checked
and the label also reads out we can have
area labeled by as as i agree
so
one thing to notice here is that
is the is the reacts component state
uh that is
building the initial ui
and it's not just the visual ui that it
is building it is also building the
accessibility
uh tree structure and and access it like
something that is not
that can't be seen by the users just by
the screen readers it also builds that
and whenever that that is being updated
it's
it's updating the state and that
reactively updates the aria values as
well so react is working for both the
things for the visual aspect of things
and and the non-visual aspect of the
things
which is super interesting
and here we are using standard input of
type checkbox so we don't have to do
much but
we can also make use of say something
like div
and make it behave like
a checkbox by
adding something like roll
is equal to say check box and then we
have our checked in there and labeled by
so
visually we can style a div
like a check box
but to make the browser understand and
the users of the browser understand that
that particular div is the checkbox we
can use role property
great uh let's move on so
let's see accessibility for mobiles
for ios and android and to do that we'll
you will use react native
so straight to the documentation react
native also provides a unified api for
ios and android to make the apps
accessible
for example we can
say that a view
which is equivalent to which is somewhat
like to div
accessible is equal to true so
as we do that
screen readers start
identifying this piece of this block of
code as accessible unit and it starts to
read out
uh
like text one and text two at the same
time in this example uh both the text
nodes are not accessible uh directly but
the view wrapper view is is accessible
and the sound
the screen reader reads contacts
everything inside that like text one
text to and it reads that out
uh
it also has focus management and things
like that
which which just maps
by using this accessibility accessible
is equal to true anyway
we have more props that can be used so
we have things like accessibility role
and accessibility label
and
yeah accessibility role and state
and value these three are like very
important that
makes the end users understand what type
of element they are they are focusing on
and then what's the current state and
what's the current value all these
things
apart from these three there are like
really important ones and uh
the the black ones are supported on ios
whereas the green ones are for android
so let's create a check box component
for mobile devices
so
standard react native
we'll use the pressable component we'll
create a nested view inside that and add
some text
then add an icon and style it with
standard react native stylesheet.create
and
then add handle the state on press
handle toggle
update the state and also update the ui
based on that state checked with checked
block checkbox marked and checkbox blank
outline
and then
we need to wire the same state with the
accessibility role so here we are using
accessibility role as checkbox and
accessibility state as checked
now this makes it work for screen
readers for the visual aspect of things
and it just works
so this is a very basic example of like
how accessibility can be enabled uh on
top of the existing ui
talk back on
not checked check box i agree
checked
so this is a quick example of like how
screen readers work when we have
accessibility enabled
uh how can we do the same thing for web
or can we write a unified uh
say markup or unified component that
works on both the platforms uh yes it's
pretty much possible we can use react
native web to map the same react native
api uh on the on the web and let's see
how that can be done so let's assume
that this is our dream api and this is
what we want to do like create a
checkbox component that works on all the
platforms it has it takes an is check
prop and it has on change handlers
that that sets updates the check value
and then it has text inside it that says
i agree
so to build this
and to make it
look
the same on web ios
android on an on android without losing
the capabilities of the native
accessibility on all these platforms how
can we do it let's see so
we can abstract out the
the
ui part and create a component say
custom checkbox ui that
that's a dumb component takes and
checked and then
uh gives us the the checked ui of that
we can pass in false for the check value
and just empties out the checkbox
great and
so
to make it accessible we have to write
some conditional code reactant web
handles it well
but
there are cases that where we will
have to write something specific for web
uh the first default thing that comes to
our mind is is handling the keyboard uh
versus handling the touch events
so here's a quick example of like how we
can make the same checkbox ui uh
like accessible on different platforms
so we can write some conditionals with
platform.os as web
and then write if it is web then use the
native input uh and and write the on
change and type as check box so this
does most of the trick like if we have
uh input as check box but
on the parent if we see we have
accessibility role as label
and this makes it tappable on the web
or maybe sorry clickable on the web
and here we're using the same custom
checkbox ui and if we have a look at the
input on change that component is is
wrapped in a visually hidden uh view so
it hides the the real input box and
shows the custom checkbox ui
while maintaining the accessibility
aspect of things because the wrapper
view at the top level has accessibility
role as label
great and for mobile phones we go ahead
and add accessibility role as check box
accessibility
state as checked
so
on the web where exactly are we handling
accessibility role as check box so we
are using a native input type is equal
to check box so that does the trick we
don't have to specifically notify that
we are using a check box
uh and then you update the state
accordingly
so this piece of code works on all the
platforms like for native react native
does the trick on web we are using a
native input box uh input type is able
to check box and then this works
so this is a very simple and a high
level
uh example of
of like adding accessibility
that works everywhere
uh there are more things to consider
the first one is definitely
keyboard interaction uh an example of
this would be when we are building say
combo box or select boxes
uh we focus that using tabs and then
when we press spacebar it opens up and
we can use the arrow keys up and down
and then press enter to select that
value then it closes the pop-up
that's one example and and this is like
one of the the hardest example when it
comes to adding accessibility to a
custom
combo box it also goes as a joke in the
community in the design systems
community anyway uh and then screen
readers we have to make it compatible
with the labels and all those things and
contrast ratio uh even the visual aspect
of things uh those with low vision can
they read the text
do we have like enough contrast ratio in
the foreground and the background color
uh we have more than this these are like
just few points and that's where the
a11y project comes in uh it's a very
nice project they have detailed down
like all the different aspects
of accessibility they also provide a
check checklist that any developer or
a team can can go ahead and check if
they are compliant with all those things
and yeah they have the
compliance in like three different
levels
uh
a double a and triple a
a is is essential uh sort of
accessibility that
all the apps and websites must adhere to
uh this can be something like adding all
text adding captions
uh adding
adding placeholder and and whatnot like
these basic things that that that is
like essential for for any app
or any website per se
then we have double a double a is a
little stricter than a it has all the
checklist of a but it has a few more
things for example it has
the
contrast ratio of text versus background
must be at least 4.5 to 1. uh so
yeah that's one thing then
then we also have uh
subtitles for the videos and few other
things and and this is like required by
multiple government and public body
websites
then we have triple a triple a is like
very strong level of
compliance this is like
uh for example it has a contrast ratio
of seven to one and then we have
if there is any video on the website
that has to have a sign language uh
support for
for people who can't hear so yeah these
three levels are really important to
understand and also
to cross check with the website like if
your app or website has falls under like
which category
anyway uh they also have a checklist the
a11y project for example for keyboard
they have like these three things make
sure there is a visible focus style for
interactive elements that are navigated
to via keyboard
uh then we have like when you press tab
does it like maintain the same order as
per the visual layout or does it like
jump from the first one to the fourth
one and then goes back to the second one
and then
a lot of things like this uh it's in
their checklist and they have a very
nice uh like write-up around it same
thing for mobile and touch do we have
like horizontal scrolling
if we rotate the screen does everything
like
reorganize well
uh so go ahead and check out the a11y
project
and
yeah so this brings me to
react aria this is a brilliant project
by the adobe team uh
reactaria provides a set of react hooks
that that anybody can
use to build like accessible ui
primitives for
their design system or for just their
component library
a huge shout out to devon who is heading
this project
at adobe
and
they also have another project in the
same
set of projects the
parent group of projects is called as a
react
spectrum
which has react aria and reacts stately
react stately is the state management
piece of of building these like ui
primitives for example we have use
toggle state as a as a hook
let's see that let's see one of the
examples so to build the same check box
if we're using react aria
so
we can use toggle state from stately
react stately and we can use
use checkbox from react aria
and
then we can have a label and input and
spread that input props that comes from
use checkbox right into the
input element
and yeah this does all the trick
of like making that particular component
accessible
with like keyboard with uh mouse on top
of it and and
uh for screen readers and and everything
also these hooks
are like service layers and
it's it's more like uh they don't
provide any ui so the
the keyboard handling or mouse handling
uh and the the
accessibility part of it all these
things are like abstracted out which can
be dropped into other ui components to
make them accessible and that's the
beauty of react aria
uh yeah so this is an example and we can
go ahead and use
like check box and
this this just works
it also gets all those props like is
indeterminate
and
all the things that a checkbox
has
great so
uh
then there's another project
this is called react native aria
this extends the support of react aria
to mobile phones
so
and this project a huge shout out to
nishan
he has worked
a lot on this project his is like a sole
developer but there were like people in
the team who helped him out uh and uh
yeah so
so let's see react native varya and how
nishan
and team they have built this react
native arya
so
react native arya is a set of react
hooks to build accessible ui primitives
for react native and web so very similar
thing
but it works for react native but with
the help of react native web it works on
like all the platforms
so here's another example so we can
import use checkbox from react native
aria
and then uh use toggle state
from react stately
and
then spread this input props
which has like on change on press and
accessibility state so depending on the
platform it returns if we need on change
or on press on press works for react
native
uh
and and on change
works on on the web so let's see so we
can use like visually hidden that's
another component that hides that that
particular input box that comes from
react area and then the custom checkbox
ui can be used and we just spread that
input props that's received from use
checkbox and
and pass it on
input
and the same thing also goes on the
principle component in in react native
and yeah so it handles like
uh most of the things for accessibility
right from
say
tab
like focus ring or handling the keyboard
interaction and check boxes again it's a
very simple example it gets really
complicated when we have like
a menu or combo box or
radio buttons
here is the the source code a very high
level source code that this hook
provides
it takes in all the props and state and
also the input ref of the check box
and then it
returns the input props that is actually
spread on the
on the pressable component if you see it
in the last slide pressable spreads
input drops
so all these things are passed back to
that particular
element
pressable and it adds accessibility role
and accessibility state
which is
picked up by react native
reactant expressible component
and on the website
so react native aria has a file for use
checkbox.web.js
so this is straight away imports react
arias checkbox use checkbox and then
exports it
the source code of react aria's checkbox
is something very similar to this but
instead of using react native specific
roles we use like arya hyphen check then
check
great so
we have a lot more
hooks that's available in react native
area
another example is use focus ring
this
adds the the focus ring on on uh
components so when using keyboard and
pressing tabs
uh we get the focus ring of the keyboard
which is independent of where the mouse
cursor is so we can use it like use
focus ring and then spread it right away
on the pressable component
next we have use hover use hover is
similar to use focus ring but
yeah this is straight away uh does the
trick of
spreading hover props like
uh
and all those things which makes it like
hoverable
great uh so that's then we have used
overlay position this places the
the the
overlay something like
a tooltip or a pop over
and yeah so we can use overlay position
and this takes in
the target element and also the overlay
element the ref of them
obviously and then places that gives the
props like top left bottom right
position of that
of the placement and it just really
works really well so we can use a
trigger component and then
click on the the button and then
it just places that
pop over
great uh so that's use overlay pop
use overlay position and then we have
more hooks like use combo box use slider
use menu use checkbox use group use
radio
and
yeah switch tool tips and pop over
great so this is a joint effort i would
say that
that nishan and team they have like
worked on something on the react native
side and then mapped back to react aria
for the react
uh system
and yeah we have uh
put all these things in in uh ui
component library
uh on the next version of native phase
so native base essentially is mobile
first
accessible components for react native
and web
this is based on the utility first
principles and react native aria is used
here with
with many components of of native phase
to make it accessible and also to make
it work
on all the platforms so native based
components works on ios android and web
and it also behaves natively like with
tabs with a hover and
a lot of platform level things
uh
yeah so
the checkbox example that we had in the
earlier slides is actually available in
native phase and we can
go ahead and use it
and yeah here is another example that
uh is to create
a menu component it's uh
really hard to make menus
accessible like pressing enter a space
opens up the menu and then using the
cursor it goes so let's see that example
how this is done so we can
yeah we can press enter and then type
event like rm and and all those
things to filter out or hover that
particular menu
so let's see it again enter and then
down and then we can type r and then m
and it takes us there this is this is
what we developers do most of the time
isn't it
and the same thing works for the
for screen readers on on different
platforms so this is an example of
android uh let's see that i hope you can
hear it
tapped
new options menu button
pop-up window menu item ariel
menu item to homework disable
menu item roboto
expo
no options menu but great so yeah that
those were like few of the examples from
react native aria being used in native
phase and
this is the team they have worked really
hard on building
uh react native aria plus native phase
and yeah it's open source go ahead and
try to use it uh all ears on the
feedback
uh yeah the team is trying to build it
like compatible for all the platforms
it's a hard problem to solve to be
honest uh but yeah let's see how far we
go
that's all from my side yeah there are a
few projects that you would like to
check from the same team
uh from
that there's a state management library
called sync state then we have react
pluggable a form library using mst forms
t and then uh builder x that's the
design tool that codes and yeah api
beats great so uh that's all from me i'm
sanketh and go ahead on and let's let's
connect on twitter my dms are open yeah
that's all for now thank you so much
thank you sanket for this talk and once
again i'm really happy that you're
working on something like this i
understand that sometimes these are not
the most important or hottest topics but
are very needed for our community to use
now we had four talks in this panel and
seven in total so far so i feel like
this is good moment to make half an hour
break so you can take this time for
whatever you want from refueling your
whatever you are having in your mac
right now or just socializing with other
attendees on our discord channel which
is i guess the most important and fun
part you can also ask questions to our
speakers they are on our discord channel
so some of the questions can be
addressed right now the rest will be
addressed on our react native show
podcast so we'll see each other in half
an hour and have a good break
this conference is brought to you by
codestag react and react native
development experts
[Music]
man
perfect
[Music]
[Applause]
hello
[Music]
hello i'm mike cyrio and co-founder at
call stock and today i'm looking for the
best react native developers to join my
team besides working on high-end
software used by millions we also
contribute to many opus projects such as
react native paper react native testing
library or repack and so you will have
an opportunity to develop your skills
and knowledge within these projects as
well as move your own ideas into life by
taking part in our r d program we are a
great team full of people crazy about
react native technology and we can't
wait to share our knowledge and
description with you trust me it's great
to be part of such a team so don't wait
anymore join us check out the job
description and in the link below and
apply and i'm hoping to see you soon in
our call stack office or maybe remotely
depending on your location bye bye
[Music]
so
wake up in frostwolf get up and get at
him
react native eu is on and it's happening
check in to check up on all of the
latest news and strategy man it's kind
of the greatest
and welcome to reacquainted view 2019
[Applause]
keynotes that unlock a new world of
insight lightning talks this cutting
edge it really seems so right
networking with everyone in the react
native community from the thinkers to
the linkers we're all here in unity
q and a's that dive deep into cold dna
and it's all covered here in only two
days
especially when it comes to trouble
after the last session we're gonna party
okay
food drinks with good vibes and dope
karaoke
[Music]
high fives all around it was good to be
here
[Music]
can't wait to the next one we'll see you
next year
[Music]
uh
hi it's me again we just wrapped up our
second session today and we heard from
amazing speakers like ola satya trolls
and sunket two of which are actually my
colleagues from call stack and i'm
really proud of you
that you gave such an amazing talks
and actually if any of you want to join
team at callstack go to our website and
find out more there we are constantly
looking for new employees for new
react native developers
and while you're there you can check out
our blog we publish a lot of cool
technical stuff we have a react native
show which is a podcast and we have a
lot of
conference talks and other video
material on our youtube channel called
stack engineers
and
yeah you can also do go to our discord
channel uh we have a networking session
right now uh where we can discuss all
the talks that are happening today
and also you can ask questions that will
be answered in the
dedicated react native show episode
uh also please go to twitter right now
and tweet react native eu
so that you can let everybody know that
you are having a great time with us
today
okay it's enough of me talking i'm going
to grab some lunch and i encourage you
to do the same
we'll see each other here again in
20-something minutes don't miss out on
our next bunch of talks that we have
prepared for you
[Music]
do
so
[Music]
this conference is brought to you by
codestack react and react native
development experts
[Music]
this conference is brought to you by
codestag react and react native
development experts
[Music]
man
perfect
[Music]
[Applause]
look at this garden
hello
[Music]
hello i'm mike serio and co-founder at
call stock and today i'm looking for the
best react native developers to join my
team besides working on high and
software use by millions we also
contribute to many opus's projects such
as react native paper react native
testing library or repack and so you
will have an opportunity to develop your
skills and knowledge within these
projects as well as move your own ideas
into life by taking part in our r d
program we are a great team full of
people crazy about react native
technology and we can't wait to share
our knowledge and description with you
trust me it's great to be part of such a
team so don't wait anymore join us check
out the job description and in the link
below and apply and i'm hoping to see
you soon in our callstag office or maybe
remotely depending on your location bye
[Music]
wake up in vroswolf get up and get at
him
react native eu is on and it's happening
check in to check up on all of the
latest news and strategy man it's kind
of the greatest
and welcome to reacquainted view 2019
[Applause]
keynotes that unlock a new world of
insight lightning talks this cutting
edge it really seems so right
networking with everyone in the react
native community from the thinkers to
the linkers we're all here in unity
q and a's that dive deep into cold dna
and it's all covered here in only two
days
especially when it comes to trouble
after the last session we're gonna party
okay
food drinks with good vibes and dope
karaoke
[Music]
high fives all around it was good to be
here
[Music]
can't wait to the next one we'll see you
next year
[Music]
uh
so
[Music]
this conference is brought to you by
codestack react and react native
development experts
[Music]
welcome back after a break uh for me
with lunch break so i feel like i got a
lot of power to guide you for the next
panel of talks which is going to be the
last one today but equally exciting so
we got four talks in front of us so
let's fasten your seat belts and let's
get started
our first speaker milka she's going to
talk about um
the journey of going native from react
so i guess this is an important talk to
all of you that are react developers
right now and are interested about react
native and want to start developing
react native or native apps in general
so if you are about to do that step or
maybe you have already completed your
journey from react to react native you
will feel like this joke
is going to probably have a lot in
common with your experiences
so let's
let's let's see how
she did her journey and how she
transitioned from react to react native
and how we can benefit from her
experience to maybe potentially make
this journey faster for ourselves as
well in the future
hi everyone my name is milita and today
i'm going to talk about react developers
in the wild world of native apps
a little bit about me i'm a software
engineer with experience working on
react and react native application you
can find me on twitter and instagram as
melee code i'm working in a company bad
in soft in serbia located in the city
niche with a strong tradition in
engineering and technology
and in one of our projects we need a
mobile application for ios and android
and you chose to go with react native
because the faster development you have
you will go to single code base for two
applications both ios and android but it
also has one more advantage and that is
the usage of react with all of its
benefits including the wide community of
web developers
however it's a whole new world because
the mobile development is totally
different adventure so in this talk i
would like to go over all the
differences challenges and advantages to
keep in mind when diving into the native
app universe
let's start starting with react native
comes naturally for react developers
because of all of the similarities you
have you will still use components as a
building blocks you still have state and
probes you will still use jsx and you
have the state management so you can use
redux or context api
but when you start going deeper we can
see more differences and challenges we
have to learn
and
you will see that the mobile world is a
completely whole new world and a whole
new adventure so let's start with that
adventure the first one is go for web
development you only need a browser for
mobile development you will require to
run your code on some sort of mobile
device for web you're familiar with
browser it's easy to just open a browser
and start developing and testing but
when it comes to native developers you
must always think about the platform ios
and android you can use android amoled
emulator which you can download from the
android studio or ios simulator which
you can use from the xcode so
simulators are good when it comes to
testing or building application
but we have some cases in our projects
when our future we are developing and
testing on the simulator and emulator
and everything was working fine
but when we start testing on the real
device we will see that
everything goes smoothly
so
because the simulation can never
replicate 100
of the hardware on the real device
so you can find your application working
without any error on the simulator and
having trouble with an actual device
so my advice is that i can give you is
to always test your application on real
devices through the development process
especially if you want to release on
both ios and android
so the next difference you can see is
styling
styling on the web you will use the css
you have a class name that's associated
with the dom element the css will target
the that element with the class name and
assign set of properties and values to
the social element on the react native
eric native does not use css installing
styling in react native is done using
the javascript since react components
have support for the style property you
can also create an object of style
values and pass them on the component as
props
and style names works exactly the same
name as in the css except they're
writing in camel case
but don't worry flexbox is still here
for example flexbox will work the same
way in the css with a few exceptions the
flex direction is defaulting to the
column instead of the row and the flex
is only support a single number as a
parameter and under the hood flexbox is
implemented with the yoke
and one more thing about styling is you
can use the
popular css in js library and that is
style components style components allows
you to write an actual css code styler
components and benefits of using style
components are that you will have css
syntax out of the box you can use
dynamic styling you can use steaming and
with style components you can also
support more complex styles like
transform which is really great so if
you're familiar with style components
and you can use it on the web before my
advice is to go for it
and let's talk let's talk about one more
big difference and that is navigation in
the browser world you have the url you
will have a current page you will have
to go back with the back button
and you if you're using react on the web
you'll probably use react raptor in the
react native react router has still
support for for the navigation
but you can use libraries like react
navigation or react native navigation
and
having pages and going back on a history
is not situation on the native world and
you must always have that in mind
in the native world we have screens
instead of the navigation between them
and for navigation between screens we
will use the patterns like tab
navigation tech navigation and backstar
stack and navigation works like you are
having a different decks of cards where
cards are screened so you will define
different decks of screens for each
purpose and this is because the user
could add or go back to a previous
screen it's important to note that on
native you start from the first screen
defined in the deck and when you add
screen it goes to the top of your deck
when you go back it goes off the top of
the deck as well and this means that the
first screen is loaded on the background
till you dismiss stack or go back
so have that in mind always you're not
using pages you're using screens and the
navigation is really different you can
always associate your navigation to the
decks
as i described so have that in mind
the next one i want to talk about is the
platform specific codes so unlike react
react native others the needs to write a
different code on different platforms
and build applications that follow a
platform-specific ui and ux guidances
so react native offers two alternative
ways to build the clause platform
application more efficiently the first
one is platform module so react native
provides a module called platform to
detect which platform or which version
of platform you're developing on joint
the application is currently running so
this is especially useful when you're
using a component that contains small
parts of the platform-specific
codes
and you can import the platform from
reac native and set some kind of
condition to check that if
you're using the ios or entrant and the
second way to check is platform specific
extensions so react native will load the
matching files for a specific platform
by automatically detecting whether the
file you're working on has ios or
android.js extensions and this way you
can be sure that each time you're coding
for ios or android react native will
always impose the correct required
component
and have that always in mind the next
thing i want to talk about is react
negative application state and this is
one more thing you don't have to worry
about on the web and that is important
to think about when you're working with
mobile application and that is
application state because user can have
application in the background or use it
uh in the foreground and this is very
important because you don't want the
user putting your application in the
background and when it comes back to you
want to show something or to update your
state and users back and forth on your
application is very common and you must
always think about that
you can use application stats from reac
native so it can tell you if your
application is on the foreground or
background and notify knew when states
change
so with app navigation from react native
you will have the three states the
active when the application is running
in the foreground the background where
the application is running in the
background and the user is either in
another application on the home screen
or on another activity and you will have
the inactive when the state occurs when
transitioning between foreground and
background and during the periods of
inactivity
maybe
some multitasking view or some incoming
call
so always have that in my mind when
developing your application to check the
application state and to check if your
application is in the user foreground
and backgrounds this comes really handy
the next thing i want to talk about is
the native features there are many
native features mobile has to offer like
push notification camera on the web too
many of those are not used so often but
when building an application you must
think of when you want to ask user
permissions for those or how to handle
those permissions for future on your
applications
for example when
you're asking for user permissions for
the camera in order to update the their
profile pictures you will have to check
every time
for yourself for permission because user
may have pressed or not give the
permissions so
think that i think about that as well
and the next thing i would like to talk
about is the network
uh when we are talking about the mobile
devices your connections may be slow
unreliable on non-existent and you must
build your software to support these
cases
beginning with connectivity prompts and
including offline methods such as
caching
so be prepared for the possibility of
the connections breaking in the middle
of network activity
so the great user experience is that you
will always show in your application
some sort of the
text message and maybe icon or some sort
of offline screen that is showing that
your
connectivity is bad or non-existent that
you're offline and
you have that to show your user that
application maybe does not working as
well because you don't have the
connectivity great so
think about that as well and when you're
talking about network i one thing i want
you to check out is the package
net info the package provides
information about the users active
network connections and collectivity
status of their mobile devices it also
identifies the user current network type
such wi-fi
and then we are using the net info
packaging uh in our application to check
the
network type so you can check it out and
use it in those cases when you want to
check the the network on
on your application and so everything
runs really good
so the next thing i want to talk about
is sharing code so if you're building
both web and
mobile application you can leverage some
of the codes reuse so if you're
converting a react native application to
react you can use a react native web to
bring a mobile application to the
browser it will require some significant
modification to perfect your port as
well and some adjustments for the user
interface and there's also another way
of sharing and using code and that you
can build your application and share
code
and share logics between web and mobile
react and react native and you can build
the components independently of the
platform
and so think about that as well
that is one of the way uh so so you can
reshare share your code on reuse your
code and talk about sharing code i have
to mention the monorepo monorepo allows
you to have the multiple projects and
share common dependencies instead of
installing the dependencies for each of
them
and this
also simplifies sharing code between
your projects allowing you to import
code from one package to another
and you might want to have a monorail
containing a website a mobile
application and some shared comb between
them and one of the most popular options
to do that is to use the yarn workspaces
and talking about monorepo i want to
mention one more thing to check out and
that is learner learner is tool for
managing javascript project with
multiple packages
so my recommendation is to check it out
we use it in our application when we
want to
have multiple packages and uh to share
code between
web and mobile applications so it's
great thing to check it out also
and talking about welding mobile one
more thing i want to talk about is
testing so programmers and developers
are also humans and humans makes mistake
and testing is important because it
helps you to uncover these mistakes and
verify that your code is working it also
gives you confidence that your
applications is working and it will work
in the the production your code is
working your components are good and
when you're writing test tests uh the
default template of react native ships
is just
so if you use testing before on the web
you will probably use chests so that
things is
similar and doesn't change and when
you're testing with jess i have to
recommend some libraries for writing the
unit test of your
native application that is libraries
like test renderer or react native
testing library those two are really
great libraries and you can check out
and see what is working
for your application so
always have in my testing also
and
one difference about i want to talk
about is debugging so for debugging you
can use the chrome developer tools to
debug your javascript code in chrome so
that thing is not different from the web
that is like
you're common to debugging in the
browser so everything is fine but one
thing i want you to
check out is the flipper flipper is
extensible mobile application debugger
flipper is a platform from debugging ios
and android and react native application
it can help you to visualize inspect and
control your application from a simple
desktop interface
so i strongly recommend flipper for
mobile developers with flipper you will
also inherit the plugin ecosystem that
exists
for native android and ios applications
this means that you will be able to use
plugins that are aimed for native apps
for react native app as well like you
will have
plugins will include the device logs the
device crash report something that was
really useful in our applications to
inspect the network request that is like
really great
so um one more thing you can check out
is the device perform preferences you
can check the cached images you can
inspect native layout elements and my
strong recommendations is to use the the
flipper it really helped us in our
application as well
and one of the biggest changes when when
we are when we are going from web to uh
to native
is the
deployment on the react native side we
are using the native way of
deploying applications so remember that
react native is only a tool for writing
native apps you will have to build and
upload your build for
if you're using ios to app store you for
google to google play store and for
huawei to app gallery so after your
build is upload for example apple will
run some automated tests on your
application for basic info providers for
the app store
and let you know if there are some
issues and after this everything is okay
you can use applications with other
developers through a program apple
provides a test flight and test flight
is the way to send your application
somewhere for testing without plugging
device on your machine and test fly
really comes useful when it comes to the
better programs and better testing your
application and it's very important to
know that each deployment will need to
pass some validation from apple that
will take some days in order for your
release to be available and to end user
to go through testing phase
and for google you will use the google
play console to publish your
applications and maybe games for the
google play
uh
so
yes and one more thing to
also mentioned here is the code push
code push is part of the app center and
codepers is in the app center cloud
service that enable the react native
developers to deploy mobile applications
and updates directly to user devices
so if you have some cases
when your tester needs bug fix really
fast and you don't want to wait for the
build and everything you can push it
directly using the code push and the
test i could get check it directly so
code push is really great and i strongly
recommend you to to check it
so that will be it um overall yeah i
strongly recommend for all the all the
react developers
who are thinking about going on the
mobile and the native to go with react
native to dive deep into the native
world and
so that's all for me thank you all if
you want to contact me you can use
twitter and instagram so that's all bye
thank you milika for this talk uh it's
always great to listen how people are
moving from react to react native at
call stack we are also looking for react
developers and we kind of kind of do the
same steps for them as well with them
together and we i feel like
part of great
like one of the great things about react
native is that it lets you actually
build mobile apps as a react developer
that's how i started on android myself
for example now moving on another
speaker john from expo is going to talk
about expo features and how you can
benefit from it but these features are
going to be different from what we
usually hear normally we talk about expo
when we think about you know just
getting started sometimes
we may even talk about expo being good
for beginners or having just great set
of libraries and features to make you
build your application faster but there
is also another dimension of features
that you may be interested about which
is about configuring your project
sharing it with your team members
submitting it to the app store and
generally speaking managing all the
things that are not related to coding
itself so as you can see expo has a lot
of interesting offerings for you related
to the devops and management of the
application as well
that go beyond the libraries that they
have in their expo sdk so let's learn
about what john has to say today about
these features and how we can take
advantage of that with our daily
projects
hey everyone my name is john samp and
i'm a software developer at expo and
today i want to talk about how to
iterate faster with expo
i started thinking of this idea because
of an app that i use named tweetbot this
is an app that shows you your twitter
timeline with a nicer design and a bunch
of other features that i find really
nice and convenient
i've been using this app since the early
days and it used to look like this this
design is really something and a relic
of a pastime that i think is really cool
i love the skeuomorphic icons and i like
the glow around the different elements
but i know i can confidently say that if
i were to ship an app that looked like
this today my users might think it's old
or
antique
so
tweetbot also had to update the look and
feel of their app if you remember when
ios 7 came out they introduced this
design language of really thin line
icons and everything being very flat and
so tweetbot followed suit
and just like that they also made a very
current version of this app that looks a
little different that has some of those
same elements from tweetbot three that
has those thin
line icons but now the icons are a
little bit thicker and things still look
clean we've got soft shadows which is
like something that's very in design
right now
and looking at the spread of these
different designs it got me to realize
that tweetbot has to change to match
what its users expect and what the
current design language and philosophy
looks like today and they've really had
to iterate a lot they've had to take
these features and change what they look
like constantly
this means that the first version of our
apps can never be the final version of
our apps it would be so nice just to
design something and to build something
and have it be done but that's not
really how apps work they're living they
have to change and they have to evolve
so to allow our apps to do this what we
really need to do
is we must embrace iteration and we must
think about how our apps can change over
time to better match what our users want
so let's talk about what iteration looks
like in a react native app
here's what i think it looks like first
you start with requirements what your
app should actually do after that
there's the implementation of those
requirements then you review that your
implementation actually fits the
requirements then you would make a build
of your app you'd submit it to app
stores and then once users have it
they're going to tell you things that
are wrong and things that could be done
better so you're going to be fixing bugs
and adding more features and making new
requirements and then this whole cycle
starts over again
so usually we can get this circle
spinning somewhat and hopefully add a
good clip but what if we could make this
circle go even faster i think we can do
that with tools that expo provides
so let's start with the first thing in
this wheel which is requirements and so
together today we're going to build an
app together and this app is going to be
a coffee app so let's brew a coffee app
together
[Music]
so let's talk about the requirements we
need to implement to make a great coffee
app
the first one is we need to know the
amount of water we need to the amount of
coffee we need when making a pour over
coffee and we can measure that with a
scale usually a great ratio is 16 to one
so 16 units of water to one unit of
coffee one thing that's kind of hard to
do in the morning especially when you're
feeling a little groggy
is trying to say okay i've got 27 grams
of coffee all right what is 27 times 16
so i can figure out the amount of water
so that's one problem and one
requirement we will have for our coffee
app the second requirement is around
pulse pouring so pulse pouring is
pouring a certain amount during a
certain duration during the brew and
usually you'll pulse pour three to maybe
six times throughout the brewing process
so our app should also count down and
guide us through the brew and tell us
how much to pour and when so those are
our requirements that we're going to
implement today
the next step is implementation of our
app the first thing to implement our app
is to start an app
we can do that by installing expo cli
globally with an npm install global
command after we do that we can run expo
init coffee app this is going to result
in a folder structure that looks like
this on our computer
on the left you can see the directories
the expo init made and this is exactly
what happens right after running expo
init we've got an app.tsx file a few
assets and just a couple other standard
files in our project directory notice
that there isn't an ios in an android
folder full of native code expo is able
to handle that stuff for us which can
make our implementation much simpler and
then later down the line if we need
native code or custom native modules we
can always add them
next up we want to start our app which
we can do with yarn start and through
the prompts we can open up an android
emulator and an ios simulator to let us
preview in real time the changes that
we're making to our app.tsx now one
thing that would make this a little bit
better and one problem i've had in the
past is when i'm developing something in
a simulator and then i actually open it
on my phone after building it and
getting it onto my device is that
sometimes it appears a little bit
differently so it would be great if i
could actually see the app on my phone
right now and expo allows us to do this
and to me this is such a big step in
iteration during development you can
download the expo go app and then when
you run the yarn start from the command
that we did earlier you can use your
camera app to scan that qr code which is
going to open up your app a development
version of your app inside of expo go
once it's in expo go and you make a
change to app.tsx you'll see it appear
almost instantly on your actual device
what a wonderful way to test the stuff
that you're actually using in the stuff
that you're actually developing
so
i should mention we've been talking
about expo a lot i work at expo so
what is expo exactly
expo is a company that builds free open
source tools and also hosted services
that help you build an application with
react native and it might be helpful to
talk about what is react native exactly
and what is expo exactly
so here on the left react native is a
set of component apis i think its main
job is to render jsx from react into
native views on android ios and also the
web
it comes along with a small
unopinionated core it's got great
third-party libraries that you can plug
in but it doesn't come with a lot of the
extra stuff you need to build a full
application and that's where expo comes
in expo provides a component sdk tools
like expo go like we just showed you and
also services to build submit and update
your app it is powered by react native
and sits on top of it and hopefully
along with both of these you can create
incredible applications
so at this point we've got some
requirements of what we need to build
it's always great to start with a design
i actually spent a while designing what
this app could look like and i went
through a lot of different iterations
and i ended up making designs and then
implementing them and this is what they
look like so on the left i'm
implementing requirement number one i
ended up putting a question of how many
ounces of coffee would you like to brew
first so you can say maybe i want 24
ounces and then below it tells you how
much water to heat and how many grams of
coffee to grind
on the right
this fulfills requirement number two
which is pulse pouring
once you tap start it'll do a countdown
timer and then tell you how many grams
of water to pour over your coffee and
when throughout the entire brew process
this makes every brew really consistent
and if you can replicate a really great
process every time you can wake up with
a beautiful cup every morning
also when testing this app it's
definitely a caffeinating process
you could say i was maybe a little bit
shaky after all of this
so the next step is how do we review our
app now that it's built how do we make
sure that the requirements are actually
implemented
this is a problem i can test it myself
and think like okay this is looking good
but how can i let my teammates and my
colleagues try this
if i wanted to do this manually what i'd
probably do is create an ad hoc archive
at least for the ios side i would add
the allowed devices through the apple
developer ui and i would also then build
an apk for my android users after that i
would have to make builds of my app and
then i would have to distribute them
either by giving my team download links
or distributing them via the play store
internal track or via test flight for
ios
but there's a better way to do this and
we can distribute our app faster to our
teammates with this solution which is
called internal distribution
if we let xo handle our credentials and
the whole process of this and expo can
also build our app we can distribute it
to our team even faster let's look at
how this works
so
the first thing we need to do is install
something called eas cli which stands
for expo application services
and eas
is the services part of expo that will
help set up your app for internal
distribution
the next command to run is eis device
create and this is going to
add a device to your credentials that we
will then manage for you so every time
you make a build you can say okay i've
set up this device previously make sure
that this build is built for that device
that i set up that i actually connected
to the provisioning profile is what it's
called
after that i can run a command called
eas build profile internal and this is
going to create two different builds for
me that are set up to work with those
credentials which enables me after these
builds are done to do something like
this where i can just send a link to
someone and say hey try my app and then
go to this link and then download the
app that i just built and they can
sideload it on their phone so what this
whole process looks like is registering
a device then making a build and then
you can send a link to download and that
makes this whole process much faster and
allows people on your team to try your
stuff faster and if you can try
something faster you might try more
features you might try stuff that you
wouldn't try before and this iteration
is going to help us make an awesome app
now we can automate this process even
further by setting up a ci action expo
has something called the expo github
action and we could make a ci action
that looks sort of like this where we
set up eas to build every time we merge
our code into the main branch
our expo action will install our clis
and we'll we can then install our
dependencies and then we can say let's
build for all of our platforms and then
also build the internal builds so every
single time someone merges to main we
can go and test our changes
now there might be an even faster way to
test our changes which is using expogo
and publishing our app with updates
so how does this work we can do
something called expo publish on our app
locally and when that occurs we build a
bundle of all of the javascript code and
all of the assets in your app and we
make that into an update bundle that is
stored on xbox servers then when you
open up expo go
you can see i have this coffee app and
if i click on this thing that says
default right here it's going to open up
that coffee app in expogo itself so
anytime i have a change i can run expo
publish
and then that change will be visible
right here in the app without me needing
to download another build
anyone in your organization that's
logged into expo go can access that app
which makes it super fast to share the
experiences that you're developing and
we can make this even faster just like
before by using that same ci action that
we showed previously but this time using
expo publish
so that makes that iteration cycle super
fast and it also after we've tested it
with our colleagues and our team
means we're ready to build our app
for the app stores
so the problem that we want to solve is
how can we distribute our apps easily to
the app store it's all built now we've
reviewed it it's ready to go what steps
do we have to take hopefully not that
many if we were to do this manually at
least for ios we'd want to enable the
app transport security we'd have to
configure the release scheme and then
we'd have to build the app locally for
release and that is a lot of steps and a
lot of configuration you have to deal
with
instead we could use eas or expose
application services to do this for you
and your team and in the cloud which
will hopefully make it an even easier
process and one where you don't have to
set up everyone's computers identically
to make this happen so let's look at the
steps to do this
we can use eas build and then pass in a
profile called release which is set up
when you run eas build and that's going
to create two apps for us one optimized
for the ios app store and another one
for the android app store or google play
then on our website we can see some ui
where you can see all the builds that
have ever been made for your app you can
download that build and you can also
submit that build which is the next step
of our process
if you were to submit manually
we would have to at least for android
download the aab file and then open up
the play store console and drag and drop
that thing in there and then we have to
wait for it to upload make sure that
everything is good
same for ios we'd have to download the
ipa file and then we'd probably open up
a program like the transporter app and
then we'd have to drag and drop that in
there and wait for it to upload and see
if any logs these are just manual steps
that we have to do you could automate
this
but it would take some extra work
so instead eas provides a command called
eas submit and we've actually set up
this automation for you already so you
don't have to deal with this process
yourself
and you can take builds that you've made
with the eas and then run eis submit and
you can say take the latest build that
i've built and then it will take that
build and we will update or submit it to
the app stores for you this is super
convenient and makes building and
submitting to the stores really quick
and it really
speeds up our iteration cycle for those
two steps of the iteration process
so our app is now out in the store
and we've actually found a bug or let's
at least pretend that we did
a popular way to brew coffee is using
something called an aeropress but let's
say that instead of writing aeropress we
accidentally wrote sparrow dress
instead
so if i wanted to fix this bug in
production which is a pretty blatant bug
i would need to rebuild my apps i would
need to resubmit them to the app stores
and then i would need to wait for my
users to download that new version
instead we can use expo updates to help
you provide small fixes between builds
like this
so let's look at how this works
expo publish ends up making an update
and an update is a bundle of code that's
javascript and also the assets from our
app so in order to fix this sparrow
address problem we would go into our app
and then we would fix the spray address
to say aeropress once that code change
has been made we could run a command
like expo publish and in the command
line you're going to see that it builds
the app at least all of the javascript
and all the assets into what we would
call an update bundle and then that gets
uploaded to expo servers
so once we have the new update on our
servers it becomes available to users
and it's important to think about what
users have in their app so essentially
apps are built into two parts one part
is this native code that's built into
the app binary and the native code is
stuff that you can't change with an
over-the-air update this is stuff like
the apps icon and some of the
configuration about how the app runs
but then there's the second side of the
app which is this js code and this
update code that we're able to
interchange with other updates so if i'm
a user using an expo app and i open my
app there's a module that's going to
query our servers and say is there any
new updates and if there is then we're
going to look for any new updates based
on a configuration inside of that
app.json file that we saw when we set up
our project this makes it so if you have
critical bug fixes and things that you
need to get out to users right away you
can do that with expo publish so in this
case if i ran expo publish with this
aeropress fix then my users would open
up their app they would download that
new code and then they would see the
typo fixed it it's at that point that i
could start making new builds and then
submit them to the app store to get
review
now there are a lot of different options
that we can opt into with expo updates
let's look at those
okay so i'm here in the expo
documentation and inside of app.json
there is an updates configuration which
i can see here on the left there are
three different configurations i could
configure which is whether they are
enabled or not
when to check automatically the
different options are on load
or on error recovery on load is the
default here so when users force close
their app and then open their app it's
going to check for an update but
probably the most important one is this
fallback to cash timeout this is saying
how long should we wait before launching
your app while we download the new
update if there is a new update so if
this aeropress update was actually like
really large and it took people a while
to download or if they're on a very slow
connection we could cap it at 30 seconds
or three seconds or something and if
they don't download the update within
that time frame then they will fall back
to the cache version of their app that's
already downloaded on their phone we
want to make sure that users can always
get their app so that they don't get
stalled on that splash screen
now there is sort of a trick here by
default we set this fallback to cache
timeout to zero which means we won't
wait at all for any new updates which
means if we push an update up to a user
and they open their app it's not going
to wait for the new update to download
and it's actually going to download in
the background while they continue using
the app then the second time that they
open their app it's going to load the
update that was downloaded in the
background the last time they used the
app this is preferable for some
developers but it's also might be
preferable for you to let users wait a
couple of seconds to download the new
update so that they can get those new
updates even faster so it's just good to
know about the different configurations
we can set with updates
so
this is a lot of stuff that you can do
with expo and there's a lot more
configuration to all the stuff that i
haven't talked about yet but i do want
to mention just quickly some of the
recent updates and things that have been
going on at expo in case that you've
used expo before
so one awesome change that we've come up
with this year with eis is that you can
build an app with any native code you
can add native modules like bluetooth or
you can also add in-app purchases or
things like a blur hash module that will
allow you to uh add in like a native
module that like blurs out your images
as placeholders there's tons of these
and you can add codes like this and we
will still
build your app for you and that is not
possible
we also have something called custom dev
clients before i showed expo go and expo
go works great if you're not using any
custom native code if you are using your
own custom native code you can make your
own version of the expo go app and still
get all of those niceties around opening
up updates on your phone and also your
colleagues can do this too
and finally we're coming out with a
service that updates our our updates
called eas update and this is incoming
this fall and early spring we'll be
rolling this out so keep an eye out for
that you're going to be able to do
things like roll out updates to your
users and see exactly which builds are
pointed at which updates at all times
so
the point is let's iterate together and
figure out how to iterate faster
expo allows you to do this in
development by implementing an app
without requiring knowledge of your
native code you can also review your
work faster with internal distribution
or with expo go
and you can build and submit your apps
in lightning speed in the cloud and make
it consistent across all of your
teammates
finally you can fix critical bugs with
updates which helps you fix things that
might have slipped through the review
process
which means hey it's coffee time so if
you haven't had a coffee today and you
like coffee please have one i would love
to have one with you next time we can
have something in person uh hit me up
i'm always free and available and thank
you so much for iterating with me and
listening to this talk i hope you
enjoyed it and can take some of these
concepts into your work life and into
the projects that you build in the
future let me know if you have any
questions and we can't wait to see what
you build with react native and with
expo
thank you john for this talk and
i'm really happy to see that expo is you
know developing quite rapidly and has
more and more features these days uh so
i keep my fingers crossed for your
future developments because i know that
your roadmap is pretty ambitious now
moving on to the next speaker of shivai
and uh
he's going to talk about machine
learning with react native using media
pipe and tf lite now these are like
mysterious keywords to me so i'm not
going to be introducing you much to this
talk because i guess machine learning
with react native is all we need to know
and we will learn more from this talk
and what's interesting is that they know
how to build that machine learning
experience in a cross-platform way that
works nicely on low-power devices so
let's see what
he has prepared for us today
hello everyone
i am shivaya lumber currently a google
server code mentor at mediapipe and
tensorflow and a developer advocate at
fabrica
i am really excited to be presenting at
react native eucon 2021
and the topic of my presentation is
machine learning with react native using
media pipe and tf light
so we'll be going over what exactly is
machine learning and how can we
integrate it with react native and what
exactly are media piper and df flight
so without wasting for for the time
let's get started
now
of course we all know that how
incredible machine learning is
probably each and every different aspect
of life that we see whether it's some
kind of industry healthcare medicine is
today utilizing machine learning and
machine learning in mobile devices is
something that is gaining a lot of
attention today because a lot of the
different applications and processes are
happening with the help of smartphones
and websites and it becomes imperative
to also be able to include machine
learning within mobile devices
now generally mobile devices are having
lower end processors as compared to
let's say standard computers and servers
therefore there is a need to be able to
actually run uh machine learning models
on lower-end devices and that does
require you to have specific changes be
made to your machine learning models or
support for running these machine
learning models on these devices and
we can also have on device machine
learning for faster processing so
removing the need to actually connect to
machine learning model that might be
hosted on a separate server on a cloud
which can result in increase in the
latency
that can be covered up or that can be
reduced by actually introducing the
machine learning to take place on the
device itself as the processors of the
various devices and um as the machine
learning application then the models
themselves are becoming more compact and
becoming easier to run uh
by increasing their performance and
reducing the overall uh you could say
processing that they actually require so
both of these different techniques is
actually helping us out to do a lot of
different things like on device uh
translation of languages on device
classification of images being able to
detect different things and do a lot of
different uh on device
algorithms that can run machine learning
algorithms that can run on mobile
devices and that is making machine
learning really uh you could accessible
on these mobile devices as well
now
we'll be talking about a few different
solutions that are there and we'll be
looking at how can we integrate the two
different methods that is either media
pipe and tf light both for uh
react native applications
now
let's take a look at this particular
slide and let's see like okay from all
these different images what are all of
these different images having something
in common so you see an android picture
with face detection you see an iphone xr
showing you poses and basically
landmarks of your hand you see the web
where you can see the different kind of
effects happening on uh this girl then
we have raspberry pike and we have uh
basically the webcams and uh all of them
are having something in common
and that's something in common is that
they are all having different
applications of machine learning and
that has been powered by one technology
and that technology is
media pipe
meta pipe is an open source uh cross
platform framework that is provided by
google that helps to build uh
perception pipelines or we can also say
that they actually help us to build a
lot of different audio visual and video
based uh pipelines and it is widely used
within google for a lot of its research
and products and uh
probably till 2018 it was internally
used by google and not really known by a
lot of people but after having been
introduced
and open sourced in 2019 now it has been
widely used to also do a lot of
different machine learning
implementations and pipelines built
around video audio and sensor data so it
can be used to basically do data
preparation pipelines for machine
learning training or it can also be used
for doing ml inference pipelines we'll
be also looking at a lot of different
examples on how it is being actually
used and that will give a better
perspective of why machine learning
using media pipe and being able to
integrate it is really popular and
useful
now some of the uh features that are
actually provided with media pipe uh it
first of all helps us to actually
include end-to-end acceleration uh that
means that whatever uh acceleration is
required for uh the machine learning
models to actually work that is provided
by the uh on device support that is you
know there uh when we are actually
implementing media pipe on the uh mobile
devices now you just need to build it
once and it can be deployed at multiple
places so um if you are creating a media
pipe based machine learning solution uh
you don't need to just you know it's not
this okay that it will be limited to
mobile devices it can also be used for
the web for python and for other places
well so you just need to create one
media pipe solution that can be deployed
to various places and these are
completely ready to use solutions
there's no requirement to actually write
post uh code for doing things like
object detection face recognition and
the solution itself will be provided to
you with the help of uh the media by
solutions that we are building and it's
completely open sourced as well
now taking a look at some of the popular
solutions uh we'll you'll see selfie
segmentation that allows you to
basically run segmentation masks that
allows you to recognize the humans uh
and their faces uh in the current window
and that will help you to basically do
things like changing your background
that also we see in things like google
meet or zoom then you have face mesh uh
now face mesh uh basically points out
468 different landmarks on your entire
face and this can be used for a lot of
different applications like let's say
putting up makeup uh and we'll see a lot
of their use cases as well in the coming
slides then we have hand tracking that
basically has 21 different landmarks for
tracking different points of your hand
then we have basically human pose which
has total of 33 different poses that you
can basically have or to do things like
let's say exercise monitoring then we
have hair segmentation that only detects
your hair we have the standard object
detection and tracking that can be used
to detect certain objects and identify
different objects then we have face
detection uh holistic tracking is
basically combining all face mesh hand
tracking and the pose uh in or right and
you can do a lot of different things
with that as well let's see create
youtubers or you know create such kind
of animations then we can use a 3d
object detection also called as a
detectron right and all of these
different solutions are ready-made
solutions that are that have been
provided by the midi pipe solutions team
and you can just go to mediapipe.dev and
look at one of the solutions and look at
their implementations for python
java android ios
web right and you can
start utilizing these solutions
now one of the again these are some of
the examples where you know it is being
used right now so for example you can
see the ar lipstick try on where you can
see that
it is using the media pipe face mesh
model to basically uh detect the lips
and whenever you're putting some kind of
an effect it will be able to actually
detect that then you can see some of the
media pipe being utilized within uh you
know youtube itself and you can see that
being utilized in the ar movie trailer
that is you know being shown over here
on youtube and you can see uh being able
to detect uh things or for example in
the lens live living surfaces then
showing augmented faces that again is
utilizing the face mesh and then we have
some kind of on device uh machine
learning capabilities that are happening
let's say with the help of lens
translate all of these are
essentially capturing the data that is
there on the device itself and you know
uh helping to carry out different kinds
of machine learning media pipe based
solutions and these are of course just a
few of the examples but there are so
many different different kind of
applications that you can build and that
is why media pipe is becoming really
popular for creating machine learning
based solutions applications on mobile
based devices because of its easy
integration and
really great performance as well now uh
to this sort of you know look at okay
what are the current uh
things that have been released right so
of course um before it was released to
the public uh there was a lot of
application of media pipe use cases
within uh google uh you know ever since
starting in 2012 uh it is being used a
lot in youtube uh whenever there's any
kind of a youtube upload so the
processing in that in that and then it
is also being used in youtube stories
right now we
actually see it being used in things
like nest cam the security cams we see
it in google lens ar ads uh we see it
even in you know gcp and specifically in
the cloud vision api cloud uh ai videos
all these are basically different
solutions uh provided by google which
does internally use media pipe and that
is why it makes it so versatile across
different platforms and not just being
limited to mobile devices
and uh let's take actually an example of
one of the live perceptions so let's say
that like what we are trying to get is
uh the hand tracking to actually work
with the help of media pipe now let's
see how does this actually work so let's
say that what we need to do is that we
have been given an image of a hand and
uh all the different landmarks the 22
different landmarks are represented over
there inside of the right hand side so
that is our ideal uh you know case that
we want to generate the landmarks and
then superimpose them with the live
footage or the live video that is being
represented right now
so what we can do is that
let's say that this is our you know
perception pipeline so the first thing
that you'll see is basically your video
input which is uh providing uh you the
live footage of whatever you want to
actually track then uh you'll see the
next uh process taking place which is
basically the
image transformation which takes in your
video input and converts it into a
relevant size that is required you know
by uh the image processing algorithm and
uh once it has been resized and scaled
to a relevant size uh we are basically
converting that image into tensors so
since
media pipe internally uses atf light we
are basically going ahead and converting
our image that we get from our video
input into tensors now if you are not
aware of tensors tensors are essentially
these uh numerical arrays high
dimensional arrays that contain
values and again these can be used for
different kinds of calculations and then
from let's say any particular given
machine learning model we run the
inference on these tensors and we are
able to decode information about uh the
tensors and then basically what we do is
once we have gotten the information
about the tensors we render uh basically
the landmarks on top of these images and
then we display the resulting video
output that showcases uh the you know
basically this particular
like you know the same thing uh that it
renders the landmarks on site on the
video that you are showing
so basically that is how the inference
of any kind of a media by base solution
takes place where you given input and it
runs you know the inference on top of it
and poses the landmarks based on
whatever it is detecting and uh when
you're talking about media pipe uh if we
go a bit deeper into how you know media
pipe actually works so you might have
heard about the graph data structures
right it's really common uh it's
representing various types of edges
vertices and the flow of information
takes place through different you know
edges and vertices similarly in media
pipe we have the midi pipe graph that uh
is sort of laying down the path of how
basically the different um you know
information uh about let's say the input
and the respondent the responding uh or
the relevant output you know is flowing
through that media pipe graph uh
essentially we uh are containing the
entire solution when we when we're
talking about like any kind of a media
pipe based solution uh your input uh
that you're providing or sort of the
image that you're providing uh will be
given to the media pipe uh graph and
that information will flow and again we
do have these edges and vertices now
specifically these vertices that we have
they contain uh configuration
information about um the different
aspects about our meta pipe solution and
these configuration information are
essentially you know
our calculators now of course we'll be
talking a bit about calculators but of
course the node of the graph is
basically showing us you know that it's
the calculator and of course um the
entire media pipe graph is representing
the overall flow of how basically the
input image is that or the input
information that we are receiving how we
are able to you know put up the
landmarks on top of it and get the
resultant output now uh basically any
two uh nodes are connected by string
which can be you know represented as
let's say an edge of a graph which
basically carries the packets and these
packets are actually containing the
information about you know uh the let's
say whether it's the uh input image the
tensors or let's say it is providing
relevant metadata that will be required
for you know further processing and it
will contain the time stamps alongside
that data now
if we talk about
the calculators right that are
representing the nodes so they have been
written in c plus and they declare
basically both the input and the output
ports that what kind of input do they
expect uh when you know any kind of an
input is actually coming to them by the
packet and what uh once that like some
kind of processing has been done like
what is the expected output that they
will be sending to let's say the next
node right and uh they basically
implement something called as the open
process close methods which basically
means that whenever there is an open
process happening or an open method that
means that the full graph is currently
running processes like let's say that
whenever some kind of an input packets
have arrived at the node they are ready
to be processed and closes that after
one entire run has completed now it's
time to actually close you know uh the
uh graph so that is basically the
calculator that is representing at each
edge that is responsible for making
changes or bringing changes to the input
images that are there and it will help
to basically uh
create our process for
converting whatever input is into
relevant transformations that need to
take place and this becomes part of the
calculator
now uh we do also have some inbuilt
calculators uh we can create our own
calculators there are a lot of different
inbuilt calculators that are used for
image audio video processing and that
are uh you know native with tensorflow
and tf lite for the ml inference part
now now basically uh we also have a lot
of different uh calculators for post
processing as well so those have
actually been created let's say for
example for selfie segmentation we have
the selfie segmentation calculator and
you can also actually go ahead and
create your own calculators as well
and finally basically what we are going
to be talking about is the
synchronization and this is really
important because all the inputs that we
receive inside the calculators and how
we are you know being processed and
they're going outside we need to make
sure that the time stamps are not
compromised if the time stamps are
compromised then it can actually result
in erroneous data and that is why the
synchronization is an important aspect
of how the midi pipe solution actually
works
and uh we can also talk about a sub
graph basically a sub graph will be used
you know whenever uh we are having to
divide our steps into multiple steps and
um
like you could say that a subgraph is a
part of the main graph and it can also
have its own calculators and be used to
basically do one of uh you know the
tasks that will be there so as you can
see over here that um if you have a
larger you know a larger task to you
know take place uh we can have one sub
graph that is dedicated to let's say
only the hand landmarks and then let's
say one sub graph only for taking uh pl
for taking care of the post landmarks
and of course um
the main aspect of this is that um
the video will be taken in it will be
passed through the hand landmarks and
you'll see the rendering image but of
course there are certain issues that can
you know take place because uh you know
the hand let's say if you are using a
live video uh the uh scale of the hand
will think dynamically if let's say you
are taking your hand closer or you know
taking it further away from the video
camera and then let's say it will
actually take a lot of capacity from the
model to deal with such kind of
variations that you know that you know
takes place so there are steps that we
can take place you know to
overcome these issues uh or basically
these issues in real time
and that is why like we can also use a
lot of different techniques to optimize
our performance of our models as well
and if we just look at uh an overview of
how does the media pipe tech stack look
like so
at its core uh we as i we have described
that basically we have you know we have
created this cross platform framework uh
that has been written in c plus plus and
it has support for interacting with
things like tensorflow opencv so uh it
comes in with helper utilities uh from
you know tf lite uh that can be utilized
right and if you look at uh you know
basically how does the entire
functioning work so at the core level
you have your graphs that are
responsible for showing the path of how
the packets are you know flowing in from
various and when how they're being
collected at different nodes now these
nodes are essentially calculators and
apart from all of these you do get a
certain apis that help you in your
process one is the graph construction
api uh that will be help you know that
will be actually helpful for creating
graph for the first time the calculator
api and the graph execution api all of
these different apis are responsible for
helping run your you know graphs and uh
essentially at the top layer is all the
different kind of applications that are
possible to run with on whether it's the
desktop android ios or let's see even in
embedded devices like uh iot core or
let's say you know uh for example
raspberry pi and this sort of shows you
uh high level uh overview of how
basically the media pipe tech stack goes
from uh you know the top to bottom
bottom being at its more raw level uh
and that is how sort of you know the
media pipe applications look like
internally
and uh you can actually go ahead and
look at some of you know the docs if you
actually want to go ahead and understand
some of the parameters and if you want
to look at some of the examples for
media pipe you can go ahead and actually
look at that or you can also use the
visualization tool for meta pipe that
helps you to see okay if you were to
build a midi pipe solution how would it
actually look like
now we can also take an example of some
of these you know mobile examples where
for example we have the hand tracking
gpu based where basically the gpu is
powering you know the media pipe and
hand tracking and you can see the
visualization that has been built for
that and similarly for you know the
phase detection and the object detection
and not talking about tf light right so
tensorflow lite is an open source uh
framework that is specifically you know
used for deep learning now it comes or
it stems from the main tensorflow
library and it is used for uh you know
on device inference so whenever you want
to actually go ahead and
do your machine learning uh and run your
machine learning algorithms doing that
inference on device on your uh let's say
mobile devices audience devices uh it is
a really great tool to use and again it
supports for on-device machine learning
and again it gives a really high
performance so one of the questions that
we before move on to is uh we have these
two different ways right one is a tf
light and the other is a media pipe now
media pipe is generally used mainly for
the audio video and such kind of streams
because you're receiving these uh
media streams and these are the ones
that are responsible for you know being
uh sort of shown and then being worked
upon but tf light uh allows you to
actually convert any kind of a
tensorflow based model into a ta flight
format that can be utilized on your
device so of course with dflight you get
much more amount of freedom in terms of
what kind of models you actually want to
run those might not necessarily be in
you know be just audio or video based so
uh for example again uh with respect to
let's say if we were to create like a
solution uh that has been built for the
um for you know the mobile based devices
uh we can use media pipe for things like
uh doing pose detection uh x-rays
monitoring right audio and video uh for
let's say doing things like facial um uh
actions uh you know creating face masks
and all so all that can be happened like
can be done very easily with the help of
uh
with the help of media pipe but of
course with tf flight you are open to a
wide variety of different kinds of
models uh that you can actually run on
your mobile device
so after having converted a model that
has been written let's intensify in
python you can convert into a
corresponding tf lite format and that
will actually help you to you know run
those on uh react native on mobile based
devices
and let's actually go ahead and take an
example of uh tf flight actually being
used for doing an image classification
problem in react native so as you can
see from the code uh over here in the
first uh you know
essentially the third line we're
importing the tf light react native
package now this is an npm package that
has been created for importing the tf
light you know uh inside of um react
native and so we are importing tf light
uh
using the uh you know basically the np
module t flight react native and uh the
idea is that we'll be using the image
speaker np model uh to basically pick
any image and in our react native
application our machine learning uh
solution will detect what is the class
of the image that we are going to be
having so in the line number five we are
just initiating our tf light function uh
or our sort of our object and the method
tf flight and as you can see over here
we have this provided some initial uh
you know uh
sort of declarations that are there to
basically do things like height image of
our canvas uh things like what is you
know the
detection model that we're using so we
are specifically using the coco ssd
mobile net model now we also have some
other ones as well we have the yolo
model we have ssd mobile net and these
are the some of the models that we'll be
actually comparing with so we are having
uh three different types of models that
we are going to be using then we are
setting up our initial state that
contains like the model source what is
the image height and what are the
recognitions because when you are going
to be running these machine learning
models on top of your image they're
going to be providing you an array of
recognitions but the most recognized one
will be selected
so that is what is happening in our
initial declaration of our variables of
important deals that are required
now
let's actually go ahead and look at this
particular code where we are going to be
looking at all the different kinds of
models that are currently being
supported
so uh we have basically taken uh three
different uh models the first one is the
ssd model and as you can see like within
you know these models we have a unique
tf flight uh you know a unique tf light
file for you know the different models
so the first model is the ssd mobile net
model we have all the labels uh so the
labels are essentially you know what
will be recognized whenever you provide
any kind of an image it will it will
actually be able to provide like a label
to it based on whichever uh you know
label it the machine learning model
actually thinks is the closest then we
have the yellow again yellow is used for
image classification and we have another
rtf light uh you know uh file for it and
then we have a standard mobile net
version v1 that is you know the df light
so we can uh sort of you know
select one of these models based on the
performance that we are seeing using the
switch statement and uh as you can see
that the ta flight dot load model is
responsible for actually going ahead and
loading the model inside of your local
storage because uh initially the model
will not be loaded directly uh for you
know saving the time and saving the
amount of uh you know computation but
using the tfli dot load model we are
basically loading now the desired model
so by selecting which particular model
do we actually want to load uh we'll be
loading that particular model and that
will be used for doing the image
classification
now if we go ahead and look at the next
particular
uh next particular uh code now this is
the code that is being utilized for
rendering the boxes so of course what we
want to do is that uh once we detect
something inside of an image we want to
create a bounding box around it now what
exactly is a bounding box the bounding
box is representing uh you know four
different points like a rectangle you
could say and those uh you know are sort
of the ending points where we have
detected we have detected something uh
like you know inside of the image so uh
we are going to be using uh the
rendering box function to render
basically the um bounding box on top of
the image that are being recognized and
as you can see what we're doing is that
we are having this recognitions.map
because there will be a number of
different recognitions and
for all of them what we're doing is that
we are basically going to be you know uh
having set uh the coordinates for our
left top width and height basically this
will give us you know uh the
coordinates or the endpoints of that
particular image where we are creating
the bonding box and we're returning a
react native view that view is basically
the generated view that is
you know created when we have detected
something successfully and we want to
render the um you could say the bonding
box on top of it so we are returning a
view a react native view where you'll
see basically it being created by a blue
colored background as we take in the
text style we have basically also used
it and uh you know we are using the
styles dot box and uh what we are
returning is basically the detected
class so class of you know what type of
uh image like you know that is there so
we are detecting that and you're also
giving like what percentage is the
confidence because as we know in machine
learning that uh based on any kind of
recognition or predictions that you're
making you'll be getting a range of
different predictions but we are going
to be taking the one with the highest
prediction and we'll be returning that
and drawing that once we render when we
once we call the render boxes function
now if we go ahead and look at uh you
know the code that is our main code we
are looking currently at the on select
image now in this we use the npm package
of image picker and we you know go ahead
and select one of the images so you will
be providing the path in your os since
this is react native so we're providing
you know that path and
then you will be giving the response you
are in the file path uh we'll be
defining the height and the width of the
response and uh we'll be basically
giving in the state we are using the set
state so since we are using uh react as
well over here so we are setting the
state of you know the source uh path
file and uh you know what is the image
height now this is where we are also
like as you can see height we are doing
basically we are uh going ahead and uh
transforming the height the image height
and image weights in the next couple of
lines where we basically are scaling it
right and then
what we're doing is that
whatever particular uh model that we
want to actually go ahead and use we are
uh we have created the switch statements
and we have created the different cases
now let's say if you want to use the ssd
one we can simply just go ahead and call
the initial method that we had declared
pflight and we can use the detect object
on image function from it and uh in that
we'll be basically passing on the path
the threshold that is uh you know that
is required and the number of results
per class and uh that is where we are
then going to be calling right uh the uh
basically this function and
the direct object on
image function will go ahead and you
know try to detect if it finds out
something and uh if it does right if
there's some error then it will throw
the error but otherwise if it does not
throw an error uh within our current
state that we're maintaining for the
recognition we are basically going ahead
and you know with the recognitions that
we have uh we are providing that
resultant array of uh basically or you
could say the map of you know the
resultants where basically for each
particular different type of result that
it gave it has given uh it has given a
corresponding uh value attached to it so
it's giving you a map of different you
know recognitions that are not made for
example if an image is of a cat it might
have detected cat dog and some other
kinds of you know labels as well and
their corresponding uh percentage of you
know um how much percent like uh the con
the model is actually confident that it
will be true and you can see that being
utilized for all these different ones
now whichever one is the one that is
having the highest one that will be
again as we have discussed uh right will
be used in this render boxes one because
from the state we are first finding out
okay which particular model to use uh
what is the map of you know the
recognitions and the image height and
image width and this will help us to
render the boxes and this will go ahead
and be utilized you know to draw it on
the canvas so
apart from this the other steps that you
will be doing is basically create you
know um another
create basically components one
component would be to you know
render the output image
that will be there and uh on the output
image you'll be rendering uh the
bounding box and of course if you let's
say are
trying to do it on live via let's say
your webcam you can have another
component and use the react native uh
webcam and have those uh you know and
sort of create this entire as let's say
a separate view uh inside of your react
native application but this sort of
shows an example of how you know it
would function so you
pick an image you select that image and
you put it and the
machine learning model uh or sorry if
you know the t flight model is actually
able to detect multiple objects within a
single image and it will be able to
create the corresponding bonding boxes
on top of each one of these and help us
to you know create a simple image
classification uh solution on react
native now apart from this there are a
lot of other benefits as well so there
is of course uh you know the simple
example but of course you can do a lot
of different other things by including
uh you know tf like with react native
now uh the support for specifically
running media pipe solutions inside of
react native is uh not that great but
there are a lot of different you know uh
sort of you know things happening within
the google's media pipe team to help you
know to integrate because right now
there is a great support for running it
in native android and native ios
applications but very soon we should be
able to actually go ahead and get our
hands on basically with
the uh implementations of react native
with uh you know like implementation of
media pipe solutions with react native
so um that sort of you know is basically
the example that we sort of covered
today and with that that brings an end
to my uh you know to my talk and i hope
that you have liked and you have learned
something from this particular talk uh
the most important thing to sort of keep
in mind is that media pipe is a really
great
solution that has been created by the
google team and has a lot of
future applications and of course the
amount of uh support and the amount of
uh you know examples are coming out for
the media pipe community those are
really great to see so if you are
genuinely interested in creating these
uh streaming uh machine learning
applications now it could be something
like you know um like a
physiotherapist a virtual
physiotherapist let's say or some kind
of a dance teacher or doing things
related to your face and all these will
actually be come in very handy and
benefit by the media pipe solutions that
are actually provided by you know the
midi pipe team and you can definitely go
ahead and check out those and of course
a tensorflow lite is uh sort of added
score you know it allows you to run uh
the tensorflow models uh using
uh basically you know by using a t
flight or like sort of a light version
of uh you know the machine learning
model but it's been generally created
for running on device machine learning
uh solutions right and it's so that can
do the ml processing on device and that
makes it really uh great as and of
course it's not just for ml uh solutions
right or basically for uh streaming
solutions it can be used for a lot of
different other aspects as well
so with that that brings an end to my
talk i hope you know you like the talk
and you can connect with me on my
twitter handle i did it how to deal up
and on github on
github.com to you know ask any questions
that you might be having with respect to
media pipe how to integrate uh you know
tf flight with uh react native and how
to basically empower you know react
native applications because react native
is one of the most popular frameworks
you know that are there and of course
being able to integrate machine learning
models with them is uh highly uh useful
so thank you so much for attending this
talk and i hope to see you uh in next
next year in act in person thank you so
much
thank you shivai for this talk uh it's
really great to see how react native can
be used with some additional advanced
features such as machine learning or
sometimes even vr showing us that react
native capabilities go beyond
traditional mobile development now
moving on to the next speaker we have
arnold from adventist and he's going to
talk about graphql with react query
something that they are using in
production in on a fully fledged
application so in this step we're going
to learn about their experience with
that all the great features and our now
i guess will try to convince us that
react query is what we should be all
using for graphql library of graphql
development
and
all the features that they are also
planning to use in the future so let's
see what arnold has prepared for us
today
hey everyone i'm very happy and excited
to speak at the reg native europe
conference
so today we'll talk about requery with
graphql cogen and tapscript
let's start with a few words about me
my name is arno and i am an entrepreneur
and cto
i'm also passionate about developer
experience and solving complex problems
requery so requery is quite popular now
it's a powerful solution to
fetch and cache remote data
and the library has been created by
tanya linsley and
is also famous for a react table or rare
chart components
the library is not maintained by dominic
and you can find on his blog
a lot of very interesting articles about
requery and tab script
we'll also use graphql code generator uh
it's a simple cli that you will use to
generate your typescript types
and operations from your graphql schema
this cli has been created by the guild
the guild is a group of open source
developers they have a lot of other
solutions for graphql and
the graphql code generator itself is
provided with a lot of plugins for
popular languages and libraries
so let's have a look at the technical
stack for this demonstration
so for the rack native app we will use
expo tab script the graphql code
generator with graphql config requery
with graphql request and rack native
paper
and also suspense and error boundaries
for the api
we'll use hazura with the post-brexit
database
and everything will be hosted with nost
which is a great backhander service
solution
so this text nickel stack is very close
to uh what we did for
for own recognitive app in production
so we will be able to share uh some
recipes and some code with you today uh
about how to use a requery with code
generator and typescript
so let's have a look to the agenda so
we will
review and look at the different
features and the code
uh
in this ragnativ app
so here you can see the different the
topics that we will cover today
and we'll conclude with a comparison
with other popular libraries as apollo
clients
and only and i will share with you the
lessons we have learned during this
project
so let's start with the stale
revalidate concept
to see how it works
to demonstrate the style while
revalidate concept i will use hazura to
edit the data in the database
azura will expose my date my my data
as a graphql api that is
consumed by this very simple uh ragnativ
application i have created especially
for this talk
so when you click on one movie
we fetch the data
about the movie details here
so what we want to offer as a user
experience is when you go back
to this movie details you want to use
the cache
at the client side so you will have an
instant
response experience
and in the meantime
you expect that
your ragnativ app will fetch fresh data
from the server
so this is actually what
it is happening now but my connection is
too fast that
if i change
the data on the server
you can see that
is displayed instantly because i have a
very high speed connection
so now i have to slow down
the connection to illustrate the style
while
revalidate concept so i'm using the
network link conditioner which is a
great solution to
experience different
connection speed you can download this
tool
with the xcode additional tools
so first let's
change
a value
of this movie title and the ratings
and i just save the data
and now
i can slow down my network connection
and click on the movie details and you
can see that we
we have one very uh
few seconds just to to display the cache
data
and uh he has just the time to
revalidate the data from the server
so let's do it again
and now let's use a very bad
connection
you can see that we are still
displaying
the same data
that are in the cache
and if i
change the connection quality to edge
for example
we will have
the data updated so this is exactly what
you you expect
in a modern app is to have instant
response from the cache
and
in the background re-fetch the data from
the server so requery has this very good
default is state while uh revalidate
concept
and it's very useful because you will
have a snappy experience
while
optimizing the data fetching
behind the scene
so let's see now how it works and how to
generate the corresponding code
with graphql code generator
to use the graphql code generator you
have to install the cli first
next you have to configure
the code generator to do that i will use
a graphql config
that will allow me to
also use a vs code graphql extension
so you can use the same configuration
file for both
the graphql code generator and the vs
code extension
so to
configure your graphical code generator
you have to define the schema endpoint
here you can add some optional headers
you can define uh
where your queries and mutations are
defined
and where you want to generate your
typescript types
and with with which plugins like here we
want to use subscripts and we want to
generate hooks by using requery and
requirey is using as a fetcher graphql
request
and that's it you can now move on your
queries and
mutations definition
so let's create a new one
and here i'm using
again the vs code graphql extension so i
can i have autocomplete so now i can
just
browse my api schema here and i can just
select
the fields
and
the queries i want to use
and i can even execute a query
so it's uh
it's it's it's really great to have this
possibility to
create very easily and quickly uh your
queries and mutation in this graphql
file
and have a preview of the data
so if we have a look at a more detailed
example here that we will use in our
demo application
uh you can see that you can use you can
define some movie fragments that you can
use in your queries and your mutation
and you can also define your graphql
variables
and you can also define some mutations
so everything is defined in this graphql
files you can have one you can have
multiple files it depends on how large
is your application and how you want to
structure
your queries and mutations
so the next step is to generate
the corresponding types
and hooks
to do that i will use the terminal
and i will use my new generate command
and this command is just using
graphql code gen
by using the config file i've just
defined
so
it's
quite easy and it's very fast here it
generates all the types and all the
hooks in
two seconds
so let's have a look to the generated
file
so here you have a very large file with
all the types and
hooks generated from the graphql api
schema
so here you can look at the movies uh
type
um
and if we go
at the bottom we will find our
hooks
uh that are using
uh
the requery hooks
and the fetcher
so you don't have to take care of this
file it will be automatically maintained
and generated by a graphical cogen when
you did two so i mean that
you don't have to manually edit or add
types to this file you just have to
regenerate
your uh your this file when your schema
has changed or when you have added some
new queries or mutation in your graphql
file
so as you can see graphql generator it's
a productivity booster
you can just focus on using your requery
hooks instead of having to create first
all the types and all the
queries and hooks
somewhere it will be done automatically
by graphql code gen
so the next step will be to see how to
use
these generated hooks and type in our
components
so here we are in our
app
component
so
as a standard rac native application
we have to define some providers
and here we have to define one provider
for the graphql client and another one
for the query clients
the graphql client provider is a custom
one that we just use uh the graphql
request
clients and where you just have to
define your
graphical api endpoints
and
maybe for your app in production you
have to define some authorization
headers
the next provider you you need is to use
the existing query client provider
it's a provider that is available with
the raw query
and you have to set your cryo client
so here our query client
is a new query client from racquery and
what is really great with requery is
that you can define some global settings
for all of your queries
so here we have just defined that we
want to use suspense
and
we don't want to have multiple retries
when you're occurs it's just for the
demo purpose but maybe
the default is three
but you can just adjust
this setting according to your needs and
you have a lot of multiple settings that
you can define globally for all of your
queries and and mutation
so that's it for the main app
file you just
have to define these two providers
next you have to actually use the hooks
generated by the graphical code
generator in your components
so let's have a look to the movies list
components
so here i have my movie movies list
component and this list is using a
custom hook to
fetch
all the movies from the api
so if i go inside this custom hook
in this custom hook i'm using the
graphql client
that
requires
needs
and
i use
the generated
hooks generated by a graphql code gen
and that's it
so it's nice because here i have a very
nice encapsulated hook and my component
the code is very lean
and here i can just add some
additional configuration and logic
and i don't have to implement this hook
it's already generated by uh graphql
code gen
so in this example
the first parameter is a fetcher so in
our case we want to use graphql client
and
after you have some variables so here
this is the query variables
i have uh defined
in my
graphql file so
here i have also for example the offset
this is one available
variable i have defined in my
graphql
file
so
it's very easy you just have to consume
the hooks generated by the graphql code
generator and use the generator and then
you have to
you get this query info
result but you can if you want uh
uh use all the
uh possible core info uh
fields uh you need here like is fetching
is your uh
is success and so on but in this case we
just want to return to our components
the data so this is uh the movies again
thanks to a graphql code generator and
types in typescript i have
automatically these
nice
types
and um
i want just to expose also to my
components a refetch method that is
exposed by requery
use query and uh i can now in my movie
movies list component i can use the
movies data and if i need to re-fetch
the list i can use this function in my
component to to re-fetch the data
so this is basically how you can use uh
requery
and the hooks generated by um
the code generator
to have a very clean and encapsulated
solution in your components
okay so we have just seen how to use
graphical code generator and the
generated hooks into our components
and now let's have a look to the other
features that require
provide
provides to us
so first let's have a look at the
initial data so if we go back to our
very
simple app
here we have the list of this list of
data and
when so this list just fetch some data
from our graphical api like the id the
title and the ratings
but so it's just this simple set of
information and when we click on one
movie we want to display
instantly
the information with we already have
have in our list
and display this information while
loading extra details uh about the movie
okay so again if i click here it's
already in the cache so it's instant if
i go here i have instantly the title and
the ratings and i want to load
the details information
when the screen is displayed
so to do that
uh the maybe the
nice way to to use requery uh to do that
is to use initial data so if we look at
our movies list components
when you click on one item you we use a
rack navigation to navigate to the movie
detail screen and we send as a parameter
as a root parameter we send the movie
the actual
item
in the list
so when i click here i just
navigate to the screen and send the
movie data i have as a parameter so i
have the ids the title and the ratings
and i want to display instantly this
information
so to do that uh if i go to the movie
details
um screen component
so i have this uh
hook it's a custom hook i use use movie
details and the parameter is a movie
a movie is a movie fragment and if we
have a look to the fragment here
it's only the the ids the details in the
ratings but the movie details fragment
is more it's the storyline the the jar
and the ratings so what i need here is i
need the details but i want to display
instantly
the information i have so to do that i
can go into my custom book
and here i'm using the generated uh hook
generated
uh automatically by graphql code jam
and i have a variable which is
the movie id
and i have this great initial data
requery property so i can
uh
say that uh
just
use this initial data
for this query and
it means that it will be automatically
used
uh by my component uh to display uh
some information without waiting to have
the all details coming from the api
so it's a great way to
to manage this case because your movie
detail uh used as a single uh source of
truth this is the requirey you don't
have to have an extra movie
um a
movie list item information somewhere
you just have to rely on the same
movie details
information here
so this is how you can use initial data
to have this kind of very optimized
solution because here you can have a
graphql query with only the data you
need for the screen
and you don't have to fetch uh
everything so i know that with graphql
you can do that and it's nice in a lot
of cases but if you have a huge list or
if you have
a lot of details
to fetch is better maybe to optimize
your list data
to fetch only what you need to display
and
to display all the and to load the
details when needed but you can
instantly display what you have in your
list
uh what also you can do with requirey is
you can prefetch so
uh on some events you can even prefetch
some data if you anticipate that the
user will display
another screen and so you can preload
some
some data
so
that's it for the initial data but again
it's very nice to have a single source
of truth in your components
and to optimize how the data are fetched
and displayed
let's now have a look at the automatic
refresh options require provide and
let's start with the on app focus
refresh
so here i am
in the app
component and i have added also some
logs about
when
data are fetched from the server
so on the left you have my actual device
and you can see that when i manually
refresh my
list you can see the logs at the same
time
so what i want is when the application
goes to the background and goes back to
the foreground i have this automatic
refresh so you can see that it's already
done here automatically and it's working
also for the detail screen
okay so when the application
is going back to the foreground it
automatically require we will refetch
all the active queries
i think it's a great behavior because
the user
don't the the users don't have to
re-fetch manually when they go back to a
screen
so as it just
uh
automatically performed by requery
so how to implement that
is quite easy
it's not
easy as the web
in a web application because this is a
default with a react web application in
with the react native application you
have to
use
this hook
that will use upstate which is a
recognitive hook that will use this on
upstate change
function
and
when it means that when
the regnative app state change
it will call automatically this function
and this function will tell to
recognitive that the app is focused and
when the application is active you don't
want to do a re-fetch when the
application is not active you want to do
a reference
when the application is active
and
that's it
and you know that all of your
requery active queries will be refetched
when uh the application uh goes back to
the foreground so i think it's great
it's you don't have to to code
everything in your component and
and in your code to to manage this
this case you just have to add this very
simple function and use the focus
manager to to tell requery that he has
to
to refetch on focus
for the next feature
uh
i won't be able to demonstrate it but uh
i'm going to show you how to implement
this solution is when
the network
is offline and when you go back to
online mode you want to automatically
refresh uh the data
so let's see how you have to implement
uh this solution
so one way to do that is to create a new
custom hook
and in this hook we'll just
use a
requery online manager to set
the network status and to know the
network status
you have to use a net info object from a
rack native community that unfolds
so it's
very easy just
you just have to
to implement and to call this hook in
your app components
and
when
the device is offline and when the
device is going back online and you
are on your app automatically all the
queries
will be refreshed
so again it's a very
nice ux
uh
because
with mobile you can have these issues
with uh with the connection so you know
that if a user has
your application open and when it's
going back offline and from
from offline to online mode you will you
will have his data automatically refresh
the next refresh options we are going to
see is on-screen focus and polling
on screen focus is when you want
to refetch for example the movies list
when you display the screen
so right now you can see that this is
actually what we we do
when you go to a detail screen and we go
back to the screen with refresh data
but again this is still while
revalidate feature i mean that
when you go back to the list
react query will use a cache first and
in the background refresh the data
from the server but to
add this automatic refresh on screen
focus
we have to implement
it
so do do that
in the movies list component i'm using a
new custom hook
and this hook
is
quite simple is using
use focus effect from rack navigation
and it will just initiate a refetch
uh
a required refresh
when we display again a second time the
screen so it will be not done when the
screen is displayed the first time it
will be refreshed only when we going
back to the screen
so this is a very simple solution to
implement
this on refresh focus with the requery
and the refretch
function here is a parameter of this use
refresh on focus hook
and
is coming from the use query
requery hook that has this refretch
function so pretty straightforward you
just have to use it
where you need to have this automatic
refresh when
a user is going back to one of your
screen
the last automatic refetch options we
are going to see is pulling
pulling is when you want to
automatically refresh your list in this
example the movies list
at a specified interval
so it's very easy to do you just have to
edit
your require requery options
so here i'm using my custom hooks use
movies and i just have to set
uh
the refetch interval option in my uh use
query look
so let's say i want a refresh every two
seconds
uh you can see in the terminal that
automatically uh this query will be
refreshed every two seconds
you can set this option
for a specific query as we do now or
globally
in the new create client options
so it's great when you want to have this
automatic refresh this can be
complementary to
push notifications or graphql
subscriptions
it's good to know that you can use this
option just take care of the energy
consumption
and if it's really relevant if the user
stays
on the same app at the same screen for a
long time
so it's up to you to decide if you have
to use this
refresh interval option
so just to to conclude about all of
these automatic refresh options
i think that
uh
requery provides maybe 80
of your needs
in terms of automatic refresh and is
quite well integrated with rack native
and easy to to to to implement
so i think recrea one very strong point
is that is so easy to have these very
good defaults
and what uh you can have
and what you can expect from a modern
react native application
now we can explore mutations
and we can
see how to to invalidate uh cache and to
do optimistic updates uh with the rear
query
so in your in our movie details
component here
we we can do some mutation about the
movie ratings here
what we want to do is to have an instant
feedback
so i mean that when you click here on
the star you want to update the ui
instantly without waiting for a response
from the server so this is optimistic
updates what you want to do also is when
you admittation has succeeded you want
to refresh automatically
list information to have a consistent
information here according to the
mutation you would have just done
in the details screen
so how to manage
caching validation and optimistic update
in my code so what
we have
done here is we have this custom hook
that returns a function that you will
call when a user click on a star here so
this function will accept the movie id
and the new
ratings
if we look deeper into this hook code
you can see that we have this function
definition here that we return
and this function just manage
the new
ratings and we'll call this
mutate in sync function
that is a required function that you use
to call your graphql api and you send
this by using these variables
so this is where the
the mutation actually
happened
we have another hook where you have to
define uh your mutation that you use
here
so this hook will use uh
the
the hook
generated by a graphql code gen
according to the schema and your graphql
file
so here it will it will create a new
mutation
according to the different options you
have defined
you have the the on mutate option
unsuccess and on your you have also
unsettled option but i don't use
unsettle here
uh in on mutate what i want to do first
is to consult ongoing fetching i don't
want to have ongoing fetching if i do a
mutation
uh i need to get the
the previous movie
details because i want to do an
optimistic update so i want to alter the
current data and i'll also need this
previous movie details data if i have to
roll back if an are occur later occurs
later
uh here this is actually where we do the
optimistic updates so where you are
using a query client
from requery with the set query data
function
so i say that i want to update my query
data for this query
and i want to use this variable so this
is the movie id and i want to update the
data so i want to
change the
the ratings here with the new ratings
so this is how to do
optimistic update
with recurring and if the mutation
succeed i just have to invalidate the
queries i want so in my case
when i change a rating here i want to
update the list and you can see again
if i click on the star look
at the terminal it will automatically
uh initiate a cache invalidation of the
movies list
so i'm sure that if the user go back to
this screen
he will uh
he will try to
have
fresh data consistent
with my mutation
and the last point is error management
is if my if i have an error during my
mutation i can by by the same solution
using secret data roll back to my
initial state
so here again i can roll back for this
particular query i can set
the data to the previous data so this is
it's very
straightforward you just have to to work
with queries queries key and data and
you have to you can
easily
set your cray data by this way
for optimistic update or when you have
to roll back to a previous value for
example
so this is basically how
complex is uh to manage uh
mutation and cache administration and
optimistic
update i think that at the end
is not so complex uh you have a very
good control of what is going on
and you can do exactly
what you want in terms of caching
validation and what data you want to
update when a mutation occurs
now how to use react suspense and error
boundaries uh with real query so first
of all require support both react
suspense and error boundaries but how do
how to
to use these features
in your code
so actually our movies list is using
suspense and
it keeps our component code very lean
because we don't have to to manage uh
loading indicator here or error
management it's all done in the movies
list screen where
you where we use suspense
on the top of the movies list and thanks
to the rear query support
we don't have to add any additional code
so we just have to fall back to our
loading screen so let's
use a slow connection here
and reload my app
so we have the time to see the loading
indicator
and here you can see the logic indicator
and
the list will be displayed just after
so it's great uh i think for eighty
percent of the cases suspense it's a
very it's a very very good combination
with real query and the same for error
boundary um
racquery provides a query or reset
boundary reprovider that you can use
to manage error boundary and you can
just fall back to an error message when
requiring your occurs for example a
graphically or something like that a
network error so you can display a nice
generic uh
this screen
and you can
use a button to reset
the the query state so
it's again maybe for most of the cases
this can be very nice but if you need
more control for example in the movie
detail screen we have this two-step
display where we want to display
first
the data from
uh the list and then we want to load the
details so we need to have
uh something more precise uh maybe it's
doable with suspense but to keep uh to
keep the code and the component very
simple
we have just eject from suspend from
from for this
movie details component so how to reject
you just have to set the corresponding
property in the requiry hook
and here uh i just said suspense to
false but i still want to use air
boundary so you can mix exactly what you
want here
and now in my
movie details code i can display a
loading indicator according to the
to the state or to data
i want
so it's great you know to
have the possibility to uh
to define the behavior you want or to to
to have the choice to
to use suspense or not according to your
needs for each
screen
flat list with infinite queries so let's
see how it works with rare query and
ragnativ
so now my
application
supports
infinite
list
in the movie screen so when i scroll
down
after 30 items i will
fetch a new page from from my graphql
api
so here you can see the terminal that
requirey automatically fetch the next
page
so how it works so i have this use
infinite movies custom hook that will
return
a fetch next page function
this fetch next page is
called by the unreached function header
and this handler is used
in this flat list property
so when the end is reached it will
automatically call this
and
this function will
if i go back here
this function we call fetch next page
and this is a function
of requery and recovery will fetch the
next page according to the settings
defined in this custom hook
so here we
don't use
a hook generated by a graphical code-gen
because there is no
infinite hooks generated automatically
by by graphical coding and requery
plug-in
so we
do have to
implement
our own uh
function so we use
uh use infinite query function function
from requery and uh we just have to uh
to call uh
the graphical client to use a graphql
claim to do the graphical request
and we this function will accept uh
the page number and according to that we
have to define the new
variables like the offset and the the
limit is the page size
so in this case uh because we are using
an offset for the pagination it's very
easy to configure and to calculate what
is the next
offset for the next page
and here we you have also to implement
this get next page
option
with a function that will return the
next
page number
so this is how to to manage a infinite
uh query in requery so first you have to
[Music]
do your query with the page param you
receive and you have to expose a
function to return the next page param
and that's it
and yes sorry you still have to return
the data and the data is
all the movies from all the pages so you
have to return the pages
that are in the current state and to add
your new
movies here so by this way your movies
list will contain all the movies
and
it's great because now i can just have
this infinite
pagination and i can
when i do a mutation you can see that it
will refresh automatically all the pages
which is good and not good because in
term of performance maybe you want only
to refresh
the impacted pages so this is something
we will discuss just after but here it's
a good default i mean if you do some
mutation you want to have your list
fresh when you go back to the list so
recrea will handle that for you you
don't have to take care of that you just
have to invalidate your query and if
your query is using
pages no problem it will re-fetch all
the pages
in your infinite
list you may want also to support
optimistic updates
so in our case when i click
on the rating here
i want to have automatically my ui
updated here
so to do that
i have to update
my
mutation to
um in addition of
doing an optimistic update from my movie
details
i have added this set movies create data
function that will optimistically update
my
list of movies
so
to update
my list i again i'm using racquery
security data
and i have to
update
the list and to do that i have to
get the previous data and to update the
corresponding item in my list
so this is a movie i've just updated i
want to update the movie
that has to be
impacted
so this is the way to go
the solution i think is is nice uh when
you really need to have a
an optimistic update uh on all the
screens
impacted by a mutation
so we don't use that a lot
because
the
query and validation are working very
nicely
and
we don't have enough line
support mode very advanced so we don't
have to to do that but again if you uh
if you want to
to optimistically optimistically update
the list in addition of the current
screen this is
also something that you can do with the
recovery and thanks to the set query
data
function
and now the last but not the least
feature i would like to discuss with you
today is the cache persistence in the
async storage
uh this is great when you want to store
all the cache data
into the async storage so when your
users are going back to your app you
will have all of this data already
populated in your screens
so it's a very snappy ux and it's also
very nice when you want to to implement
offline mode support
so uh to uh
to activate this feature you have to um
use
some new experimental racquery features
so in the app components we call this
function and this function will need
persistor it's
a custom function
we'll use the new persisquery client
function and then you create a sync
storage persistor
so
it's very straightforward this person's
correct client
just receive a query client a persister
and
uh value to to know when the persis
query client has to burst the cache so
here we want to
clean the cache when the application
version has changed so we are sure that
uh we don't uh we we won't reuse uh data
that can have changed according to a new
api exchange
or
about a new changes in our components so
we want to to burst the cache
uh
when uh
when the app version has changed
and that's it
this is actually what you have to do to
persist your queries cache
data
enthusiasm storage is simple as is
so you can imagine oh simple now is to
persist
all of your queries cache by using this
very simple function here so it's a
great feature hopefully
it will be an official and stable
feature right now we have decided to use
this feature in production
and so far so good and we are so happy
and so excited to to use it because
again it's a
maybe 10 likes 10 lines of code just to
manage uh
this great
feature
as you can see
racquery is a great solution
especially in terms of developer
experience and features with very good
defaults
but how it compares to other popular
libraries
i think
all of the solutions i show you now are
great
you can create very nice and
sophisticated application with all of
this solution
so it's really a question about the
philosophy and the strategy you have uh
in your rank native app development and
also about the skills
of your team and what you want to do so
i think that two categories right now
there is the the universal data
featuring and caching approach and the
graphql set management frameworks
approach so requirey is on the first
category is something very universal you
just have to think about queries cache
optimistic updates
you don't have to think about the schema
and how your graphical api
schema is defined it's just queries and
just invalidate queries with variables
and so it's something very
straightforward and
uh
it's also you have a total control on
how your cache will be invalidated and
when so this is something which is can
be really
good for some team
because you have this very easy learning
curve but you can have very precise
configuration and for sophisticated
cases
in this category you have also swc
often used with neck gs and redox store
kit which is something more integrated
with redux if you like this approach
so racquery in this category
is is really great
and you have also to have in
consideration the community as a mentor
and
all the resources around like the
graphql gen plugin so for me is my
better
library
is my
preference choice in this category
on the other hand you have the state
management frameworks
with relay apollo client and oracle
i think relay it's the oldest one and
it's very mature but it's opinionated
about the schema
so it can be a show blocker in some
situation where you want to do
what you want about the schema and you
don't want to have some requirements
about the schema
you have created but if you respect the
rules
but really you have a really great
solution because it's you have all the
documentation all the features you just
have to follow
uh the rules of this framework and you
will have great results
apollo client is really nice and used to
use a lot of follow clients on other
projects and even in the
in the first version of our react native
app is very nice
again if you like the framework approach
and other very good
features uh that relies on your
graphql schema is nice it also relies on
the normalized cache i mean it will when
you do a mutation it will automatically
knows
which
data to update in other queries so it's
nice but there are a lot of edge cases
and again there is maybe a kind of
learning curve
when you
want to
to use all the possibilities of this
great uh apollo client framework
ercol it's something a little bit newer
compared to apollo climate and relay but
it's very nice because it provides both
document and normalized cache approaches
so i think it's great
maybe this is the one i prefer in this
category very close to apollo clients so
again
just uh have a look at the documentation
the the repo
a real life application example and just
decide first the approach you want is it
a universal one or you want maybe
something more optimized about your
graphql schema
and the last one is uh
gqls
so it's very very uh
interesting one because you don't have
to create
your query before you just have to code
uh your
your um
and to use your query and it will
automatically generate uh your graphql
query so it's brand new it's very
interesting maybe if you want to go very
fast
and don't bother with
creating
your graphql queries and mutation
elsewhere just
use
your query and it will automatically
generate
your graphql queries so i think it's a
great uh
a great new solution and we are very
lucky because the graphql ecosystem now
is so good with very good solutions that
we can just
decide which flavor
we prefer so it's a question of test and
team
and how you want to to manage your
recognitive project with with graphql
it's time now to share with you the
lessons we have learned during our
journey with ria curry
so first start your project with graphql
code generator
it's a game changer in terms of
developer experience and productivity
it's so fast so don't waste your time
by adding types and
hooks just use a graphical code chain
with the requirey plugin it's so fast
and the vs code extension is really nice
use custom hooks as possible to keep
your rack components logic clean even if
the use query used mutation are very
easy to use it is good to have this kind
of abstraction
so you can keep your rack components
really clean
when possible just use and have a single
source of truth for your
queries data
so you can use the initial data property
when uh it's relevant so it's great
because
your components just fetch some data
and this data can be set by initial data
or by an optimistic update or by a
graphql api but it will be the same
source of truth so try to to to have
only a single source of truth uh when it
comes with your data
always test with the network conditioner
because uh if not uh often your
connection is very fast and you don't
see exactly what is going on so if you
want to test loading screen errors and
just hold the optimistic updates behaves
just use the network conditioner as as
possible when you evaluate
your feature and your application
it's very easy as you have seen just
before to log everything
is happening in your cache and your
queries so
just monitor and especially at the
beginning to understand really how uh
recovery is working and when the data is
fetching
so it's it's a great solution to learn
and to debug
there is a
enable option in use query and we use
this a lot to manage dependent and
conditional queries so again it's a
great solution
and if you use
have a look at this option and you will
see a lot of use cases when you may need
to use this enable option
and
about suspense yes
suspense you know in terms of
productivity is great because it mean it
means less code in your components
but
in some situations you may need to have
more control about
the loading state or the error
management
so at one point you can be limited with
suspense
um
and so this is not a problem because uh
requery supports a lot of status
variables you can use to check very
precisely uh
what is the status of your query
what's coming next for us uh so we will
uh
work with requerry for full offline
support
so right now we have some limited uh sup
offline support features
and but i think real query will provide
all the features we need
to have this full of line support
and
the other point is graphq
graphql subscription supports
so right now it's possible but it's not
very well documented in the
in the current website so you have to
investigate a little bit there is a very
nice article
by dominic about using web sockets with
mercury a discussion in the repo but
we would like to to see more details and
more examples and
and best practices about
using graphql subscriptions with
recurring
so
again i was quite excited and happy to
to to speak at
rec native europe conference and i hope
that this talk will be useful and with a
lot of recipes and cod example and i
wish you a great conference and with the
very interesting talks
thank you
thank you arnold for your talk i'm
always happy to see people sharing their
first event experience of their
production application
i think we can all learn from that and
let's discuss this on our discord
channel
and next up is helena ford founder of
stack tiger and maintainer of a library
called notify and her talk will
allow us to take our notification game
to the next level helena the stage is
yours
hey everyone i'm helena ford and i'm the
cto of stat tiger a mobile dev agency in
the uk i've been working with react
native since the beginning and i'm an
active maintainer of notify a local
notification library by invites
you can find me at helena ford on
twitter and i have a blog 4.dev
today i'm going to give a quick demo and
talk about how you can exploit the full
power of notifications to increase user
engagement and retention
we'll cover get and start set up with
notify media support quick actions
scheduling user notifications and a few
other bits
personal notifications often require
third-party services like firebase to
operate however local notifications are
configured on the device itself and
allow you to get them up and running
without any such third parties a good
example is your alarm clock
that sends a local notification at
whatever time you set your alarm for
there are several react linkedin
libraries out there that can help you
configure these notifications one of
these which i'm going to talk about
today is notified by invitates
node fee enables developers to build
richmond creations with a simple api
whilst thinking of complex problems such
as scheduling background tasks device
api compatibility and more okay so let's
get into the code then so you see on the
screen an example project i prepared for
this demo
which is some tv shows
um just plain simple json data with a
display notification button
um and if we look here um
it's just plain button
on press
so what we want to do here
is
display a notification a local
notification
so before we even do that we should also
say
we would need to install the library
first of course so
i've already installed it for this
example but
if you can see my kernel here you can do
yarn art
add note free for slash react native
and then if you cd
into ios
pod install
that's all you need to do to
set up nooga fee
[Applause]
and i'm going to just get right in scope
so it's fairly straightforward
um
so
bait no
display notification
so
everything is typescript subconsciously
okay what does it expect to take
um we'll just start off with simple
python body hello world
world
and
android requires one extra step which is
a channel id
[Applause]
and we'll have to make it this i
normally just tend to go general
default
anything really you like but just be
keep in mind that the user will see
the name so when you create the channel
[Applause]
[Music]
create channel
[Applause]
the same id you pass it to the payload
so
and then
i mean so this is what the users see so
just keep it fitting
user friendly and then
importance okay so
this is probably one of the things that
rips people up the most
it which took me myself up to um
is if you want it to be a banner like a
headset
to go over the apps and not just like
hidden in the traditional tree when it
comes through is to do importance
of high
um
[Music]
also you can call create channel as many
pictures you want it's not really
an issue
um because android will just ignore if
it's already created um
but also remember once you've created
channel you can't
then update any of this properties
you have to delete it first and just
so if we go ahead and try to display
this
fingers crossed
it'll come up hello world
we haven't added we haven't specified a
notification
yet
but we can easily do that um small icon
spot icon
[Music]
and
you have to add this to your project
separately
which is
detailed
on the box page
i've added this earlier and it's just a
tv icon
you can give it any name that's just the
default name that address studio
uses
so
if we try to display the scan
you'll see now it has a tv notification
icon yay
so
that's basically part one
and next
we'll go into
making this bit more complicated so this
is probably like
what you know most apps can do title
body is pretty standard okay
okay so as you can see i specified a
large icon
um this is literally just a random url i
got off google
and it's a
png so
on android
you can
add a png.jpg
and it can be local or remote so this is
a remote url
you can also add like require through
here i tried to do an example of a local
and a remote one
so here's a local asset file
so if i look into here you can see i've
added some
i've added the image
and then some actions um
this is probably getting ahead of
ourselves but we're just taking it once
every time so
if i slowly start to build this up so if
i do a large icon
and then this url
just copy from here
i'm not going to type that out
okay
there you go so you can see the large
icons on the
right hand side
which is perfect it's what we want
so if i just swipe that way
and then we'll go
down into adding the big picture
so
on android this is thinker style so you
can have different types of styles
messaging
big picture inbox um
again
i don't really want to go into like
specifics of
um the api because it's all online
along the box but it's just to give
a feel of what you can do what is
possible so oh yeah
because i've taken it out of this farm
here it's not recognizing
it's at six
okay
so if i swipe down now on the
notification
you should see the picture
so this is the larger icon and then this
is styles and restart big picture
we should use
just like a local asset
and
if we now look at ios so on ios
they don't have channels but they do
require to request permissions
um
so for the civic demo i'll just add it
here
and
let's see we
got this permission
you can specify exactly what you want
but default is fine it will give you
the efficiency you need to display alert
that comes over there
so
i swiped up
and
i was
um so here we want to
show
a video
you can add images too
but this is the cool thing about
ios is that you can't have videos i've
been an example again of how you can do
the image which is pretty much identical
to
android
just the field is under attachments
on ios is you can add an array
so
it will if you have loads of images and
videos specified here it will let you
just go down the list in order
until um one can successfully
um
load
okay so let's just fill over the ios
emulator
and see what this video displays like
so let me say display notification okay
so this is the extra step there's way
different ways you can call this and all
where you can call it throughout your
app life cycle to be less intrusive to
the user but
demo processes let's just call it
straight away and
display the notification
okay so
yeah the first time it um loads it might
take some time to load if you've got big
files i've obviously not optimized this
video or anything you could also make a
gif which
probably speed it up
excuse me as well
and
you can play it
here you go
so
if i
um just quickly
take all this out
and actually see
what it would look like
with all the white text and everything
so new episodes great enough to me
absolutely
play
great
this isn't actually very useful though
to the end user
so now we can actually start going into
what
quick actions are so quick actions is a
cool way for your user to engage with
your app
without them actually having to be in
your app which is great if they're doing
something else and they see a
notification pop up they can quickly
interact
and
it's not it doesn't really affect what
they're doing
so
for android let's just we'd have to go
into the api a little bit um he accepts
an array of
actions
i press action which is an object and a
title so titles basically that enable
so we've got watch now and save later
and an id so id default notifi will know
this what you want when someone presses
on that you want the app to open
and id bookmark this is completely
whatever you want um in our case we want
to know we want the user to be able to
bookmark from a notification
so
before we actually
display this or we can display this and
show you the buttons won't do anything
much until we
add the event handlers to know okay user
has actually pressed
these buttons so
the first thing we need to do is
add
a background one
so
you just import notifications
[Applause]
okay
and then literally you've got
the background the back
is saying the expression
and this
will give you an event of type and
detail
so we can
quickly just print that out
to see what we get back from the event
handler
and this as the function is called
background this will only run when the
app is in background there's also an on
foreground event handler
um which we'll add
in a separate place
so
with the background event you'd always
want it to
be really here
before your apps loaded so
it's always there um and then the
foreground one you can pretty much
have it wherever you want
and i always try to put it in my when i
put it in my apps i always try to
put it when the app first renders um as
early as possible really is a while but
again that one really
anytime anywhere you want um
okay so
as we have two actions
um with these id this is what we want to
hook into
so
we can do if
type
equals equals event
dot action press um
not sure
well type script pick that up yeah
but action press
and
id
so we can get that from press action to
dpl
dot press action
for id
um
and
so if your user
presses
the default action
that will open up but also we'll have to
come to the notification so we'll just
do
notary.console notification
and give the id of the notification so
that's just detail
dot
notification dot id
we'll just demonstrate we can
demonstrate here but watch now
how we would use watch now
so we trigger this um
if this was a real world
up
out there in the world
this would be triggered when
you know the actual episode is about to
air
or it has been released
um so if you put that in the background
and then hopefully our background
handler will pick up this event which is
what we want i want to cancel it
when the app opens
and if you look down in my terminal
you will see
that
you can see all these events coming
through um
if i
do this to make it more
more easier to detect
two is press action
and you can see it's coming through from
the background
next we'll add a foreground of a handler
so
this can go like i said can you go
anyway
i always do it this way i'll use the
fact when my app is just rendered
or loaded
and
um he
bought
on the foreground event
and it exactly the same as the
background one so we have a type and
detail
[Applause]
of the event
we always want to make sure we're
returning that so it's unsubscribed
after the app is
unmounted
and then in here we want to do the same
as what we did in the background one so
you want to do if
and just copy that
put it here
and port event type
and this needs to be brick marker
and we want to set
so our user has actually bookmarked this
this episode or tv show
so what we want to do here is actually
set up the state of bookmarks
um so the user can see that they booked
back this
okay so all we need to do is to set
the max
and then the id which we will get from
data you could
set your notification id to match the
show id but
you could also do data
um i don't have it here because if you
wanted to
say have two notifications upgrades and
that's me
you might if you just used show id that
would restrict you um
so if we just get it from data the
notification so
also
um just to explain
this
every property in data needs to be a
string so
dot
notification
this could be anything any custom copy
um
this isn't a
number anymore you pass it
um
okay so
[Music]
if we try that
we should see
grey's anatomy a big man
awesome so that's android next we have
ios which if i just bring that in
quickly so on ios
it works a little bit different but also
very similar to android so if you it
takes in a category id so rather than
like
specifying the quick actions inside the
notification payload
you have to create this category
beforehand
and it can be like a one-time thing so
you have to create the categories all at
once together
i tend to do this again in the use
effect um
just when the app first match
but it's totally up to you
we could also do it in when we click
display notification
it really doesn't matter that much um so
if i just write about the native
function
and call it
so in here wait no you've got set
notification copies this is the ios
function only but
on android with numerically you'll just
ignore this
so you don't have to worry about
wrapping it in a condition condition
check the platform
so category so it's basically the same
as this except for
without the press action object you just
need an id so i'd be
basalt
and python
watching
so if you go into actions
[Applause]
so i got this i mean new accent
new episode is the one category we got
um
we wanna basically want it to be the
same watch now
same old android and ios you can also do
it differently um
and then
the next action for this category
is
bookmark which is the most important one
probably
um
okay so
and then our foreground event will
be cut i'll request performances
okay let's give this a whiz
let's play notification
we drag down see the actions click save
later
and things first yeah
it's updated to be bookmarked
yay
foreground true so this is actually
important
so these little um
little differences between andrew and i
asked like
documented on our
thing so if you do trip up you just go
to the docs you'll see that
um or ask for help on the github get
help we post policing
um easiest way to get in touch with us
who maintain notably is just quickly do
a get issue or look through and see if
anyone else has the same issue
probably they have um
but yeah
more than have to answer any questions
um on there
so let me try this again display
notification
put it up in the background
use a notification
watch now yeah so yeah don't forget to
do the foreground trick
now we'll go on to scheduling so now
we've seen quick questions about android
on ios and how they can
help the user engage without
more
we go into scheduling
so next we move on to scheduling so
this is really useful if for like
calendar apps allow notifications
um
anything really that you want to
plan ahead
alert the user ahead of time
and
these are not great and then normally
you normally ask to use it beforehand if
they want these notifications so like
for example in our skeleton now it's on
tv show so
if i just get right into it if you click
on grey's anatomy
or
ozark which is the
payload already designed for this um
you can ask okay would you like a
reminder when this show is back to a
10 minutes before one day before
do you want it to be repeat repeated
every monday at 8pm
um but for this stuff i would just say
time is before
ozark is aired
please let me know set reminder
at the moment this button
doesn't do anything
so let's go ahead and
[Music]
give it something to do
okay
so we want in here to start to create
our
[Music]
figure notifications
so we'll import notified here
so this
makes it a notification so what the
notification wants to we want to look
like our payload and the trigger so when
do we want this to be scheduled into the
future so
um i already have this setup to in
my notifications. also this will be
available online so
go back to it
this is exactly the same as the
notification i showed above with the new
episode but instead it's just a
different show
different image and
slightly different quick actions
um
we've got default
smith's default
um
and yeah a different category idea on
ios which will have the same actions but
the other thing is i do have this here
which is slightly jumping ahead of the
demo
um
but yeah
i'm this
so we will trigger type there are
multiple um trigger types
for this one we're just going to do
timestamp eightfold is more if you want
to like alarm and
you want to notify the user every five
minutes after they press snooze
or you want to count down like okay
trigger in 60 seconds
that's what info is great for time
sounds more great for
an actual date and time
so if we do timestamp
and for the demo we'll just go ahead and
say we want trigger in three seconds
rather than
monday at 8pm
so
which might be
um five seconds one time you're watching
this right now but for me it's not so
i'm just gonna go ahead and
[Applause]
create a date but it's gonna be
three seconds into the future
and we go ahead and just add that date
then as the time is done
[Applause]
okay
i also need to import this which is the
payload to the right
okay and we should be good to go um
i think that's literally all you need oh
that everything we're doing android
first so yeah don't need to create the
category at the moment
and
yeah that's all we're going to be doing
so
we're just going to be dismissing it or
default
for the dismiss
this is just like okay i don't need i
appreciate the
reminder but i don't want to look in the
app right now
i'm just going to get ready for my tv
show so
we can actually
when they click dismiss we can actually
cancel that so if we
update our event handler
let's cancel this for them
otherwise they can spec it out ahead of
time so this is gonna be a ten minute
reminder ahead of the episode so they
could browse up
get the app ready if they're not eager
to watch the show
the um reminder
and close the model
you should get a notification yeah here
you go oh sorry about the beginning 10
minutes are you ready grab the popcorn
okay great
um and there's an option dismiss or see
more
if we
for double reasons put this in the
background
you see that anything
it's not clear i'm not sure
hi
um
i think
did i start something wrong oh i know
why this is it's because i put that up
in the background but this is what i'm
saying about this is the awful grand
event
i can quickly just put this logic into
the background event
and
i already have one of you actually
just doing it again
you could also
just um
okay is it default or dismissed
basically any id that you want to cancel
you could just
have to put them there
i think i'm gonna have to
every time you update the background
handler you you have to make sure your
app updates um
and we'll do that now
and we put the app in the background
and just hit dismiss
yeah it cancels okay
great
so let me open up that
so that concludes that's a quick
brief look at scheduling
um but it really opens up a lot of stuff
you can do without a database like
remote notifications just within the
device itself um
so that's pretty cool
and
i haven't even encountered this i have
not even come to half stuff you can do
this is just i think
the features that i think are most
useful like
that are more
i probably gonna be used to the most
about different types of apps so images
um videos
scheduling there's also loads of stuff
you can do like timers
the code for this demo is live on github
so go ahead and try it out if anyone has
any questions feel free to reach out to
me
notifies free for development and full
production a license is required on
android but invites has been kind enough
to offer 100 free licenses using code
rneu
i'm helena ford thank you so much hope
you enjoyed the brief intro to local
notifications in react native
thank you helena for showing us the ins
and outs of this notification library
i'm going to check that right after our
conference today which is now because
our conference is ending that was our
last speaker
please join our discord channel to
discuss all today's talks and interact
with other react native freaks uh thank
you for staying with us for the whole
day uh we really appreciate it thank you
uh to all the speakers for the great
talks
and i hope we'll see each other tomorrow
at the same time we have a great lineup
of talks prepared for you
see you tomorrow then
this conference is brought to you by
codestack react and react native
development experts
[Music]
you